in 1713 the Englishman magazine issued a
new word into the English language or re
it was taken from the name of the earl
of re who put up the money to build a
machine like this
a mechanical depiction of the Earth's
movement in the solar system
the motion of the universe itself laid
bare by Isaac Newton's work on gravity
and cosmology had been put into
miniature order an age of reason was
attempting to bring order to everything
around it and in the 18th and 19th
centuries a series of self-appointed
authorities tried to tame the unruly
English language it was a heavyweight
contest
the age of reason which began in the
late 17th century was born out of years
of massive political upheaval in Britain
it had seen civil war during which the
King left London and set up court here
at Christ's Church College Oxford the
war made familiar such words and phrases
as round head and Cavalier plunder
iconoclast cabal regicide Lord Protector
Common Wealth restoration papist
nonconformist keep your powder dry and
warts and all a lexicon of faction and
dispute often mortal
the philosopher John Locke was educated
here at Christ Church and lived through
this turmoil he developed his greatest
work in the 1670s an atheist an essay
concerning human understanding in it he
argued that better use of language could
put an end to disputes and factionalism
if the definition of words could be
agreed and misunderstanding avoided
peace would naturally follow it's a
wonderful example of rational idealism
did John Locke a man of such supreme
intelligence really believe that by
getting the language clear and the
arguments stripped to basic simplicity's
then as he put it
disputes would end of themselves clearly
he did there is blind faith here at the
heart of what seems pure reason it's a
fascination in this story though the men
of Locke's calibre did think that in
effect language was the master of life
perhaps it could rule everything
Locke was a member of the Royal Society
founded in 1660 to promote what we call
science but they called physico
mathematical experimental learning they
tried to write pure and simple English
to avoid what they described as this
vicious abundance of phrase this
volubility of tongue at the time learn
ed books were usually written in Latin
because Latin was understood
internationally and was regarded as more
precise the members of the Royal Society
wanted to make English a fit language
for scholars and English began to make
inroads into the territory of Latin
Newton had published his Principia
Mathematica in 1687 in Latin but in 1704
his optics was published written in
English a new kind of rational English
larded with terms of inquiry and
argument I proceeded by this analysis to
discover and prove the original
differences of the rays of light in
respect of refrán ability reflects
ability and color and their alternative
fits of easy reflection and easy
transmission and the properties of body
is both a Paik and pellucid on which
their reflections and colors depend
here was a new vocabulary of reason and
investigation refrán ability and reflex
ability were words coined by Newton to
allow him to describe his experiments
with refraction and reflection
transmission had been used before to
mean passing from one place to another
Newton changed its meaning to describe
passing through a medium and opaque had
met unlit for 200 years before the 17th
century changed it to mean not allowing
the passage of light the word Lenz had
only been coined a decade before Newton
use it in his book and as he reported
his observations he also gave English
the terms in distinctness and well
defined the scholars were reframing
redefining and refashioning the language
they made it part of their apparatus and
there's another word that took on its
meaning is the equipment for an
experiment during this period
there appeared to be a growing and
general confidence in the state of
English printing presses were no longer
licensed and they it spread and
proliferated for the first time daily
newspapers would be printed and
circulated reports of events around the
globe went into the hands of ordinary
people the fashionable meeting places of
the day were the coffee houses it was in
places like this that people read and
talked about the news this one sold
coffee until just a decade ago now it
serves up stronger fur printed English
and become part of the fabric of daily
life as it had never been before here's
the first issue of the daily current for
March the 11th 1700 and too the news
comes from the wall of the Spanish
Succession that the French have sent
over 20,000 troops to Italy there was a
massive appetite for this news shows of
Addis until the readers of his magazine
The Spectator the different papers
cooked to the same news in different
ways and that no one could bear to leave
coffee houses like this one before they
read all the different versions but
coexisting with the exuberance of grub
Street and the coffeehouses possibly as
a result of it there was a deep anxiety
about the state of the English language
there was no royal society here
protecting English from vicious
abundance of phrase and vulnerability of
tongue there was no John Locke pressing
the case for agreed definitions and
clarity of meaning the greatest worry
was that English itself was changing the
poet Geoffrey Chaucer was still revered
three centuries up to he'd written the
canterbury tales but by then he'd become
difficult to understand the satirist
Jonathan Swift writer of a series of
bogus trouble Diaries we know today as
Gulliver's Travels voiced his concern
how then shall any man be able to
undertake his work with spirit and
cheerfulness when he considers that in
an age or two he shall hardly be
understood without an interpreter the
aristocracy couldn't be relied on to set
the example Swift hated the vulgar
liberties as he saw it that they were
taking with the English language the way
they clipped vowels out of words or
abbreviated them
for reputation pause for positive incog
for incognito and the one that survives
a standard English today mob from the
Latin mobile a bogus the common people
in coffeehouse society elegant English
was supposed to consist of long Latinate
words these shortenings were considered
crude and swift also hated what he
thought of as merely modish words like
banter bubble bully cutting shuffling
Parman and Shan Swift found a model in
the classical languages Latin in Greek
those languages that was thought had
survived because they never changed they
were carved in stone Swift would save
English by arresting it putting an end
to changes he would take control of
English and take it away from the
anarchy of the upper-class Bloods on
their slang in 1712 swift proposed the
foundation of an academy for correcting
improving and ascertaining the English
tongue the Academy would replace the
aristocracy ascertain was the big word
English was to be fixed ascertained
forever no matter that the French
Italians already had academies that had
failed to halt changes in their
languages Swift's determination was
ferocious one critic sneered that he was
attempting the impossible and he said
may as well set up a society to find out
the grand alexia the perpetual motion
the lowly to does to fix our language
beyond our own times well it was wrong
about longitude Swift even took this
case to court and proposed his scheme to
Queen Anne saying that only classical
English would endure to report her glory
but she died two years later and her
place on the throne was taken by George
the first the German king who spoke
little English and cared about it even
less Swift's plans were dead
but English fielded another champion an
intimidating scholar the monarch of
London widths a beacon of his age a
savage melancholic and like Isaac Newton
and effortless eccentric he lived and
created his master work in this house in
Goff Square just off Fleet Street in
London
Camby are came dr. Samuel Johnson when
his great dictionary
he thought he could write it in three
years when it was put to him that it had
taken 40 Frenchmen 40 years to compile
their dictionary he replied 40 times 40
s 1600 as 3 to 1600 so is the proportion
of an Englishman to a Frenchman
in fact it took him seven years and this
is where he did it in this Garret on the
top floor of this house he fed material
43,000 words and definitions etymologies
and quotations showing how they were
used to six assistants who wrote them
down
Johnson's achievement with the
dictionary was immense and immensely
idiosyncratic he left out proper names
he included obsolete words if they were
found in authors not obsolete and was
criticized for including archaic words
such as Digg l'addition cubicle Larry in
Kompas ability job an owl and opinio
tree he confessed to omitting words he
couldn't explain because he didn't
understand them in a manner which would
enrage and amaze all future
lexicographers he acknowledged that many
terms of art manufacture and trade are
emitted but for this defect I'm a bold
the allege it was unavoidable I could
not visit cabins to learn the minds
language nor take a voyage to perfect my
skill in the dialect of navigation his
dictionaries lacking in the areas of law
medicine and the physical sciences he
left out rude words and went to society
ladies asked him why he responded what
my dears then you've been looking for
them
the dick show is finally published in to
failure volumes in 1755 and this is it
with all his emissions and banishment
sits a wonder that the dictionary
carried any weight at all in fact it
carried immense Authority and also
served a purpose of national prime that
English literature could boast such a
mighty engine of words and through the
genius not of a French committee but of
an English individual we like that and
the personality of that individual
shines through willful prejudiced and
learn it the dictionary becomes an
autobiography a portrait of an age and a
book that remains entertaining way
beyond its useful life as a tool though
it has to be admitted that as a tool it
doesn't stand up by modern standards
some of its etymologies accounts of the
origins of words are questionable and
its definitions don't always shed light
cough a convulsion of the lungs
medicated by some sharp serosa tea and
dross
he says the recomment or desperation of
metals sometimes they're biased or
inaccurate oops he describes as a grain
which in England is generally given to
horses but in Scotland supports the
people tarantula is an insect whose bite
is only cured by music doll he says he's
not exhilarating not delightful as to
make dictionaries his dull work when he
began his work he sounded very much like
the inheritor of Swift's great plan the
idea here was to make a dictionary by
which the pronunciation of our language
may be fixed it's used as attained and
its duration lengthen but after he
worked on the dictionary and come to
write the purpose his pragmatism and his
honesty so a rueful but radical change
of mind English wasn't going to be tied
down no dictionary Johnson added could
embalm a language and preserve it from
corruption and decay implying that for
Johnson like swift change was still for
the worse but I think there's something
to celebrate in the end of the idea of
trying to fix the meaning of words
English would never be lashed down and
the power of its freedom gave it I think
an extra cylinder when it came up
against the obstacle or the
opposition of other languages
goat a ruminant animal that seems a
middle species between deer and sheep
electric attractive without magnet the
Trillium is a literate virtual lab
floating on the water of spring
enthusiasm a vain belief of private
regulation lexicon vain confident a
writer of dictionaries a harmless Drudge
Johnson's work won both brickbats and
Garland's but it was rarely ignored
there was praise from the two European
countries which had established
academies to regulate their language
Italy in France a French Journal
declared that Johnson himself was an
academy for this island and although it
didn't fix forever the meaning or in
Swift in Johnson's word ascertain a
single word the dictionary is still read
and enjoyed in all its eccentric dusty
glory the second half of the 18th
century was an age when nature itself
was being put into classical order by
landscape gardeners like William Kent
here at Gresham in Oxfordshire and a
host of grammarians led by Robert laughs
wanted to do the same to the English
language from now on things were
different from but certainly not
different to the old individual freedoms
in some ways they added clarity in other
ways they created pedantry between you
and I was outlawed between you and me
was now the only way comparatives were
to be used with a pair of objects and
superlatives with more the better of two
but the best of three in comparables
like perfect unique or round weren't to
be qualified so you should no longer be
more unique or less perfect lie and lay
we distinguished from each other as were
will and shall perhaps surprisingly
louth recognize that a preposition was
permissible to end a sentence with
though avoiding it was more elegant but
we're two ways of using language existed
one must be wrong they carved a single
path through the thickets of English
grammar and they began to turn their
attention to the cavalry there were
attempts to ban popular words and
phrases words such as fib banter bigot