In 1077 William the Conquerer, ruler of
Normandy in England ordered
the construction of a special building.
It was to be part Palace, part Treasury,
part prison and part fortress.
It was the White Tower on the banks of the Thames in London.
And it was a powerful symbol
of the way that the Normans were
imposing themselves on this conquered country.
They hadn't just brought armies
and architecture to mark their authority,
that also brought their language.
The French vocabulary of power forced
its way into the English language. "crown" and
"court" were both French words. So are "castle"
and "tower" and the "Barons" who built them.
And so are "obedience" and "justice" "treason" and "prison".
The Anglo-Saxon Kings had
governed using the Old English language,
now the Normans used French and Latin.
English had become the third language in
its own country, it would take over 300
years to emerge from the shadows.
In the years following the arrival of
Williams army at Pevensey, the Normans
tightened their grip on England,
now part of a kingdom that extended across the channel.
Across the land William's men
took over every position of power
in the state and in the church.
Within 60 years, the monk and historian William of
Moultrie could write: "no English one
today is an Earl or Bishop or Abbot,
the newcomers gnaw at the wealth and guts of
England, nor is there any hope of ending the misery".
He wrote in Latin.
Written English which had managed to establish
itself so boldly before the conquest was now dying.
It breathed its last here.
Now Peterborough Cathedral, in the mid-12th century,
part of Peterborough Abbey.
??? two oxen ??? to
the king and he ??? him but ???.
Around the country monks had been
recording the great events of
the last 650 years in books
known as the Anglo-Saxon chronicles.
They were written in the language of
the people : English.
And there was nothing like them
anywhere in mainland Europe.
??? ??? ???
Since the Norman conquest of 1066
these unique accounts
had been abandoned one by one.
The Peterborough Chronicle was the last survivor.
In 1154 a monk recorded that
the abbey had a new Abbot, a man with a
very French name of William de Waterville.
?? chosen ??? named
William de Waterville
his ??? good ??? and good man and
??? ??? begun. "He has made a good
beginning" the monk writes. "Christ is he ???
" Christ grant that he may end as well".
With this last entry six and a half
centuries of written history came to an end.
Old English had ceased to be the
language of record in the land.
But that didn't mean that it was going to go away.
Since the conquest English in varying
dialects had remained the language
spoken by 90% of the population,
from the south coast to the uplands of southern Scotland
just a few miles north of here.
Even further north in Scotland and
west in Wales the culture and language
were still Celtic.
Old English had continued to develop and change partly
as a result of contact with the language
of the date particularly here in the north.
The grammar was becoming simpler,
more plurals were being formed by adding
an s. "Naman" for example the Old English
plural of "name" became "nam-es", which would
become our "names". Prepositions were
performing more of the functions of the
old word endings and word order was
becoming more fixed. Despite being the
officially ignored language, English
would continue to evolve and change and
it would endure resisting and absorbing
the invaders language until the time
came free to resume centre stage as a nation's language.
The Peterborough chronicle of 1154 also
recorded that in that year the people of
England acquired a new king : Count Henry of Anjou,
grandson of William the Conqueror,
and the first of the Plantagenet Kings.
A lover of learning he spoke fluent Latin as well as French but no English.
And the English acquired
a new Queen : Eleanor of Aquitaine,
the daughter of William X (the tenth) of Aquitaine.
Henry II was crowned here in
Westminster Abbey in a lavish ceremony.
The clergy wore silk vestments that were
more costly than anything ever seen
before in England. The King and Queen and
the great Barons wore silk and brocade robes.
The luxury was fitting,
s
it was thought, for an occasion that solemnised
the bringing together of so much land and wealth.
Henry brought his inheritance of William
the Conqueror's land in England and
northern France.
Eleanor, the greatest heiress
in the Western world, brought with her a great sway
that what is now France
from the Loire to the Pyrenees,
from the Rhone to the Atlantic.
This was a huge Kingdom.
The greater part of it made up of French-speaking lands across the channel.
As it grew the English lands and the English language
became an ever less significant part of it.
French and Latin were even more
firmly entrenched as the languages of
the court and government of the country.
Yet after their coronation,
Henry and Eleanor rode in procession along the
Strand and it's reported that the people
shouted "Wes hal!" and "Vivat Rex", wishing
them long life in English and in Latin.
English was still alive in the streets.
In the court and royal palaces
new ideas from across the channel were in the air.
And new words to express them,
words which ???, of "courtesy"(cortesie) and "honor"(honor),
"questing" and "damsels"(damesieles), "jousting" and "tournaments"(torneiement),
French words everyone.
The macabre romance and chivalry was heard in England
???
Eleanor， England's new queen was
considered the most cultured woman in Europe.
It was she more than any other
who patronized the poets and troubadours
whose verses and songs created the
romantic image of the Middle Ages
as the age of chivalry, a glorious vision that
was never realized outside the pages of Medieval literature.
A hundred years before,
the word "chevalerie" formed around
the word for horse had simply meant cavalry.
It was the fierceness of the mounted warriors
that had carried the day for
the Normans at Hastings.
And since then many English peasants had come to know
the mounted Norman soldiers
as little more than thugs and bullies
who run the country by force.
But now mounted warriors had become Knights
and the word "chivalry" came to
mean a whole model of ideas and behavior.
Infused with honor and altruism,
one that prescribed how to act towards
one's liege-lord, ones friends and
enemies, and of course fair, cruel ladies.
Ideas had shifted, and words with them.
It was in Eleanor's reign that French writers
brought the stories of Arthur
and his Knights out of the history books
and into poetry, cultivating a language
far richer and subtler than the one that
the first Norman settlers had spoken and written.
The poet's rhapsodize about Eleanor,
celebrating her as
the most beautiful woman in the world.
Pouring out the impossible longing for the perfect woman
that was at the heart of the cult of courtly love.
The poetry of affairs of the heart
had come to England, singing a pain and joy
and beginning a line in literature
that runs through Shakespeare's sonnets
and the great Romantic poets to
today's three-minute pop lyrics.
Oh, my love，my darling,
I've hungered for your touch
A long lonely time.
Shit
Meanwhile England's native inhabitant  [BREAK]
That song was first recorded in 1225,
making it one of the earliest pieces of English
that's still recognizable today.
There's not a single French word in it.
Words like "summer" "come" "sew" "seed" and "nu" can be
traced right back to the flatlands of Frisia.
"spring" and "wood" can be found in the
Anglo-Saxon poem Beowulf and "merry" "sing"
and "loud" in the works authorized by Alfred the Great.
There's a pure line of
Old English vocabulary here in a song
that comes from the peasants and the land
at the opposite end of the social scale from the troubadour songs.
The French language of the Grand Lord hasn't
penetrated down to the common people.
Certainly the native English and
the French overlords live very different lives.
William the Conqueror had
introduced the system of feudalism into England,
and though evolving,
it still defined all economic and social relations,
expressed in French words like
"villain" and "vassal", "laborer", "bailiff" and "factor".
In the country where 95% of
the population lived, the English were
essentially "serfs", another French word.
Not technically slaves, but tied for life
to their Lords estate which they worked for him,
and at a subsistence level for themselves.
While the English-speaking
peasants lived in small cottages or huts,
their French-speaking masters live
privileged lives in their castles.
Our modern vocabulary still reflects
the distinction between them.
English speakers tended the living cattle which
we still call by the Old English words
of "ox" or "cow". French speakers ate the
prepared meat which came to the table
which we call by the French word "beef".
In the same way the English "sheep" became
a French "mutton", "calf" became "veal",
"deer" "venison" and "pig" "pork".
English animal, French meat in every case.
The English laboured, the French feasted.
Where English underlings and
French masters lived and worked together,
the boundaries between their languages
inevitably wore away, and the vocabularies
??? countryside mingle.
For example a local man would have been
involved in the training and flying of a nobleman's hawks.
And some now common words have come to us from for falconry.
The word "Falcon" itself comes from French.
As there's a "leash" which refer to the
strip of material used to secure the bird.
And "block" on which the bird stood.
Our word "codger" comes from the often elderly man
who assisted the falconer by carrying
the hawks on a "cadge" or cage;
"Bate" described the bird beating its wings and
trying to fly away;
"check" meant at first refusing to come to the fist.
Our word "lure" comes from the leather device
still used in training and recalling the hawk.
"Quarry" was the reward given to
the Falcon for making a kill.
When a bird moulted it was said to "mew" and from that
came the name of the buildings where Hawks were kept : "Mews".
Today that name can
still be seen attached to streets or(???) estate agents
rather than hawks hunt(???) their quarry.
We've just heard 9 French words that
came into English from one activity alone.
Steadily French vocabulary was pouring over English.
The French influence on the English language as a
whole is enormous in terms of vocabulary,
not in terms of grammar, but in terms of
a vocabulary, it's unmatched by any other language.
For example "fruit" replaces the
old English "wæstm", pretty quickly at
within a space of about 40 or 50 years,
"wæstm" simply isn't used.
But the majority of words don't replace
the Old English, they stand side by side with them.
So we have word like "apple" in Old English,
meant any kind of fruit.
Whereas what happens is because "fruit" comes in
and is basically expresses that
"apple" starts to mean a very specific sort of a fruit.
I think it's not true to say that
generally speaking French words came
into the language and ousted the Old English words out of it.
Generally what seems to happen
is that the the Old English words
simply narrows in meaning.
It was now almost 150 years since the Norman Conquest.
Though the people at the top had changed,
the ascendancy of French was still absolute.
Written English, that triumphant achievement of Alfred and
English scholars was dead.
And spoken English was being progressively
colonized throughout society by French words.
But the balance of power and of languages was about to shift.
Of course early 13th century English society consisted of more than
English peasants grubbing the land and
French-speaking nobility lording it in their castles.
Trade was on the increase,
The wool trade, in particular, made part of England rich.
On the proceeds grand churches were built,
Even in small villages like this one, at Northleach in the Cotswolds.
Services would of course be conducted in Latin.
Towns were growing, sometimes French and
English towns together as at Norwich and Nottingham
Then as now London was the magnet.
Its population would double in the course of the 13th century.
As feudalism loosened its grip,
English speakers would flood in
from the country looking for opportunities,
a better life.
Already established with
the French-speaking court officials,
administrators, lawyers and merchants,
but also craftsmen who gave us the French
names for some tools of the trade:
"measure" "mallet" "chisel" "pulley" "bucket"  "trowel".
This is petit France in London,
it's name shows that it originally housed
a community of French immigrants.
In the early Middle Ages, there were areas like
this in many English towns,
home to craftsmen and merchants who'd come here from Normandy.
English and French speakers met and mingled in these places
and the English middle classes picked up
French words by the thousand.
"merchant", "money", "price", "discount", "bargain", "contract",
"partner", "embezzle".
The English didn't just borrow French vocabulary they took their names.
Then as now names were a matter of fashion,
and the fashion in the early 13th century was for French.
So out went the good Old English Ethelbert
Aelfrics, Athelstans, Dunstans, Wulfstans and Wulfrics.
And in came the newfangled Richards and Roberts
Simons and Stephens Jones Jeffries,
and most popular of all Williams.
It seemed that everywhere French was the name of the game.
If this process had continued well by
French percolated and penetrated into
every area of English society,
then French could eventually have engulfed English.
That didn't happen, why not ?
One critical reason was that because of
particular historical events，
French speakers in England became cut off from
their cultural and linguistic roots.
In 1204, the reigning Monarch John,
King of Normandy Aquitaine and England,
lost his Norman lands in a war with a much smaller kingdom of France.
The Norman dukedoms, ancestral lands of William the Conqueror
and cultural homelands were part of another Empire now.
As long as the French nobility and
middle classes who live in England kept
contact with their homelands in Normandy
as long as they thought of themselves as French
and married within French families,
their identity and language were secure.
When they lost their connections across the channel,
their language began to lose its grip on English.
One thing that happened was that
French speakers, even within the noblest families,
began to look for wives
not from across the channel but in England.
They married English speakers,
and in doing so they married, as it were,
into the English language as well.
It said that the hand that rocks the cradle rules the world.
It's likely that by the middle of the 13th century,
many children in families
which would previously have been French-speaking,
were learning English from their mothers or nurses.
???
Now that many of the
children of Anglo-French marriages grew up
bilingual, perhaps speaking one
language to the servants in the castle
kitchen and another at dinner in the
Great Hall. By 1250 there's even
some evidence that children of the
nobility were having to learn French
from a written primer grappling with the
vocabulary of what was becoming
effectively a foreign language by the
middle of the thirteenth century. More
and more French speakers throughout
society with themselves beginning to
speak English, becoming bilingual. the
result was that while French itself
became more of a foreign language. French
vocabulary French words continued to
stream into English. Many more words are
recorded after 1250 than before ： "abbey"
"attire" "sensor" "defend" "figure" "malady" "music"
"parson" "plea" "sacrifice" "scarlet" "spy" "stable"
"virtue" "Marshall" "Park" "rain" "beauty" "clergy"
"cloak" "country" "fool"
and because French was the international language of trade，
it acted as a conduit
for words from the markets of the East.
Arabic words that gave to the English
"saffron" "mattress" "hazard" "camphor" "alchemy"
"lute" "amber" and "syrup"
Our phrase "checkmate" comes through French from the
Arabic "shah mat" - the king is dead.
As we've heard very often the imports didn't
replace existing English words but
settled down with them,
each word adopting a slightly different meaning.
The same thing had happened with English
and Old Norse, this layering effect,
re
So a young English "hare" came to be named by the French word "leveret",
English "swan" French "signet",
a small English "axe" is a French "hatchet",
"ask" English and "demand" from French have slightly different meanings
as do "bit" and "morsel", "wish" and "desire"
"might" and "power", "room" and "chamber".
On the surface some of these words
appear to be interchangeable and
sometimes they are.
But more interestingly there are fine differences,
that's the beauty of it.
"answer" is not quite "respond"
"begin" isn't always "commence", "liberty" isn't always "freedom".
Shades of meaning representing new shades of thought
were massively absorbed into our language at that time.
The range of what I would call almost synonyms
became one of the glories of
English, contributing to the languages
precision and flexibility, allowing its
speakers and writers over the centuries
to select very precisely the right word.
Rather than replace English, French was
helping equip and enrich the language
for the central role that it was on its
way to reassuming.
Towards the end of the 13th century
a new idea of the English people is being born,
the Norman lands across the channel
were a foreign country now,
even the families who traced their roots back to
William the Conqueror's Norman followers,
men with French names and French blood
started calling themselves trueborn Englishman.
Behind me is the tomb of Edward I
- the hammer of the Scots,it says there in Latin.
Latin was the language of
official business, but when the French
King Philip threatened invasion of England in 1295,
Edward used the English language
as a symbol of nationhood to galvanize support
"If Philip is able to do
all the evil he means to from which
God protect us,
he plans to wipe out our English
language entirely from the earth" he said.
The old language reborn could now be a
rallying point for a new mongrel people.
The invasion never came,
and though Edward made the English language
a symbol for the country,
he didn't elevate it to official use,
Latin and French were still the languages of state affairs
It was Edward's direct ancestor
William the Conqueror who more than two
centuries before had enshrined Latin and French
as a written languages of state,
banishing English.
But as the 13th century gave way to the 14th,
English was becoming the one
language out of the three that everyone
in the country could be counted on to know.
In 1325 for instance, the
chronicler William of Nassington
could write : "Latin can no one speak, as I trowe
But those wit from school do know.
And some know French but not Latin,
who used to court and dwell therein.
and some know Latin though just in part
whose use of French is less than art
and some can understand English
who neither Latin nor French
but unlettered or learned, old or young,
all understand the English tongue. "
The bestiary in which birds and animals were
portrayed and their behavior made the
basis for lessons in Christian morality
was a particular medieval form.
They were usually written as here in Latin,
but in a late 13th century example
the text is not in Latin but it English
the wild deer has two properties
he draws out the Viper from the stone
with his nose and swallows it
a venom causes the deer to burn and he rushes to the water
the devil is like the whale
he tempts men to follow their sinful lusts
and in return they find ??.
It is the weak in faith the little ones
that he thus beguiles
And it was an animal
which in just a few years time, would by
a cruel twist of fate, give English its
greatest boost yet, a small black rodent
with a Latin name
Rattus Rattus the black rat.
In 1348 ancestors of these black rats deserted a
ship that coming from the continent had
docked near Weymouth they carried a
deadly cargo a germ then modern science
calls Pasteurella pestis that the 14th
century named the great pestilence and
that we know is the Black Death plague
had come to Britain infected rats
carried the deadly germ East than North
they sought out human habitations
building nests in the flaws climbing the
wattle and daub walls shedding the
infected fleas that fed on their blood
and transmitted bubonic plague
this is Asheville in Hertfordshire in
the bell tower of the church some
desperate soul perhaps the parish priest
scratched a poignant record on the wall
in bad Latin
the first pestilence was in 1350 - 11350
pitiless wild violent only the dregs of
the people live to tell the tale
the dregs were those of the
english-speaking peasantry who'd
survived though the black death was a
human catastrophe it's setting trend a
series of social upheavals which would
speed the English language along the
road to full restoration as the real and
recognized language of the nation for
one thing the Black Death dealt Latin
the language of the church a body blow
where people live communally as the
clergy did in monasteries and other
religious orders the incidence of
infection and death was
disproportionately high at a local level
many parish priests either caught the
plague from tending their parishioners
or simply ran away as a result of the
plague the Latin speaking clergy in some
parts of England were reduced by almost
a half
many of their replacements were barely
literate layman whose only language was
English
the England after the Black Death was a
very different place in many parts of
the country
those hardly anyone left to work the
land or tender livestock the acute
shortage of labour meant that those who
did the work had the power to break from
their feudal past and demand better
conditions higher wages times were
changing
wages rose the price of property fell
working people seize the opportunities
they've never had before the fortunes of
the common people were changing they
were rising through society and they
took their English with them
by 1385 English had replaced French in
the schoolroom and his education and
literacy spread so did the demand for
books in English. And English was already
finding a place in the state and in the
law in 1362 for the first time in three
centuries English was acknowledged as a
language of official business since the
conquest court cases have been heard in
French now the law recognized the too
few people understood that language
probably because many of the educated
lawyers had died in the play from now on
it was declared cases could be pleaded
showed defended debated and judged in
English in the same year 1362 parliament
was opened here at Westminster for the
first time ever the Chancellor addressed
the assembly not in French but in
English while the worship and honor of
God King Edward had something at his
planets Dukes Earls barons and other
Lords of Israel to its parliament hold
on at Westminster the year of the king
six and soon English would once again be
the language of Kings the country hadn't
had an english-speaking monarch since
Herald have been hacked to death at
Hastings in 1066 in 1399 king richard ii
was deposed by henry duke of lancaster
parliament was summoned here to the
Great Hall at Westminster the Dukes and
Lords Spiritual and temple were
assembled the royal throne draped in
cloth of gold stood empty then Henry
stepped forward crossed himself and
claimed the crown and in a great
symbolic moment he made his speech not
in the Latin language of state business
or the French language of the royal
household but in what the official
history calls his mother tongue English
in the Nama of the hardy our son and
holy ghost II Henry of Lancaster
challenge this realm of England and the
corona with all of the members and the
appurtenances as either
undescended bay reached leaner of the
blood coming for the feudal lord the key
Henry third and fourth not reached that
God of his graça had sent me with the
help of me King and OB friend s toll
recover it which Alma was he point to
pay undone for the fault of governance
and undoing the God allows
and so Henry Duke of Lancaster became
King Henry the fourth the English was
once again a royal language the tide
seemed to be turning in its favour by
the end of the 14th century it was on
course to regain its status as the first
language of the country and now it also
had a literary champion who could
harness its full capabilities to produce
great writing Geoffrey Chaucer won that
aprille with his shoures suit the draft
of March hath perced to the roote
and Basset every vine encyclical of
which virtue in general is the floor one
zephyros egg with his sweater breath in
spirit has in every halt and Haythe the
tender crops and the young son has in a
ram his healthy course Iran and smile a
fool is mac and melody a that slip and
alden eked with open yay
so prick as Hamlet or in ear courage
than long and Fulk to go on on
pilgrimage
Chaucer wrote those opening shower
aligns to the Canterbury Tales more than
six centuries ago in 1387 for millions
of people since the canterbury tales
have been the flowering of the medieval
english language and also a great
staging post for english literature
Chaucer pictured here as one of his own
pilgrims wasn't the only writer of his
time and he didn't invent the language
he was working with but he more than any
other recognize its richness the
potential in having at his disposal by
cabbage some high and low society
brought from French and Old English and
he worked it to the full Chaucer was a
Londoner and an important man with
connections to the royal family and a
high position in the civil service he
troubled widely perhaps even been a spy
and he knew Latin and French might have
been expected like many other English
boats at the time to write it either of
those languages for an exclusive
audience but he didn't he chose to write
in English the English that was spoken
in London the language of London would
have been a huge mixture you've got
people coming in from the central
Midler's from the northern Midlands from
the northern Minnesota bringing more
Scandinavian terms because it's an area
of strong Scandinavian settlement but
we'd have also have heard French
loanwords which people would have heard
in literature as well so it's it's it's
a vibrant variety of English
befell that in that season on a die in
software cat the Tabar does Eli ready to
wenden on my pilgrimage to Canterbury
with full devote garage at nicked was
coming to that hostelry well mean and 20
in a company this is where the table our
Dean used to stand now it's the rather
dismal backyard of guy's hospital this
is where Chaucer's pilgrims gather
before setting out on their pilgrimage
to Canterbury the buildings may have
gone but Chaucer's characters are
connealy constructed cross section of
medieval society live on in his writing
a quiche there was and that a ward a man
that for the team that he first began to
read a note hail Ovid chivalry truth
there was also a nun a three RS that of
his smeeling was full simple and coy a
merchant was there with a forked bird in
Mott LA and he owned horses at a good
whiff was there of BC the baths but she
was some del deaf and that was SCAF the
Miller was astute car for the Nonna's
full big he was a brown and a cook who's
the pilgrim set off for Canterbury
journey of about three days then and to
pass the time they told each other
stories the stories have a range of
styles from serious moral fables to
bawdy farces with episodes that wouldn't
be out of place in a carry on film what
Chaucer did most brilliantly was to
choose and tailor his the language to
suit every tale and its teller the
creation of mood and tone and the
realization of characters through the
language is something we expect the
writers today so it's difficult to
realize how extraordinary was when
Chaucer did it he showed he proved that
reformed English was fit for great
literature which gives him a key part in
our story. This gentil cok hadde in his
governaunce Sevene hennes for to doon al
his plesaunce
Whiche were his sustres and
his paramours And wonder lyk to hym, as
of colours; Of whiche the faireste hewed on
hir throte, Was cleped faire damoysele
Pertelote. Can you tell us what
language is predominating in this
particular passage we've got so many
French were suddenly they really hit you
between the eyes even today I think
you'd noticed some governance
please danse paramore in fact a Chaucer
is is thought to be the person who
introduced Pariwar into the English
language himself and those words
Plaisance governance all appear from
about the 1350 so they're quite new at a
time when she'll sir use them in nuns
priests ale questioners courses why is
he doing this well it's odd really isn't
it because this is a story about
chickens it's true about a cock and his
hens and you thought that perhaps a a
less refined language might be in order
but choice was playing with a whole idea
of an exalted style and so he's he's
investing these these hens and cocks
with a feeling of great literary quality
you know it becomes almost a mock epic
Chaucer not only used existing French
words for poetic effect he also
introduced his own elevated synonyms
sometimes bypassing an English word in
favor of a more stylish French boring so
English had the perfectly good hard as a
noun
Chaucer bored the French word difficulty
in place of unhappy he gave us this
adventure for shin ship dishonesty for
building edifice for uncommon ignorant
and for meaning significance but Chaucer
wasn't just ensnared with the elegance
of French
he also cherished the directness and
earthiness of English and used it for
example in the Millers tale where the
student absalon's midnight assignation
with the neighbor's wife doesn't go
quite according to plan this epsilon can
weep his mouthful dream there was the
neat as pitch or as the coal and at the
window would she put her whole and
epsilon him feel no better worse but
with his mouth he kissed her naked airs
the language of course is predominately
Old English and again Chaucer is aware
of what linguist would call register he
knows that you have to have a particular
style for a particular purpose with
Miller's tail we have both the Miller
himself who is a man of extraordinary
quality so he opens doors simply by
running at them with his head which is a
clever trick and the story itself is as
you know about bottoms out of windows
another such thing and of course in that
case it's appropriate to have a simple
earthy style he knows that if he's
talking about basic earthy stuff he
might as well use good old English words
and I think it's actually mark that used
by not using many French words I think
people would have picked up on that we
certainly do the style seems very direct
almost colloquial of course that's
literary artifice but it does seem
direct and colloquial and that's as a
complete result of the way in which he's
using the language the language he'd
have heard on the street words like s
meaning ass I'm afraid and other such
rude words
scholars dispute how much vocabulary
Chaucer actually introduced into English
with Old English he certainly
reintroduced words which hadn't been
written down since before 1100 probably
because they weren't considered
important or seemly enough words like
churlish farting friendly learning
loving restless sway Vern wasp wifely and
willingly. The brilliant Archbishop son
of a French merchant had been brutally
murdered in 1170 by Knights acting on
the wishes if not instructions of Henry
the second that first Plantagenet whose
wife Eleanor had done so much to promote
to the courtly French language which
Chaucer was now mining so expertly
in Chaucer's day this area around the
cathedral and the nearby streets would
have been thronged with pilgrims from
all over the country
well the thronging hasn't changed but
they would have been speaking in the
dialect of their homes English wasn't
uniform in the way it was spoken and
Chaucer himself in the reves tale gives
us literature's first fully northerner
who speaks with flat vowels
he says him for home now for no gong for
gone and nan for non all pronunciations
that will be quite understandable in the
northeast of England today
Chaucer himself worried about whether
his work would be mispronounced or
wrongly copied or just misunderstood in
other parts of the country he bids one
of his poems Troilus and Cressida I
rather worried farewell voicing a
concern in a sorcerer felt for The
Canterbury Tales go little book and for
there is so great diversity in English
and in a reading of all tongue so try
God that non miss rate de neige they
miss Metra for deaf out of tongue and
read web so Dube or le song that though
bei understand a god besiege
of course Chaucer's books particularly
The Canterbury Tales were understood his
language the language of late 14th
century London would become with some
later modifications the standard form of
English and is genius in harnessing that
language to serve his vision as a writer
would guarantee that it lived on a
century and a half after his death
Geoffrey Chaucer was famous enough for
this tomb to be put in Westminster Abbey
in intervening years his tales had
spread around the country and delighted
listeners and readers ranging from
London merchants to the future Richard
the third before the 15th century
resulted the canterbury tales had been
printed by thomas Caxton ensuring the
future
Chaucer's work and furthering the
process by which southern English
sources English would become the
standard Chaucer was the first poet to
be buried here in what's become Poets
Corner
it's appropriate for the man who not
only entertained and delighted in his
own work but who through expanding the
capabilities of the English language
created a standard and a platform for
those who followed
you