in the first three programs in this
series we've seen English language grow
from a ruff the wonderfully expressive
dialect to Chaucer's English and a
language fit the Tyndall's Bible now the
language makes a dramatic leap forward
over 400 years ago here on London
Southbank
lived and worked a man who was to become
the greatest English writer the greatest
master of language of all time William
Shakespeare Shakespeare wrote at the end
of the 16th and the beginning of the
17th century this was the period of the
English Renaissance a word that was
borrowed from French meaning rebirth
during this time the English language
too was reborn English vocabulary was
rapidly changing it expanded grew
flowered and exploded with new words
this is the story of the growth of
Shakespeare's English in it's an
adventure that starts on water
most important changes in the English
language had come about through foreign
invasions but in the late 16th century
the legendary repulsion of an invasion
started off a new chapter in the
adventure of English
in 1588 English ships were battling it
out with a Spanish Armada Elizabeth the
first was queen of three and a half
million subjects and determined not to
surrender for a much stronger and much
bigger enemy she appeared before a crowd
at the port of Tobruk and using all her
skill in rhetoric together with the
power of an English language growing
rapidly in richness and eloquence she
delivered her rallying I am coming to
live or die amongst you all to lay down
for my gods and for my kingdom and for
my people my honor and my Bloods evil in
the duct I know I have the body of a
weak and feeble woman but I had the
heart and banner of a king and never
King of England to not Spain not any
Prince of Europe so dare to invade the
borders will pluck up your heart by your
piece in temp and your better in the
fields we shall shortly have a famous
victory
Elizabeth's famous call to arms at
Tilbury delivered here by Dame flora
robson in this 1937 film has been told
and retold for over 400 years
it's because Elizabeth understood how to
use the new power and resonance of the
English language to inspire her people
and this new power of the English
language reflected the naval strength of
a small country that was able to hold
off the Spanish Armada
but Elizabethan ships for doing
something far more important still as
far as language was concerned a naval
supremacy opened up the world to trade
as England imported a huge cargo of
goods the English language imported the
cargo vocabulary alongside a stunning 10
to 12 thousand new words entered English
in the spirit bringing with them new
ideas
by the time of the Spanish Armada
English was still lagging behind other
European languages and the influence is
exerted in the newly conquered
territories abroad Portuguese had
already made its mark in Brazil and
Spanish had been spoken Cuba and Mexico
for more than half a century elsewhere
Arabic had spread through the Middle
East over eight hundred years earlier
and Hindi was comfortably establishing
itself as a vernacular if not a literary
language throughout the Indian region
but on a very much smaller scale English
was at least beginning to make its mark
during the sixteenth century it had
begun to spread to parts of Wales
Scotland and Ireland English was
spreading but English was also absorbing
some of the thousands of new words had
entered the language came from just
across the channel
England's thriving maritime trade was
most successful close to home and it's
not surprising that French which had a
long history of providing words to
English was to provide English with many
of its nautical and meteorological terms
words like crew detail Passport progress
moustache and Explorer were traded in
English for French rule under maritime
terms like embargo tornado canoe and
port come to us from both Spanish and
Portuguese we get keelhaul smuggle yacht
decoy cruise and reef along with
knapsack and landscape from Dutch and
although the popular myth is an
anglo-saxon game English all its swear
words he was sailors that brought us
crap and bugger from low Dutch
now called Flemish in the 16th century
Anglo Saxon is an eclair
but these sailors brought back more than
just colorful language
they're trading expeditions to Europe
and the Spanish mane literally bore
fruit and barrel loads of other goods
that was to affect the English language
but the most domestic of levels
more of our food began to come from
abroad in many of our food terms have
renaissance origins spanish and
portuguese gave us new delicacies and
new words for them to hear and Borough
Market which would have existed in
Shakespeare's day we can see these goods
such as apricots bananas
lime mandarin yams potatoes and
anchovies coco maize and port wine
meanwhile the words for chocolate and
tomato come to us from the French
and the sailors and traders told tales
of new world words from a total of 50
other languages joined the cargo of new
words that were integrated into English
English now bristled with newly imported
terms from overseas like Shi from
Chinese bamboo and ketchup from Malay
and curry from Tamil during the 16th
century English also imported yoghurt
and hoard from Turkish bazaar and turban
from Persia and coffee magazine and
alcohol from Arabic it wasn't just the
traders who returned to England burying
their exotic goods and linguistic wealth
English artists and scholars and
aristocrats explored Italy and its
culture which was the dominating
influence of that time there they
wondered at the architecture of the
scions and the music carrying back new
ideas and a sumptuous lexicon to
describe them so balcony still
pronounced at that time in the Italian
manner balcony as well as fresco villa
cupola portico piazza miniature and
designer all from italian as a opera
violin solo sonata soprano trill cameo
and carnival
but the biggest influx of words came
from the classical languages Latin and
Greek in the sixteenth century here at
Oxford and also at Cambridge there are
nestled scholars wanted to revive Latin
they found in schools teaching pure and
literary Latin and Greek and they also
translated classical texts into English
Latin is still used ceremonially today
at Oxford University in the 16th century
it was not only the language of religion
but also the language of classical
thought science and philosophy Latin was
the language of scholarship controversy
and diplomacy English scholars spoke and
wrote in Latin so that they could
communicate and debate with other
European scholars
Lattin had been spoken by some people in
england for over 1,500 years since Roman
times but they was the language of
scholarship on an everyday basis things
were changing everyone from the common
people to the academics and the Queen
now spoke English and not Latin even the
Latin was still a compulsory subject in
schools
there was a great ransacking fervor in
the English language which was at its
peak for 20 years the decade on either
side of the earth 1600 saw thousands of
Latin words come into the English
vocabulary of educated people words like
excavate horrid radius cautionary
pathetic pungent frugal dislocate
submerged antipathy premium specimen and
even the words of manuscript and lexical
were absorbed into English during these
two decades Latin and Greek were the
perfect building blocks for a new
English vocabulary to describe the new
concepts techniques and inventions that
were coming in from continental Europe
during the Renaissance this was a period
of great intellectual and scientific
fervor during this time were invented
both the ideas and the words for
atmospheric chaos critic strenuous and
explain along with the other Latin and
Greek inspired words such as paradox
eternal and chronology. In fact concepts
and inventions are themselves words
borrowed from Latin and technique is of
Greek origin the developing field of
medicine particularly relied on
classical words still today medical
terms were in Latin and Greek and many
date from the Renaissance amongst the
words that arrived at that time from
Greek via Latin were skeleton tendon
tibia larynx glottis pancreas and
sinuses from Latin we also inherit our
temperature along with the parasites and
viruses detecting pneumonia delirium and
epilepsy that plague our health even our
thermometers tonics and capsules to cure
them are all words of classical origin
in fact even now we use Latin and Greek
for medicine and technology the Greek di
plutonium or the Latin insulin heed
internet quantized audio and video are
all 20th century inventions one of the
most recent additions to the oxford
english dictionary this year was the
phrase quantum computation which is
purely Latin in origin Latin seems set
to Honeycomb English but not everyone
agreed with what critics called new
inkhorn
terms descent was growing among the
scholars
you said for the national uproar of the
inkhorn controversy
the inkhorn controversy named after the
horn pot which held ink for quills was
the first formal dispute about the
English language never before had there
been such a consciousness of what the
English language was and should be what
began was a few testy written outbursts
culminated in a full-blown academic
background.
Many scholars objected to the increasing
incursion of Latin and Greek words. A key
figure among them was Sir John Cheke who
was published at King's College here in
Cambridge he argued strongly that
English should not be polluted by other
tongues ironically Cheke was a
classicist and the first Regius
professor of Greek in Cambridge
nevertheless she felt that English
should be reappraised as a Germanic
language going back to its anglo-saxon
roots. He even invented words like
crossed for crucified gain rising for
resurrection ground rot for founded
collar for publican moon for lunatic for
sale for profit and hundreder  for
Centurion. "I am of this opinion that our
own tongue should be written clean and
pure unmixed an unmanned gold with
borrowing of other tongues when if we take
not heed by time ever borrowing and
never pay, she shall be fain to keep her
house as bankrupt".
Cheke wrote about the bankruptcy and
counterfeiting of the pure English
language but it's again ironic that the
very word to use words like bankrupt
counterfeiting and indeed the word pure
itself art of anglo-saxon or Germanic
origin at all they're from the Latin
based languages Italian and French the
cheeks enthusiasm for English brought
about something else which is
significant here in the Protocollum book
and the records of admission to Kings
College the name of the book is Latin
and it's written in Latin the gridding
beneath Cheke's entry for the very first
time in this book is a text in English
this short English note was the first
chink in the classical armor that have
protected scholarship and isolated it
from everyday people look it starts off
in Latin if we can decipher it a Gradius
via Maggie's tray you're Hannah's cheek
at mrs. threw it in verum at epitome the
positive aleady regardless predictive
which means that this were demands on
304e
Cheke was admitted into the true and
perpetual Provost ship of the aforesaid
King's college but underneath it is a
short passage and this is the quiet
revolution which is in english it says
first of all I do protest and declare
that otherwise I do not swear or promise
anything
by that should bind me contrary to the
true doctrine of the Church of England
but however Hardy tried to promote a
pure English cheek and his supporters
couldn't stand the huge influx of
Latinate words that people have started
using no one could control the English
language by the end of the sixteenth
century over a period of some sixty or
so years the building blocks have been
laid to create a language that we can
still understand today that we call
modern English in the modern English
that we read and speak today we hear
some of these Latinate words that seem
oddest at the time but some of these
have survived 16th and early 17th
survive
century words like industrial
exaggerated mundane permit transmit
capacity disagree disabuse necessitate
an expectation external celebrate and
extol cures at the time but we use them
today
however cheek may have taken some
comfort in the fact that some of the
thousands of Latin and Greek words
coined during the great inkhorn
controversy didn't survive. Through a
process of natural selection
"obtestate" to bear witness and fatigate to
make tired have been lost as have
“illecebrous” meaning delicate or "deruncinate”
to weed. “Abstergify” to cleanse
"arreption” a sudden removal and “subsecive”
remaining over of all slipped out of use.
“Nidulate” to build a nest, "latrate” to
bark like a dog pity about that and
“suppeditate” the supply, have also
disappeared whilst a word like impede
survived its opposite "expede" didn't. As
we explored the globe so at home we
explored the world of words it's fun to
poke fun with these questions but they
demonstrate the intense interest the
English language inspired people from
the Queen to a young grammar school boy
from Stratford William Shakespeare of
course were reading an English language
that was flush with thousands of new
words and ideas it was an English that
could be used as a tool of power to
rally spirits against foreign invasions
but he was also in English which could
and did create a literature of the most
remarkable poetry and flexibility
English already had a great author in
Chaucer but now the English language was
to take on an even bigger challenge to
lay the foundations or a world language
in the 16th century English was a
delicate flowering language that needed
to be protected it had long been in the
shadow of other European languages there
was such an interest in these languages
that glossaries were compiled in the
form of bilingual Italian to English
French to English and Spanish to English
dictionary's
English was finer to get its very own
dictionary 8 years before Italian 35
years before French but 800 years after
Arabic and nearly a 1000 years after
Sanskrit. The word dictionary is first
used in its latin form
dictionaries in 1225 by an english
scholar and in many ways a dictionary is
particularly suited to the english
language the language which has absorbed
so many others
the very first English dictionary is put
together in 1604 by Robert Corddry he
called it a table alphabetical and this
is it it's a list of english words
mainly of Latinate origin with the brief
explanation so we can see that the very
first word in this only surviving copy
of this tiny dictionary is abandon cast
away or yield up to leave or forsake we
see that malady is a disease or that
some early is briefly or in few words
argue is to reason geometry is the art
of measuring the earth elegance is
finesse of speech an empire is
government or Kingdom quadrangle is
four-cornered and radiant is shining
bright there are only two thousand five
hundred and forty-three words in this
very first English dictionary it was a
meagre word horde but a first attempt at
a collection it's by no means exhaustive
you don't find everyday words like shoe
cold food or house cow wet rain dress
fish or love more than anything this
little book was a recognition of the new
status of the English language as it
declared on its first page full of hard
usual English words borrowed from the
Hebrew Greek Latin or French Corddry
intended this dictionary to be used by
those who might not understand words
which they shall hear or read in
scriptures sermons or elsewhere this
wasn't a book for scholars it was a book
for the ordinary people to catalog new
words and to explain the new ideas
associated with these words this was
because the English population was
growing more and more educated one
estimate is that by 1600 half of the
three and a half million population at
least in citizen towns had some minimal
literacy
but it was the good education of those
brought up around the world of the
Elizabethan Court in Grand homes like
this one,
Henry VIII's place in Kent that was to
contribute strikingly to the adventure
of English in England thousands of new
words were absorbed into the English
language
with these words came an intense
interest in how to use them the study of
rhetoric the art of public speaking and
Composition became part of a good
education and rhetoric had a fine
spokeswoman and speech writer in Queen
Elizabeth the first who excelled at it
she was a literary and educated monarch
she had private tutors she spoke six
languages and translated French and
Latin texts furthermore Elizabeth
enjoyed writing poetry I grieve and dare
not show my discontent I love and yet
unforced to seem to hate I do yet dare
not say I ever meant I seems dark mute
but inwardly do prate English was
looking for a literature to reflect its
newly enriched status and it was to the
courtiers
the Knights of Elizabeth entourage that
the role fell to turn the English
language into literature the gentleman
poet who handled the pen with as much
skill as the sword he was called up to
play his part in the adventure of
English
the courtier wrote for pleasure and for
him writing playing and molding the
language all became things to aspire to
there even existed manuals of rhetoric
that advised would be caught your poets
on the best composing techniques the
perfect embodiment of the courtier poet
was a heroic nobleman who was born here
in pencils place in 1554 Sir Philip
Sidney. By his mid-twenties Sidney had
already worked as Elizabeth's ambassador
abroad and had written the finest
collection of beloved firms of his age
he died in battle when he was only 31
and achieved lasting fame for giving his
water bottle to another wounded soldier
with the words "thy need is greater than
mine"
Above all he had the leisure education
and wit to make English the subject of
both his poetry and his treatise about
language "An apologie for Poetrie". Sidney
composed music and songs he wrote for
pleasure and for art's sake not for a
living. Fly fly my friends ,I have my
deaths wound,
fly. See there that boy that murthring
Boy I say, Who like a theefe hid in a dark bush
doth ly. Till bloody bullets
get him wrongful pray.
I talked to Katherine Duncan Jones
Oxford Don and Britain's leading expert
on the work of Philip Sidney about his
importance to the English language what
was new about that Pam I thought was new
was the application of very bold still
very fresh immediate words to what might
be called a very trite clichéd situation
words like bloody bullet and thief who
like a thief hid in dark bush to fly
that murdering boy which make it sound
as if the speaker has just been mugged
and fatally wounded by one of these
juvenile criminals who were very common
in Elizabethan tongues and villages and
I'm afraid is still very common now and
I think like many of semi-solid says
it's a sort of trick performance with
language that he makes us think we're
reading something very surprising and
new well it's just that tardo story of
cupid shooting with a group Golden Arrow
but bloodied bullet makes it sound
completely different as if it's a
gunshot wound
what in general you think Sydney did
with the language that was given him
this sort of core Charis man penning
what could be a new English what was he
doing but he was enormously expanding it
if you look at the Oxford English
Dictionary online look up Philip Sidney
there are 2225 he was expanding it
enormous Lee both the usages and the
actual words with foreign words probably
some words there were all all some words
that hadn't been used in literary
language before words from words that he
had made up essentially by turning nouns
into verbs and creating new adverbs and
new forms of speech like describing a
cat saying the cat is moving scratching
Lee and nobody had ever thought of
describing a cat we were in scratching
lifts before numerous first usages are
attributed to Philip Sidney bud bar
scummy as a term of abuse dumb stricken
miniature for a small picture he was
fond of adding words together to form
evocative images ranging from milk white
horses by pleasing fire
well shading trees to more unusual ones
like honey flowing eloquence hang worthy
necks or even long with the love
acquainted eyes. Could you say that at the
round the time of Sydney English was
becoming a modern language. I think it
was because I think there was this sense
that very modern things of the
absolutely present moment could be done
with it
as of course happens now with the new
words we have with every almost every
month new words into our language was
that exciting in sense that it was a
language which was both very historical
and carried many relics of Latin and
Greek conception and yet was absolutely
streetwise what ideas were was Sydney
bringing that had not been expressed for
as well expressed before English and
English culture could be as rich as
French Italian even to name the enemies
Spanish culture Cynthia was very well
informed about Spanish literature and
culture too was actually Philip of Spain
godson named after him so confidence in
in the English language as a medium in
which great works of art could be
produced and everyday transactions could
be carried on they didn't have to be in
Latin or in the kind of French was by
diplomats the English language could
actually be used for important matters
of state where be the roses gone which
sweetened so our eyes where were those
red cheeks which oft with varying
creased in frame the height of honor in
the kindly badge of shame
who have the crimson we've stolen from
my morning skies which words phrases
comic fight phrases like my better half
for a much-loved spouse which actually
in its context in Sydney's tragic and
now is the sort of sitcom cliche I'll
see what my better half thinks about
that but I think when that rather be
said phrases use people have no idea it
goes back to Sydney's Arcadia well it's
this is not solution if it word like
far-fetched as applied to a narrative or
even what we're doing now Melvyn having
a conversation commune exchanging speech
simply brought that into the language
conversation used to me and just having
dealings of an undefined kind with other
people but the specific application to
having dealings through language with
Sydney's. But for the uttering sweetly
and properly the conceits of the mind
which is the end of speech that happy
equally with any other tongue in the
world English had it equally with any
other tongue in the world there's a
sense of triumph uh a victory even the
sweet smell of success
Sydney was one of the courtly stars of
poetry poetry became the benchmark for
English by the 1600s purged like John
Donne Edmund Spencer Ben Johnson George
Herbert and many more were writing lines
like Johnson's drink to me only with
thine eyes or Duns
no man is an island they become everyday
expressions and in polishing their
technique the poets also polished
English as a language fit for the most
testing poetic and dramatic endeavors
but the flowery sonnets of the gentleman
poets wouldn't have been understood in
the area that we now know a Southwark or
the South Bank just outside the city of
London jurisdiction it was an area of
disrepute with thieves and vagabonds
taverns and brothels it was a red-light
district of London in the 1590s the
prostitutes and thieves who prowled
around this area had their own street
slang much as local gangs today have
their own argot. We know the cove meant
man fumbles made fans gang was mouth
PanAm was bred and skipper was a barn
not many of these words have survived
but even today Cove is a slang word for
a man. Most importantly though the
language of the streets was a simple and
direct communication using single
syllable words and plain speech by the
end of the 16th century theatres were a
main feature in this dubious area and
the most famous was the globe.
By the time the globe was built in 1599
people had been attending performances
in the commercial play houses for 30
years and it was on these hugely popular
stages that something extraordinary
happened the playwrights of the period
echoed and transformed the turbulent
english language which they were hearing
combining the rich vocabulary and poetry
of the quarters with the slang of the
commoners because the theatres of the
time had no scenery and barely any props
language was the means of choice on the
stage to captivate the audience and the
scene was set for the most famous
dramatist of them all William
Shakespeare to make his indelible mark
on the English language the plays that
were written by Shakespeare as well as
those of his contemporaries such as
Marlo Johnson and Nash attracted
enormous crowds the globe could hold
between 3,000 and 3,500 people
and the other five theaters in London
could easily rival a globe a 10-day run
for a play counted as a long one and the
London population the merely two hundred
thousand inhabitants about the same
population a Sunderland today demanded
constant novelty and excitement
it's astonishing to realize that a box-office
hit like Shakespeare's Titus
Andronicus would have been seen by one
in two men in London. Genius and the new
mix of language was bringing together a
mix of society in the popular play
houses. English is seeding the words was
no longer restricted to the scholars and
the quarter poets. With Shakespeare and
his contemporaries English had a new
audience it was ready to travel the
world. All the world's a stage and all
the men and women merely players they
have their exits and their entrances and
one man in his time plays many parts his
acts being seven ages
this is stratford-upon-avon
Shakespeare's birthplace English's
best-selling author has served the town
weld three million tourists visit every
year making Shakespeare English's
biggest export. The beauty of
Shakespeare's language is that we can
still understand it today
Shakespeare's English has become so
quotable that it's come to define
English in the words that we use the
thoughts we express be it for native
speakers or students of English or for
tourists. For example Julius Caesar
friends Romans countrymen linear years,
to be or not to be. most important to be
and not to be that was here a mouse it's
a it's a good read the video not to be,
that is the question. The quality of
Mercy is not strained that's about it
It's my friend come from China and such
the I saw their famous person in Chinese
Romeo Romeo wherefore I don't yeah
wait for out there and this is the
dagger I see before thee me we heard
about Shakespeare at school and later on
at the theater and
we are interested in reading Shakespeare
he'll detain alums they'll detain of
Kedah
Hilde came here after. Shakespeare's
favorite all over the world
nice scholars today attributed 38 plays
154 sonnets and other major poems to
Shakespeare who was born in this house
but his biggest contribution to English
might be the vocabulary that we find in
his work well over 2,000 of our words
for instance today I first recorded
their words which broaden the way we
look at life tell us how we act tell us
how we think tell us what we value
although Shakespeare didn't invent them
for instance the words obscene
accommodation barefaced misanthrope
leapfrog and lackluster all make their
first appearance in his work as do
advertising assassination courtship
dexterously indistinguishable
premeditated and reliance over four
hundred years ago
Shakespeare already used an enormous
English vocabulary of at least twenty
one thousand different words English was
in a state of flux and Shakespeare was
perfectly placed to make the most of it
Shakespeare is influenced by the
language of ideas at the end of the
sixteenth century his language still
influences ours today in many ways his
words and images defined the way we
think
Hamlet's to thine own self be true for
instance explores the notion of personal
identity which we still probe
what the Dickens has nothing to do with
Charles but makes its first appearance
in Shakespeare's Merry Wives of Windsor
as good luck would have it that does two
beggars all description and salad days
are inherited from Antony and Cleopatra
Hamlet gave us "in my mind's eye" "caviar
to the general" "to be cruel to be kind" "to
the manor born" "hoist with his own petard"
"to hold the mirror up to nature" as the
lady said it's full of quotations
Shakespeare coined many of the
expressions we use today but "brevity is
the soul of wit" so I won't play "fast and
loose" but I'll "make a virtue of
necessity" and vanish into "thin air".
In many ways Stratford itself defined
Shakespeare's use of the English
language the Stratford of the second
half of the sixteenth century was a
village of nearly 1500 inhabitants
Shakespeare's thought of attended
Stratford school he would initially have
been taught in English but had also
studied the Latin classics
Cicero Virgil and Ovid and by the upper
forms it would have been forbidden to
speak in English only in Latin fine
arias it's our case
over 400 years later they're still
teaching Latin in the same room that
Shakespeare studied it
if Sakawa Solon's I Graham teststudent
our Morin
Tay dual kiss con honks - solemnly to
their second day when he entered d teh
dekyon taking a bat tenaris a t on focus
I'll post EOD tests elegante Migra for
me deny you can ingress this monistic
way howdy Reagan cray tremendum later on
in Shakespeare's life it seems that he
picked up both French and Italian the
Italian story source of a fella for
example never appeared in translation
into English
but Shakespeare's English education
would have been completed at church, this
church, Holy Trinity Church in Stratford
in which he was later buried. This is his
grave.
a church is  ??? lesson, he would have
had to read texts in English especially
Tyndale's English Bible Shakespeare
didn't go to university and early on he
was mocked for that by the London ??
who benefited from university tutoring.
But just a church and a grammar school
education or to provide the young
William Shakespeare with the language
base that he needed to become English's
greatest playwright Shakespeare also
knew about the inkhorn controversy and
used both a Latin words and playing
terms in his own writing
he used new words which had just
appeared towards the end of the
sixteenth century like multitudinous
emulate demonstrate dislocate initiated
meditate or illumined eventful horrid
modest and vast he invented and was also
fond of compound words like
hugger-mugger
baby eyes fair play break vow or
pell-mell smooth-faced widow-comfort
canker-sorrow bare-pick’t, basilico-like
half-blown and ill-tuned which are
uniquely his. But there are some words
which Shakespeare used which don't
survive our everyday language might
sound very different if we were saying
“appertainments,” “cadent" exsufflicate
“questrist,” “tortive,” soilure abruption
persistive protractive ungenitured unplausive
vastidity and shakespeare's longest
word "honorificabilitudinatibus"
which means with honour has sadly fallen
out of fashion altogether.
Shakespeare's vocabulary also betrays
his Midlands roots in his work we find
regional words like "keck" for "fool's
parsley" and "honeystalks" for "clover
stalks" we find "baton" which means a
cudgel and "batlet" which are still used
until recently to mean the bat to beat
clothes in the wash. You also find the
very ??? ??? to thrust and ??? to
smash. Sometimes I call it Devil's fly
thing but the general name for it the
everyday name for it that we use was
"keck". let's say I get a bit of keck for
the rabbits. Do you remember him saying about
batlet tool? edge in the yard,
yes we had a batlet tool
??? in the backyard to put there
well washing or you could put to soak
stuff in it you know all that morning.
shakespeare's regional accent is thought
to have sounded a bit like the locals
today speaking a kind of Midlands
English with a strong "r" in words like
turn and herd, "side" becomes "sider" and
"farmer" becomes "faarmer" Right” and “time”
become “roight” and “toime.” Although nowadays
the stratford accent is more influenced
by nearby birmingham, Shakespeare's
Midland accent was described as having
been a mixture between west country and
Irish. we asked Peter silver a Stratford
man like Shakespeare to read us a
passage from Henry V. The even mead that
erst brought sweetly forth the freckled
cowslip, burnet and green clover. Wanting
the scythe, withal uncorrected, rank, Conceives
by idleness and nothing teems But
hateful docks, rough thistles kecksies, burrs,
Losing both beauty and utility.
It's intriguing to think of what
Shakespearean verse would have sounded
like during Renaissance.
John Barton an expert on speaking
Shakespeare thinks who would have
sounded like this once more into the
breach dear friends once more or close
the wall up with our English dead in
pace as nothing so becomes a man as
modest stillness and humility but when
the blast of war blows in our air then
imitates the action of the tiger stiffen
the sinews summon up the blood disguise
fair nature with hard favours rage then
in the eye a terrible aspect that it
prey through a head like the portage of
a brass cannon let the brow or helmets
as fearfully as doth the goal is rock or
hang and jutting his confounded bass
swiveled with a wild and wasteful ocean
Inside that wonderful speech have you
got any particular words or stresses
that you say look this is what they did
then that we don't do now Shakespeare
was very free with words and would scan
the same word differently within the
same scene or speech like whether you
said complete or complete that was
heretic licence. And for writing more
freely I think that we tend to look down
the wrong end of the telescope if we
don't allow that they actually were not
yet quite settled on spelling that they
were free to play games with words and
language and it was in dispute that was
the culture, the culture was a different
one which we we've tended to codify so
if you are asked to say what what you
thought what you thought was unique
about Shakespeare's language where would
you put the emphasis
it's the mono syllables that are the
bedrock and and life of the language and
I believe that is so Shakespeare the
high words the high phrases he sets up
to then bring it down
to the simple which explains it like
making the multitudinous seas
incarnadine making the green one red
there is high language what hell's he
talking about
specific clear definition and I think
that the heart of Shakespeare listening
to it for acting it is is that the great
lines often the most poetic lines of the
mono syllables but do you think that the
mono syllables were what would be called
common speech and the high lines were
Shakespeare being Latinate proving that
he didn't need university education to
be clever. this is the paradox high words
can be verbal show-off and rhetoric. Deep
feeling probably comes out most in more
syllables so I say that not to deny that
he teamed with word invention but I
think in some ways his the living power
of the language comes from the
interplay of the two this interplay of
the high speech with the commonplace was
important to Shakespeare. He was also a
fertile ground for comedy. He was so
inventive with just one insult, "knave"
that we can find 50 instances of it in
his plays, playing off monosyllables with more complex formation.
Foul knave! Lousy kaves. Beastly knave! Scurvy railing knave! Gorbellied knave! Bacon-fed knave! The lyingest knave in Christendom. rascally scold
deadly lousy pranking name filthy
roasted stocking name in "The Tempest"
Shakespeare's last play the main
character the magician Prospero uses a
staff that's often seen to be an image
for Shakespeare's quill. Shakespeare
called Prospero's magic "a potent art" and
Shakespeare himself used the power of
language to conjure up images for a
spellbound audience here at the globe.
when in Prospero's last speech he breaks
his staff.
Shakespeare is setting down his pen the
instrument of his own potent and magic
art.
But this rough magic I heere abjure, and, when
I have required some heavenly music
which even now I do, to work mine end
upon their senses that this airy charm
is for, I'll break my staff, bury it
certain fathoms in the earth, and deeper
than did ever plummet sound I'll drown
my book...
And Shakespeare put down his staff but
his language lives on in print in the
editions that have appeared
uninterruptedly ever since. Shakespeare's
english has spun around the world and
his 38 plays have been translated into
50 languages to be or not to be for
instance is understood today by people
of dozens of nationalities the oxford
english dictionary lists are stunning
33,000 shakespeare quotations there'd
been over 300 film adaptations of
Shakespeare and almost every person
brought up in the United Kingdom when
the bread or seen at least one of
Shakespeare's plays at any given moment
the Shakespeare plays being performed or
read somewhere in the world from London
to Broadway to an amateur theatre group
in Nepal Shakespeare's plays and
Tyndale's Bible have been the two
greatest ambassadors for the English
language and for the first time with
Shakespeare and his fellow playwrights
language supports the professional
writer the man of letters an English
that we understand that his modern is in
his poetry prose and drama Old English
began here in Friesland as a rough
tongue but his latest speakers and
writers the people of England learned
how to exploit its potential and
thousands and thousands of new words
were added to its store by Shakespeare's
time English is a rich and glorious
language and as the Plymouth pilgrims
set sail for America they took with them
flags to claim foreign lands their
English Bibles and this remarkable
language
there were new worlds for English to
discover and English itself was poised
to discover a new world of world