this is the story of how British
interests abroad spread the English
language and now it was changed and
recharged bytes foreign adventures in
India in the Caribbean so why do you
have to the right on this part and I
said to myself like you know he can make
some money here and in Australia the
forces of empire spread English around
the globe whatever the rights wrongs of
this drive he could truly be claimed but
the Sun never set on the English
language as it spread it gave birth to
new English's and they became locked in
battles for power and prestige with the
mother tongue new English's became a
source of pride for some have shame for
others a conflict of liberation even a
Brotherhood and one outcome is
indisputable the English language was
enriched immeasurably
in India English faced a country of
intense and elaborate civilizations a
magnificent Empire initially much
greater than its own and it faced an
enormous challenge if it was to
establish itself in a country which
today boasts over a thousand million
people and 200 different languages
including Hindi Sanskrit Bengali
Gujarati Marathi Punjabi Kashmiri and
Rudra but establish yourself it did and
here in Calcutta the signs are still
literally all around
we gave English words to India and some
words from our experience in India have
fed back into English most of them from
Hindi familiar words like Blighty Mangal
oh shoot
loot GU thug pundit Kashmir
dungarees bandana jodhpurs pajamas
caught divan shampoo cash toddy deco
Gymkhana polar bangle jungle cushy car
key do Molly dinghy catamaran cast
swastika juggernaut avatar guru karma
mantra yoga and sacred cow all these and
many more were adopted from the
subcontinent
trade contacts through the early middle
ages what the first words from Asia into
the English language often through Latin
or Greek which absorbed them and passed
them on words like pepper barrel ginger
Panther sugar musk sand or camphor and
opal all seem to have their roots in
languages spoken on the subcontinent and
especially in Sanskrit
but the close relationship between
English in India really began at the
start of the 17th century when the East
India Company was granted a monopoly
charter to seek out and trade with the
rich spice markets of East this was a
collision of cultures between the
British merchant adventurers and the
potentates of Oriental society and in
order to prosper the English had to
learn a lexicon of power and degree and
to curry favor obsequious this matter
the English at that time were amateurs
in class and social distinctions
compared to the culture which included
Maharaja Mandarin nabob cha mogul con
Raja padishah lama sage Santana and
Maharani the English at the kowtow and
learn Bengali and Hindi to survive and
they did in India after years of
negotiation begging and buttering up the
Mughal rulers in their own Persian
tongue they were allowed to set up
trading posts factories at Madras Bombay
and amid the opulence of sure
at the end of the 17th century the
English established another factory here
in tiny village on the banks of the
river Hugoton which would become one of
the world's greatest trading cities
Calcutta what brought the English to
India was a commodity that they could
turn a profit on around the markets of
the East a commodity that India was
famous for then and now
in India the English found a variety of
brightly colored printed and woven
fabrics delicate Muslims chinses calicos
and gingham
when these reach Britain they became an
instant success and their names as
familiar as they are today
India and Britain it was the start of a
relationship that would be enduring
passionate and often mired by
misunderstanding and violence
English had planted his foot firmly on
Indian soil but if it hardly announced
its presence with a fanfare the East
India Company prospered but in this vast
country its english-speaking employees
were numbered in hundreds not thousands
some of the senior employees were
encouraged to go native take a little
wives and adopt a local habits and dress
and when they wanted to conduct business
they had to learn the local languages
for most British errs this was a matter
of commercial necessity but there were
others who knew most scholarly interest
in India's languages one of these
British students of the Orient
made a discovery which rewrote the
history of the English language English
traced its roots back to the dialects of
the Germanic invaders from frizzier in
the 5th century as we did at the start
of this series but no further
but in 1784 William Jones who was in
India in its capacity as Supreme Court
Judge founded the Asiatic Society of
Bengal to encourage inquiry into the
history civil unnatural the antiquities
arts sciences and literature of Asia and
when Jones started to look at the
ancient language of Sanskrit a language
written down two or three centuries
before the Iliad and the Odyssey he
discovered what was effectively the
prequel of the adventure of English
he discovered that one of the deepest
roots of English was here in India Jones
made the startling discovery that there
were similarities between words in
Sanskrit and a younger language is a
Greek Latin English and others where
Sanskrit had Peter Latin had Pater Old
Norse father Gothic father and English
father
the Sanskrit Bharata Latin freighter
German brooder Slavic broto
Irish brother and of course English
brother even a forms of verb look
similar
English ham Old English Rome
gothic in Latin soon Greek ma sanskrit
puzzling english is gothic fist latin
ask greek st and sanskrit asking
challenge decided that this was evidence
that they were all descended from one
indo-european language and his work was
the foundation of modern philology the
study of languages
English had acquired a new past here at
the headquarters of the Asiatic Society
it was just one of the new buildings
with which the British were reshaping
Calcutta by 1765 the balance of power
had shifted the Mughal empires had
collapsed and the East India Company
took over the administration and
financial control of Bengal India's
richest province Calcutta was becoming a
colonial capital a center of commercial
political and social life here the
relationship between Indian and British
became one of servant and master a
dangerous climate of feeling was
developing that it was a duty and
destiny of the British to govern in
India they were no longer going native
marrying Indian women adopting Indian
customs and learning local languages
they began to see themselves as superior
to the native population and the essence
of their superiority was their religion
in 1830 in the Foreign Secretary William
Wilberforce told the British Parliament
that they were morally obliged to change
what he called India's dark and bloody
superstition from the genial influence
of Christian light and truth
the British had looked at India and had
decided that the Indians just run
foolish enough in the interest of their
happiness and for the good of their
souls they needed to be converted to
Christianity and Western morals a string
of missionaries headed east to devote
themselves to this work in order to
teach their religion they set up schools
and they taught not in the languages of
India but in English there were Indians
who welcomed the establishment of
English language education recognizing
that it could give India access to
modern Western thought and scientific
knowledge but what happened next went
beyond education a new english-language
policy changed Indian society and its
relationship with the British forever in
1835 thomas babington macaulay writer
and member of the supreme council in
calcutta wrote his famous or infamous
minute in it he laid out why he thought
the teaching of English rather than any
Indian language should become official
government policy he summed up the
dialects commonly spoken among the
natives of this part of India contained
neither literary nor scientific
information and are moreover so poor and
rude that it will not be easy to
translate any valuable work into them
the claims of our own language it is
hardly necessary to recapitulate it
stands preeminent even among the
languages of the West I think it clear
that it is possible to make natives of
this country perfectly good English
scholars and to this end our effort
ought to be directed
today that sounds astonishingly
patronizing it sounded to the many at
the time English would be the Imperial
language of India there were some who
welcomed it and saw it as a window to a
bigger world and they still do others
who resented it as an intolerable
imposition and they still do this
English education would only ever be for
a minority of immigrants the core is
intention in creating these good English
scholars was to create a new class of
Indians whose knowledge of the English
language and ideas would make them loyal
to their colonial rulers the class who
he said would be interpreters between a
few thousand British in India and the
million was from their government these
were the cloths of the Indian Civil
Service who are now here as writers this
huge building behind me the writers
building was constructed to house them
from here hundreds of thousands of
instructions dealing in law finance
health Commerce and the nuts and bolts
of government were issued in English
from here the British through English
ran India
as the 19th century progressed the vast
continent was opened up British
colonizers engineers surveyors doctors
planters invested their lives in the
adventure British civil servants working
with their english-speaking Indian
writers administrative
without the english-speaking bureaucracy
there have been no Raj a word meaning
rule or Kingdom taken from the Hindi
English was institutionalized now in
India it was part of the fabric of
government it was the language of
preference the language of prestige and
English as often was changed by this
encounter I stand under the shoes of my
client and only seek to place my bone of
contention clearly in over time the
English spoken by Indians became a
particular ornate form
Babu English she was called your honor
will be pleased enough to observe that
my client is a widow a poor chap with
one postmortem son the language is often
told by Indian to Indian with no British
here to check its proliferation of
florid phrases their relationship is
only homeopathic so the misty arguments
of my learned friend will not hold water
the English spoken by the British also
changed the district officers
magistrates and other officials who
toured the country attending the Raj
picked up Indian words by the bushel and
incorporated them into their daily
speech
the British Army particularly relish
picking up Indian words they pride
themselves on being able to bolo the
batter Torah meaning to speak the lingo
a little or perhaps they were banged up
to the eyeballs stoned on bang in which
case they might need a word with the arm
n wallet the chaplet and find themselves
facing tory Peachy which meant delayed
repatriation and was taken from the
Hindi words for a little later the slang
was so prolific but it needed a
dictionary in 1886 this great glossary
of Anglo Indian colloquial words and
phrases was published almost 900 pages
of it
here's kaki taken from the Hindi but
dust coloured meaning a light Brad cloth
the dictionary notes that it is said
that it is about to be introduced into
the army generally the dictionary has
the curious type of Hobson Jobson as the
book explains this is another army term
a corruption of a phrase shuttered by
Muslims in a procession there are plenty
more examples of the way that the
British had adopted an altered Indian
words chapatti entered the English
language's Chowpatty perhaps with an
echo of Patti or even a cow Pat pushing
it that way the Indian plant carriage
which as irritating hairs became courage
and the fish Kaka became cock-up
Allahabad became known as I love bats
buzzy karna stale food or yesterday's
dinner warmed up became brass knocker
brinjal aubergine became brown jolly and
the great killer cholera morbus in Latin
became the very English Corporal forms
whenever they could
the British fled the threat of corporal
Forbes and the heat and dust of the
plains in summer and took to the hills
in and around Hill stations like
Darjeeling army officers civil servants
and tea planters built a little England
where they could take Tiffin on the
veranda with their mem Symes or sip a
chota peg as the Sun went down
the British shall become comfortable
with India and English comfortable with
its Indian but while English enjoyed
that minion the seeds of Indian
nationalism were being sown in meetings
in this room and rumours alike it by the
pioneers of Indian independence used to
gather Niro himself the young Niro used
to come to this room
this was the unlooked-for fruit of
Macaulay's minute and the education
policy that had brought the english
language to the indian people as well as
words they'd taken on ideas Western
ideas of democracy self-government and
freedom and English are not only given
them the theory it had given them the
language to communicate it to the world
Rudyard Kipling noted that many Indians
claimed that they could run their own
country and that some Englishman
believed them but only because the
Indians put that case in what he called
beautiful English which made it sound
credible Kipling dismissed Indian
independence is no more than a pretty
idea but it was more it was persistent
the English language had inadvertently
sowed the seeds of the destruction of
the Raj the British didn't see it coming
when the Viceroy Lord Curzon
choreographed a spectacular durbar to
celebrate the accession of Edward the
seventh in 1903 India was still the
jewel in the crown of the British Empire
and what or who could possibly dislodge
it
five years later one of the leaders of
the independence movement a lawyer
called ma Hindus K Gandhi wrote a
pamphlet in which he complained about
the imperial status of the English
language in India to give millions a
knowledge of English is to enslave them
the foundation that macaulay laid of
Education has enslaved us I do not
suggest that he had any such intention
but that has been the result is it not a
sad commentary that we should have to
speak of home rule in a foreign tongue
what's fascinating is the idea that a
language can enslave a people
the British didn't much have slavery on
their minds at that time what concerned
em was building a new symbolic capital
more than a thousand miles away from
here to be designed by Sir Edwin Lutyens
a New Delhi but they still taken an
interest in Indian languages and customs
they might have come across the proverb
which said that anybody who tried to
build a new capital of Delhi was doomed
it had happened six times already it
happened to the Raj the rise would be
lost and with that loss would come a
move to oust English from India
altogether
we came to the island of the Campbells
called Dominica where we arrived the 9th
of March near about this place inhabited
certain Indians who came down to us
presented mill and cakes of bread which
they had made from a kind of corn called
maize and they brought us down hens
Pines and potatoes these potatoes be the
most delicate roots that maybe even the
natives from Hawkins called Indians I
mean given that name by Christopher
Columbus in 1492 he thought he'd found a
Western route to India but he had in
fact made landfall here 12,000 miles to
the east in the Caribbean another stage
on which the adventure of English will
be played out the name Caribbean itself
which denotes the Great Sea and the arc
of islands which string out for more
than 1500 miles
the real name of one of the native
tribes here the carriers who notorious
for their fierceness and cruel treatment
of captives another version of their
name was Cali from which we get our word
and the Carib languages gave English
caiman canoe Farrar a peccary and
tamarind among other words from the
language of another local tribe the
arrow axe came hurricane cassava guava
hammock iguana and Savannah two words
used by Hawkins maize and potato and
mangrove barbecue probably and Jamaica
itself it soaked up new words but the
adventure here in the Caribbean is very
different from the one in India their
English initially at least it had to
accommodate itself to establish
languages spoken by people with status
in the Caribbean local people and local
languages would be pushed aside others
would be important and they would react
with English and other European
languages to produce rich and unique
fibers
English interest in the region had begun
with attempts to hijack Spanish treasure
ships by Drake
Hawkins and others with the unofficial
approval of Queen Elizabeth
we were pirates and pirate tales were as
popular then as now by the time Daniel
Defoe wrote his history of pirates in
1724 words from their exotic and
bloodthirsty world had already entered
the language doubloon pieces abate sea
dog couplers freebooter privateer and
Buccaneer in time the Buccaneers went
freelance preying on ships of all
nations hiding out in fortified bases
they set up throughout the Caribbean
the Buccaneers were eventually flushed
out of their strongholds like this one
at Port Royal in Jamaica the future
belonged to other opportunists the
colonists who had already begun the
systematic exploitation of the Caribbean
where the Caribbean and the Atlantic
Ocean meet lie the tiny islands of
Nevison Saint Kitts British settlement
of the Caribbean began here at Sandy Bay
in 1624 the first thing the settlers did
was to drive the local carry people off
the island
the mainly English settlers at first
grew tobacco then switched to the more
lucrative crop of sugarcane they needed
a laborer to work in the fields and
mills soon they were importing slaves
from Africa slaves who picked up English
words from sailors on the ships that
brought them over and from the British
on the plantations the English that was
spoken on sent kids took different forms
there were many British servants and
laborers and they spoke in their own
regional dialects but those further up
the social ladder the landowners and
their managers aspire to something more
refined one 18th century plantation
manager called James Granger put these
aspirations into writing in an epic poem
in praise of the sugarcane
what's oil the cane affects what care
demands beneath what signs to plant what
ills await how the hot nectar best to
crystallize and Eric's sable progeny to
treat a mules that long hath wandered in
the groves of Myrtle indolence attempts
to sing to come out of the Americas high
society admired his ornate style as
English at its best whatever its
qualities it was a world away from the
language spoken by the majority on st.
Kitts that sable progeny of Africa as
Grainger coyly puts it the black slaves
who now at numbered the white settlers a
taste of their language was recorded by
an English carpenter Samuel Matthews in
the last decade of the 18th century on
st. Kitts he wrote down the following
exchange a darker version of plantation
life in granges and perhaps the nearest
we might get to the authentic voice of a
slave vast matter but equal a brioche a
volume you tell us about all the bottom
and go wrong your body flow what's the
matter brother for anything the overseer
hate you
you don't stand in the hall that white
man is going to this is language it
shows the speaker's African origins most
of the words in this short passage I
recognizable in English on the page but
the sounds have shifted brother has
become buddy a word that's now very
familiar but this is the first time it
was recorded overseer has become OBC
this is what happens when people try to
voice strange words using the sounds
that they know we've seen it before in
America when the Pilgrim Fathers
struggled with Native American words
there's another example here the English
word stan has become tan that's probably
because a lot of African languages don't
allow two consonants to run together so
the STS Stan has become T and the nd has
become n stand
English vocabulary African grammar
there's one word straight from Africa
Bhakra for European or white man and
another has come through Portuguese
slave traders their words Savin as here
becomes so be to know you turn the
sorbitol the bokram and go wrong your
body for this kind of language is called
a creole it's the result of African and
European languages colliding producing
hybrids spoken by the black population
Lemmy lon
not such trouble begin no you mind tic
von Thal some knock your rotten this was
the pattern throughout the plantations
of the Caribbean but on each Island the
social and racial mix was slightly
different and each Island developed its
own unique Creole unfortunately English
wasn't a benign parent to what is
regarded as it's rather uncouth
offspring the Creoles continued to be
treated by English speakers as unfit for
polite society
this pressure meant that some Creole
speakers tried to gentrify their
language to sound more like the standard
English speaking social elite so
throughout the Caribbean that wasn't
just a division into two languages with
standard English at one end of society
and deep prayer at the other there was a
whole set of variations across society
but however many variations there were
standard English was treated as superior
at least by white speakers the original
inhabitants of the island had been
cleared by brute force of disease
English had moved in with the settlers
and now it had dominion over the other
forms of languages did it spawn at least
for the time being
wherever English traveled around the
globe the story was the same new
colonies developed dialects of their own
even when no other foreign languages
were involved
in January 1788 a fleet of 11 ships
commanded by captain Arthur Phillip
sailed gingerly between these headlands
after eight months at sea to make a
landfall in the country which would
become Australian place they chose to
settle would become Sydney Harbor today
the ferries which transport Sydney's
commuters by the names of the ships of
what was known as the first fleet
serious supply Fishbourne friendship
Borradaile their original cargo was also
hewn over 700 CC half-starved souls
feared despised and rejected by the
british homeland the ancestors of some
of these commuters the first conducts
let us drink a good health to our
schemas above what lengths have
contrived from this land to remove over
the next 80 years over 150 thousand
convicts were transported to Australia
at Botany Bay the hulks and the jail's
had some thousands in store but out of
the jails are 10,000 times more
the British saw this as unsettled land
but of course it was peopled by native
Australians the Aboriginal tribes had
over 250 languages many would disappear
over time but in the early days the
settlers were fascinated by the natives
and from them they learned the names for
many of the new plants and animals they
are encountering like the kangaroo
English picked up more words from the
native languages around Sydney Harbour
boomerang bingo Cola wallaby wallow Roo
and wombat and Kui which was a call used
by natives to summon one another from a
distance was soon adopted by the English
and there's also a type of owl called
the boo book a tree called owatta which
has become the emblem of New South Wales
what ago which is another name for the
dingo boo murder a throwing stick a
settlement spread English picked up
words from other native languages
Billabong a cut-off pool in the branch
of a river would you regard yeah be
which is a crustacean but a Mundy a
giant perch and from Western Australia
Kylie another word for boomerang when
Australian English developed its own
character which it quickly did it came
less from the relatively few borrowings
from the native languages aníbal
whelmingly
it was shaped by the regional and
criminal background of the early
settlers some words that we think are
most typically Australian were actually
imported dialect words that have died
out England but Pond in their new home
cobber comes from the verb cob meaning
to take a liking to dinkum was a word
for work and fair dinkum meant something
similar to Fairplay and Digger was
another word that sail halfway around
the world English then Australian now
the new Australians got their most
colorful vocabulary from the criminal
slang of 18th century London which was
known as flash or kiddie talk kiddy from
the verb to kid hasn't achieved for the
fool
some of the words they used up Emilia to
us now Chum meaning a fellow prisoner
swag was a bundle of loot job for
robbery Judy for woman mug for face pigs
for police beat for magistrate larva
Frank split for betray by informing put
up job and stow it meaning keeping quiet
are all found in Australia and in the
criminal language of Dickens Oliver
Twist it didn't take long for tension to
develop between the prisoners and their
descendants and the other British
immigrants had come to make a new life
in Australia and were forming the
colonial establishment people like the
MacArthur's who settle here at Elizabeth
farm near Sydney and invented the
Australian sheep industry these British
incomers were known as sterling and they
spoke the language of the home country
the people born in Australia were known
as currency and spoke the local dialect
an Elizabeth farm male convicts were
assigned to labor in the surrounding
fields females to work as servants in
the house and kitchens social divisions
continued defined by language but over
time convicts would serve their
sentences could become citizens of the
emerging country and call themselves
government men legitimates X Isles or
Empire builders
by the 1880s immigrants were outnumbered
by native-born Australians and
Australian English was in rude good
health the weekly bulletin started
appearing in Sydney known as the
Bushman's Bible it was sensational
outspoken and slanging in its pages you
find word like fair dinkum larrikin
bonzer bloody offsider fair cow Butler
and Beluga classic Australian and there
are examples of vivid Australian phrase
making better than a poke in the eye
with a burnt stick or as miserable as a
Bandicoot on a burnt Ridge and they're
also poems and songs which helped create
the image of the Australian bush man and
his speech in the outback once a jolly
swagman the shiny the cool about a tree
and he's saying yes he was and why did
Tilly's Billy Boy you know Wolf's in the
tool with me well Waltzing Matilda
Matilda is slang for a bedroll what's
him a tilde means going on the road was
written on a sheep station by the
Potence Lister Banjo Paterson in 1895
and why did weirdest mix of words from
English convict slang like swagman
meaning a drifter and from Aboriginal
languages like Billabong upon and
Coolibar for eucalyptus waltzing matilda
and capture rates the essence of
Australian English at the time and in
the figure of the swagman who'd rather
die than be taken prisoner it captures
an attitude a contempt for authority
which will become a national try
but while the Australian vocabulary grew
when Australian phrases were coined
Australian English didn't get official
respectability in 1926 the director of
education in New South Wales could still
write it is said to reflect that other
people are able to recognize Australians
by their speech most unfortunately our
variation from the accepted standard is
along lines which are harsh unmusical
and unpleasant to the ear teachers must
do their utmost to check this
development away from standard English
all nations have their symbols and
Australia is well served by Sydney
Harbour this day fit for a queen their
queen the English language had sent its
slang and its dialects to a new country
where they developed a personality of
their own but standard English was
keeping them in thrall the ways of
speaking in Australia formed a rigid
social hierarchy the broad vowels of
slang were at the bottom in standard
English Queen's English was at the top
the convicts might have thrown off their
physical shackles but the local language
wouldn't lose its chains until the late
20th century just as in the Caribbean
English was still keeping its children
down
but all Australia was eager for a sight
of this young woman yeah - it was the
first time that the reigning sovereign
had landed on Australia's Shores
the British Empire by the turn of the
20th century was in its heyday and
British interests as every schoolchild
knew then had taken the english language
all around the globe the spread of the
language was inseparable from the
growing feeling of superiority which
marked the empire its people when Daniel
Defoe's shipwrecked Robinson Crusoe
encountered the man he called Friday the
first English word he taught his new
acquaintance was master there was no
question about who was in charge and no
question about the language they'd use
as the empire spread cruisers attitude
became the norm around the world
English pushed hundreds of local
languages aside in some cases it could
be said to have killed them off less
than half the Aboriginal languages
survived and they now face extinction
North American languages also suffered
among them Lakota the language of
Sitting Bull and the Sioux people did
you speak Lakota to your grandfather
yeah otherwise you wouldn't understand
me if I start speaking English we have
to learn the English and if we speak
Indian to each other then both of us
have to go up to that there's teachers
deaf and she makes us stand in front she
gets his big ruler about this long and
this thick and she slaps on him it says
it's already and they won't let us speak
our language because I think the return
that changed us into whiteness you know
cooking Juli sitting bullying someone
did hurt each other so like ortho out
there how much of it
I spoke to Dolores blacksmith in Chicago
but you don't have to go that far around
the world to find examples of English
bullying no further than Wales
the military political and social
dominance of the English over the Welsh
has always been reflected in their
languages when the two countries were
united in 1536 there was no law actually
to prohibit the speaking of Welsh but no
one who insisted on using Welsh was
allowed to hold an official position a
prejudice against the Welsh had been
established it continued by 1847 a Royal
Commission declared that the Welsh
language is a vast drawback to Wales and
a manifold barrier to the moral progress
and commercial prosperity of the people
and the Education Act of 1870 dictated
that children would have to learn
English in school rooms like this it
could lead to unfortunate even cruel
practices Welsh wasn't banned but some
teachers and schools outlawed it in the
classroom in some cases a token like
this the letters WN stand for Welsh
naught was placed around the neck of any
child slipping back into their first
language child was encouraged to inform
one child or Welsh on them that's where
the term came from and humiliation was
used as a cultural weapon a wish from
the valuing an order in the last year's
in the 19th century there was a push to
revive the Welsh language it was led by
the future Prime Minister of Britain
Lloyd George the National Eisteddfod
continued to promote and celebrate Welsh
language and culture bilingual signage
and official literature were introduced
in the 60s so that today the Welsh
language can be seen everywhere
throughout Wales but it's debatable
whether all this has really been enough
to turn the tide in 1900 half the people
in Wales spoke well by 1981 it was less
than one in five
the story seemed to be one of a long and
irreversible decline while English
marched on from strength to strength
just this year though surveys have shown
that the number of Welsh speakers is
increasing for the first time in two
centuries Welsh has found its way back
into the school rooms but it's still a
minority language 80 percent of Welsh
people don't speak it at all and its
future is far from certain but at least
the days of the Welsh note are over and
in Wales as elsewhere in the world
English is no longer acting as a
state-approved bully as the British
Empire has faded away English has had to
come to terms with a changed world
reaching accommodations with local
languages and with new political
realities
here in India the new constitution which
followed independence plan to abolish
English altogether and instead make
Hindi the sole official language but it
didn't happen
Hindi is only the first language in some
states of India and other parts of their
own languages like here in Calcutta and
the rest of Bengal where Bengali is
spoken regional rivalries are often
fierce and so the users of other
languages exerted political pressure in
some places even wyott it to keep
English rather than be forced to use
Hindi and even the most cursory glance
at any of these bookstores here in
Kolkata will show you how English is
still part of Indian life its minority
language but it's the language in which
many Indian states communicate with each
other and with the outside world and
that gives it tremendous part some would
say too much
it's 7:30 a.m. in Calcutta the
Tollygunge Club is the favorite meeting
place for the state's top officials and
captains of industry for these people
English is a badge indicating that part
of India's social and ruling elite
across town in another world Street
children are being taught the basics for
them English might mean a finger hole
the scrap of advantage in getting a job
against desparate all across India
parents of all classes will make great
efforts to make English part of their
child's education
for this man English is the language he
must hire to deal with the bureaucracy
of taxing a car for this man it's
essential to his business
somebody came and hit the vehicle many
Indians sleep happily from English into
the native Bengali or Hindi and back
again for them English has become in a
sense another Indian language
in other parts of the former Empire
English and his linguistic offspring
have also had to come to terms with
independence in Australia it came later
the election of the Whitlam government
in 1972 rode a wave of nationalism
Australia began to look back towards
Britain less than it looked forward to
its own future as a multicultural
country four years later the first
Australian dictionary to be compiled in
Australia reached the bookshelves
helping to legitimize the language and
showing that Australia had cast off its
cultural cringe and was ready to revel
in its own distinctive language this is
the Macario dictionary in the in the DS
alone you find Australian words like
dagi meaning dirty or slovenly from DAGs
the name given to the matted Tufts of
wool around a sheep's bottom dead has
room in a hotel where drunks are put to
sleep it off delle a shortened form of
delegate dingo stiffener a dingo hunter
dogs an exclamation mark dog eye an
Aboriginal English word for a white
person drag an adjective depressingly
unattractive possibly from Dracula and
Donnie an outside toilet a name that can
be traced back to the English words
Donna meaning dong and Ken meaning place
or house in old British dialects you
could find Daniken or Dunnigan the
Australian shortened it and keep it in
use
vocabulary aside Australian English has
developed some distinct variations in
return good no I'm done by secular
campus and bricky
I think there are two features that
really earmark Australian English at
least for me
one is the abbreviations that Straley in
love of shortenings so that a word if
it's not a ready a single syllable gets
reduced to a single syllable and then an
ending is I'm going on e ending or an O
ending so something like my mate Jacko
the weirdo Jono from Frio he slept on a
bit of lino during your smoker one arvo
and ended up on compo and a real vero
another characteristic I think of
Australian English is the sometimes
called HRT this is not hormone
replacement therapy but high-rise
terminal
it's the Australian questioning
intonation so it really is like the
rising intonation of a yes/no question
except that you find it on statements
like one of the servo and here in
Australia you encounter quite well
amused probably even hostile reactions
now to British receive pronunciation and
Queen's English people find them
affected now and they're wanting much
more to speak Australian English
independence reached the West Indies in
the 1960s and with it came a
determination to reject the colonial
past in ordered sports here in Jamaica
there's been a campaign to make patois
the local speech a socially acceptable
as standard English it's all around and
no longer regarded as a badge of social
inferiority
anybody who wants to communicate for the
public feel effectively in a language of
of feeling and a language that will get
them to move and uses abundance of
Muhammad obviously wanted to popular
music it's a region region top shoes are
largely carried out in Jamaican even by
people who can speak English it was not
the language of hostility for illiterate
ignorant people
patois on the airwaves or in the
dancehall is one thing for it to be
tolerated or encouraged in the
schoolroom is another not if you work
with the top chapter anything governor
of env people - how are you is when
Jamaica was under slavery because Caesar
was abolished the breaks there are those
like the purge and performer Joan Andrew
Hutchinson who actively promote patois
among children but it's not government
policy yet to teach it in schools here a
standard English is still the norm and
there are those who argue the children
educated in partner at the expense of
English will be placed at a serious
disadvantage in dealing with the rest of
the english-speaking world and see
typical anglo-saxon response the
anglo-saxons seem to think that people
can only speak one language right in
fact Molly's multilingualism bilingual
reserve is the norm there's no
particular reason why Jamaica will be
cut off simply because Jamaicans used to
make up all right the language is
popularly called password for purposes
of organizing their lives internally and
using English for international
communication but I think it's a mindset
an anglo-saxon I'm certain which our
English is the official language of
written in the US and is also an
international language absolutely our
history
historically English began its Imperial
adventure as an export from our Islands
it's for new English's new varieties
that were at first despised by speakers
from the mother country which grew into
distinct from national tongues as their
speakers freed themselves from their
colonial past today English and his
offspring stand side-by-side around the
world a world in which English as we'll
see has adopted a crucial role as a
global language
you