saluton kai bon venon ala lhasa program
all on shi xuxia do and for those of you
don't speak Esperanto I just said hello
and welcome to the last program in the
adventure of English it's often argued
that the modern world needs a common
language with which to communicate
that's why Esperanto was invented in the
late 19th century with a dream of
providing an artificial second language
for all the people of the world there'd
been numerous attempts and similar
schemes but none of them anywhere near
as popular as a language which spread by
natural selection through the 20th
century English English can now claim to
be a global language more so than any
other language in history
I'm in Chicago the Windy City the 20th
century could be said to begin here in
1871 a fire had destroyed old Chicago
but within two years an entire new city
was built for a new century with a huge
charge of economic and technical
development America was about to burst
onto the global stage the German
Chancellor Otto von Bismarck said near
the end of the 19th century the decisive
element of modern history is the fact
that the North Americans speak English
but there were now two English Azur one
language that we might call English -
American or American - English and the
story of the last century is how these
two English's have grown together
sometimes in harmony
sometimes in competition
America was flexing its economic muscles
at that time and the words and phrases
reflect that big business executive
well-heeled fat cat go-getter and
yes-man as well as assembly line and
close shop they're all American English
Europe and its towers but it took
America to build and to name that
quintessential image of the country the
skyscraper
the first skyscraper ever was built here
in Chicago in 1885 it's been knocked
down but this one was built soon
afterwards it's now the oldest one still
standing in Chicago now it's a hotel
hotel in the modern sense is an American
word in French she just meant a large
private house and it was in America that
they first called this reception area a
lobby with this desk clock I mean Clerk
dressed in black of course at the front
desk is bellhop and it's concierge
another European word given its modern
meaning in America to get to your
penthouse if you should be so lucky you
would of course need an elevator English
already had the rather less technical
word lifts but as Oscar Wilde inevitably
said we have really everything in common
with America nowadays except of course
language you can see it everywhere I'm
gonna tell gives us quite a few examples
in England we would have a wardrobe this
is a closet in England we have a
bathroom well that's the same but could
also be called a washroom the tub with a
faucet not a bath with the tap and when
we go into the bedroom at least that's
the same word we find that the window
has drapes not curtains the bed has
covers not bedclothes instead of a
dressing gown here's a bathrobe beside
the bed there's a nightstand not a
bedside table and somewhere there's a
trashcan not a wastepaper basket the
British had long looked down on the way
the Americans used the language color
age thought the word talented was a vile
and barbarous American word but he was
in fact English Dickens noted how they
corrupted the language with words like
reliable and lengthy there's always been
some perhaps misinformed resistance to
American words but the Americans had
never cared much for English opinion
about their use of the English language
the bird what Whitman observed in 1888
that American English was the apotheosis
of slang a glorious new language he said
reinvented away from the traditions and
authority of British English
two days ago let's go for the one-on-one
and with omelet you also get a corn
muffin a biscuit or toast you guys get
growth you get Apple maple or chicken in
doing the psychiatry's looked at we
should point out that the increase will
not be any more than this day means
right where they're writing over 2600
and a quarter
all righty in Britain correct English
was linked with manners morals and of
course class just as one had to keep a
straight bat and hold ones knife and
fork correctly so one had to use the
right word use the wrong one and you
could be caught out and ward in English
abhorred flamboyance when somebody wrote
a group had broke the young poet who
died during the first world war that he
left Cambridge University in a blaze of
glory the poet's mother crossed out that
melodramatic phrase and replaced it with
a single word he read he left Cambridge
University in July in part here was a
case of British formality versus
American informality American was
thought to be a classless version of
English and there were those in at
Warner Society
who found that idea difficult to
tolerate but the First World War would
test and change most of them
Edwardian English like its Victorian
parent love pageantry pomp and a society
where every word knew its place the
trenches of the First World War
detonated much of that the First World
War gave us new figures of speech as
well as a vision of equality here in the
trenches before the war if you were in
trouble
or under pressure you might have said
you'd been thrown like a horse rider
into a wasteland or a swamp perhaps
under a shower of criticism words drawn
from peaceful country life after 1918
you'd probably say you're being
bombarded under a barrage shell-shocked
or in no-man's land the First World War
gave British English firepower and
frontline gas masks and camouflage bunk
for tishell with artillery and done for
defective round the balloon goes up was
the signal for the artillery to open
fire at zero are over the top comes from
the terrifying moment of climbing out of
the trench the biblical phrase at the
11th hour gained a new meaning from the
time the final ceasefire was declared on
Armistice Day all terms from the very
end of world war war when the armistice
finally came more than the first world
war was over it underlined what was
already a trend the shift of power in
many areas including language to America
while Europe had been burning the USA
had experienced massive industrial
expansion
the factories of the northern states
needed new workers and the poor of the
South many of the descendants of former
slaves saw the opportunity they offered
and moved in
the migrants overwhelmingly black came
along tracks like these and railroads
like these they came to the cities of
the north cities like Chicago pounding
with growth then and pounding with
growth now and they changed America they
also changed the English language in the
nineteenth century almost all Afro
Americans had lived in the south by the
end of the century ninety five percent
were up in the north and they injected
the new energies of the language they
brought African speech African rhythm
new vocabulary together and put black
speech into mainstream American was
music first jazz then blues new words
and expressions started to accompany the
soundtrack of what America's perhaps
best known for popular culture today the
language would be unimaginable without
its colonization by words and
expressions of black and African origin
the very words jazz and blues arrived
from a pro-american speech at the
beginning of the century the African
word hypocrite
meaning attuned to the environment or
with his eyes open gave us hepcat and
later hip and cat later still of course
its meaning grew to include the idea of
hippie white American embraced black
American speech when people started to
dance the hootchy-kootchy and then the
cakewalk the shimmy jive and boogie
woogie
and perhaps it was the sex in black
music that seduced white America jazz
itself may originally have been a word
meaning to have sex later on rock and
roll certainly was Jelly Roll cherry pie
and custard pie were all words of the
female organ Shack up in the sense of
living together comes from black speech
at this time to Black American
expressions are now so mainstream that
it's forgotten almost all Americans and
very many British including almost all
youths now speak some sort of black
young people want to be cool or bad
which was first recorded as meaning good
in America in 1928 and this might want
to be groovy or mellow which came from
melody in jazz circles in the early 40s
Square is out but it may come back
thank you but it wasn't just black words
flooding into American English in the
early 20th century around that time the
country's population nearly doubled in
just 30 years mainly due to incomers
from Central and Eastern Europe as more
Europeans migrated here and began to
speak English words from their own
languages came with an American English
like English English before it was ready
enabled to soak them all up and what the
France forum now sounds apple-pie
American English
if this coffee had been really hot
someone it might have said ouch from the
German word ouch aut s CH as well as
hamburger and frankfurter the Germans
gave us words like wonder list seminar
dumb for stupid and even the game of
poker from the German fortune bond
meaning trap comes from bumbler a
good-for-nothing hold on
from Pelton and so long from the German
Zoo langa langa itself may originally
come from the it is Shalom bagels locked
pastrami and borscht became part about
not another Yiddish word soon German and
Yiddish speech patterns flooded the
language and by the end of the century
we would all quite naturally be using
turns of phrase such as am i hungry I'm
telling you now he tells me could I use
a drink
I should worry and there was plenty to
worry about in the 1920s the prohibition
of alcohol encouraged gangsters and in a
garage on this unremarkable site seven
men were moaned down by Al Capone's mob
in the notorious cent Valentine's Day
Massacre it was a time of racketeers and
hatchet men of goons and Fink's if you
took the rap for a heist you might find
yourself in the can or even in the hot
seat especially for a hijack with the
submachine gun
a woman was a chick a bimbo a broad or a
babe and the telephone was a blower we
learned not to spill the beans or we'd
be taken for a ride and to avoid
gimmicks and pranksters junkies pushers
and the fuzz and when we drank hooch
we had to watch out for
gangsters are forever linked with the
movies never more so than here John
Dillinger the FBI's public enemy number
one was gunned down as he left the
Biograph movie theater in 1934 he was
fingered or betrayed by his companion
the notorious lady in red she's still
here by the 1930s motion pictures and
sound had been united and the talkies
were in full swing bringing a new
vocabulary going to the movies at a
movie theater on Nickelodeon was a
national pastime you could see the stars
in closer in a weeping or a tearjerker
laughs at some slapstick I'll be gripped
by a spine chiller or a cliffhanger
while the usherette was selling Isis you
could watch a trailer for next week's
show you might even dream of going for a
screen test to yourself more than
anything else the talking picture would
be the engine-- to spread American ideas
and american english from hollywood
around the country and then around the
globe over the next century
but back in britain their language
caused an outrage
the words and accents were perfectly
disgusting and there can be no doubt
that such films are an evil influence on
our society those truly loathsome
transatlantic importation z' to help
meit worthwhile nearby and colorful are
spreading like the plague but with the
popularity of Hollywood those complaints
were simply swept aside by most people
in Britain films were starting to bring
the two languages closer together
but despite the incursions of its
vigorous cousin English in the UK was
alive and well with its own style and
also with an awareness of American
influence PG Woodhouse defined himself
in some measure by stressing Englishness
yet he was informal and up-to-date with
phrase making as you
see for a couple surprises she had a
penetrating sort of laughs rather like a
train going into a tunnel you could say
first avid warden English second North
American English or the such a thing is
going too far and you have gone it again
could be it warden and America would
house came to school here a Dulwich
College in London and he left the school
his books and the desk on which he wrote
many of them and a writer regarded as
the epitome of American style also came
here to Dodge College
Raymond Chandler was seven years younger
than Woodhouse he was born in Chicago
but came to England as a young boy and
became naturalized British at the age of
19 from the Edwardian playing fields of
Dulwich College came Blandings and
Jeeves in a timeless England and the
mean streets of LA and Phillip Marlowe
in a timeless America Marla is the name
of a house of this school just as
Woodhouse played with British English
chandra played with american english
making it elegant but tough it was a
blonde a blonde to make a bishop pick a
hole in a stained-glass window she gave
me a smile I could feel in my hip pocket
in the air Chandler published the
entertaining American prose of farewell
my lovely Hitler was preparing to invade
England and make German the common
language of Europe different situations
make different demands on a language we
shall go on to the end which will fight
on the Seas and oceans we should fight
in the air which will fight on the
beaches we shall fight on the landing
grounds we shall fight in the fields and
in the streets we shall fight in the
Hills we shall never surrender this is
part of Churchill's War Rooms on the
ground behind Downing Street and from
this desk
he made his broadcasts to the nation in
1940 Britain stood alone against Hitler
Winston Churchill made a speech which
drew on the deep historical roots of the
English language it's a masterpiece of
rhythm and rhetoric Churchill had
studied the speeches of Elizabeth the
first and this has the same resolve as
her words at Tilbury which inspired the
English to repulse the Spanish Armada
and it digs deeper into the history of
English all but a handful of words here
can be traced back to Old English the
key vocabulary we shall go on to the end
fight strength Island landing ground
field Street hills and never had all
been part of English for more than a
thousand years
Churchill was rallying some of the
country's oldest words to the fight not
to the battle that was a French word and
surrender to is a French word the
hostile Nazi invasion never came but in
1942 a friendly American one did nothing
could reverse the effects of such
sustained exposure to American English
the GIS introduced words like beef
burger crew-cut and disc jockey gizmo
gobbledygook pinup and GI bride but the
traffic was not all one way the
Americans published this book a short
guide to Great Britain the war and Navy
Department Washington DC for all the
troops in this country it's very
friendly and I think a cute about the
British the British were reserved it
says but not unfriendly then it
describes it don't show off it says the
British dislike showing off don't say
you've got too much money you've got
much more than the British and don't
show off about it they learn how to eat
they learned that french fries with
chips and a smoked herring was a kipper
they learnt at bowling alleys and
tenpins
we're skipper Holly's with nine things
but a five and ten store should be
called a bazaar and then instead of okay
they should say right oh and they were
told the British are tough don't be
misled by the British tendency to be
soft-spoken and polite the English
language didn't spread across oceans
mountains jungles and swamps of the
world because these people were
pantywaists pantywaist that's American
English thought the British would have
called a by 1944 on the eve of
d-day one and a half million United
States soldiers were billeted around
grim
the Americans eventually returned home
but the language they brought with them
stayed ever since and English was
massively enriched
in March 2000 the Pope made his historic
first ever visit to Israel on this
important occasion he addressed his
hosts not in their own language Hebrew
nor in the Vatican's official language
Latin nor in his native polish but in
English may peace be last given through
the lab he chose English has become the
primary language of global communication
the most understood language in the
world so why has English becomes so
important on the world stage 19th
century linguists felt that there was
something special and unique about the
language itself in 1851 Jakob Grimm of
the Brothers Grimm told the Royal
Academy of Berlin that English was the
strongest language because it had
dropped all its complicated word endings
he wrote of all modern languages not one
has acquired such a great strength and
vigor as the English for none of the
living languages can be compared with it
as to richness rationality and close
construction you'd be hard-pressed to
find any linguist today who'd follow
that line or even a less triumphalist
argument put forward by another foreign
scholar the Dane Otto Jespersen in 1905
he wrote the French language is like the
stiff French garden lure the four teams
while the English language is like an
English Park in which are allowed to
walk everywhere without having to fear
rigorous regulations but most linguist
today would agree not with the genius of
Jakob Grimm but with the linguistic
scholar David crystal but the spread of
a language is little to do with its
intrinsic qualities social political and
economic factors are now seen as the
forces behind the spread of languages
there's a saying among linguists that a
language is a dialect with an army in
the Navy so a language that spreads just
has more quite
at the end of the Second World War
British and American troops were
stationed as administrators in Europe
and the Far East in Japan learning
English became compulsory in Germany
knowing English gave people an edge in
dealing with officials and regulations
after the Reich and a world impoverished
by the war turned his eyes anxiously to
the American dream expressing not only
the American love of beauty but also the
basic freedom of the American people and
the language of that dream was English a
language that came to represent the
delights of consumption and consumerism
of material advance and its promise of
happiness but perhaps the most desirable
consumer product at the end of the 20th
century was first developed in England
in Manchester
it made the English language adapt and
expand to a whole new vocabulary in 1948
this was the state of the art of what
the boffins were calling the electronic
brain the computing machine or the
electronic numerical integrator and
computer the baby as this rather large
piece of hardware was christened was the
first distorted digital program in his
2:04 8-bit memory in the essence baby
received its first input of data the
computer in its vocabulary have embraced
the micro circuit the database the chip
and the mass the floppy disk and the
hard disk we progressed from the
mainframe to the desktop the laptop to
the handheld and now even a cell phone
like this can download information from
the internet and with an estimated 85%
of the world's web pages being written
in English this newest technology has
become one of the great Congress taking
the English language around the world
with the dollar leading the world
economy in the latter part of the 20th
century English became the most
significant trading language global
trade in English is reckoned to be worth
over 4000 billion dollars that's three
or four times as much of the next
richest languages Japanese and German
though Chinese is more native speakers
than English trade conducted in Chinese
is just one tenth of the value of trade
in English
can shoot what color do you like I have
a tie dye and with petrol and a pen
color
there's an international rule the seller
speaks the buyers language if I want
your money
it pays me to learn to talk to you in
your language it's the same on a larger
scale whether selling postcards to
sightseers or raw materials to
industrialists English opens the purse
strings some 40 million people speak
English fluently as if it were a first
language mostly two second or third
language but it's reckoned that a third
of the population here have some sort of
familiarity with the language and that's
over 300 million people and that pattern
is repeated around the globe wherever
there's a population of English speakers
you'll find a much larger number of
people who come into contact with it and
have some knowledgeable or at least
learning it now is their time to relax
and enjoy the program in the second half
of the 20th century the number of people
speaking English as their first language
has doubled to nearly 400 million
though it's still not as many as the 900
million who speak Mandarin Chinese
national English international ranges
today however there are another 500
million people around the world who are
bilingual in English or at least speak
it fluently it's here that the big
expansion has taken place the number has
quadrupled in 50 years but because of
its usefulness as a second language some
thousand million other people are
learning English in schools and colleges
add it together
that's about 2000 million people or a
third of the world's population who have
some knowledge of English it's an
unprecedented expansion English is now
used as an official or semi official
language in over 60 countries around the
world and plays a significant role in 20
more the English is now well established
on all six continents and it doesn't
stop there because in all sorts of ways
when nation needs to speak on to nation
they do it at the European Parliament in
Strasbourg business in the Chairman is
translated into all the languages of the
Member States
ten years ago French was the language
most commonly used by delegates outside
the chamber today is English final
European Parliament documents are
translated into all languages but it's
the language they are drafted in that's
changed in 1970 60% of EU documents were
drafted in French and 40% in German by
1997 45% were drafted in English 40% in
French and 15% in other Union
English plays the leading role not just
here at the EU but in international
bodies around the world the United
Nations NATO the World Bank and hundreds
of other associations English is
important even when it's not the natural
language of the major players it's the
only official language of OPEC the
Organization of Petroleum Exporting
Countries it's the working language of
the European free trade association at
the association of Baltic marine
biologists the Asian Amateur Athletic
Association the European Association of
fish pathology and the African Hockey
Federation whatever country they come
from most medical journals are published
in English like this one
the Japanese Journal of biochemistry
it's not translated into English it's
published only in English and it's
writers include tatsuo hamada yuki
tatsuko Quintero cattle almost anywhere
that a body wants to communicate with
the world or where they want access to
the literature of international politics
ideas culture and sport you'll find
English in Germany international
corporations such as Daimler and
Mercedes conduct important meetings in
English and thousands of English words
have made their way into German speech
and print from a counted acid trip an
advertising agency to yellow pages
yuppie and Zappa a movement has been
started to hold back words for which
there's already a German equivalent
though when it's a choice between
pesticide and um crowd penetrance Mittal
the smart money is on the import but
this opposition is nothing compared to
France where the tide of frog glare was
seen as a national threat just as we
took in thousands of French words in the
Middle Ages French speakers and writers
today are taking on thousands of English
and American expressions I meet you
whose
in garden party basketball the
downloader the football this girl sub
drink coq10 and jumbo jet that's coach
on which the Bohemian Wendy Club
so many English words made away the
France then it became clear that
something had to be done and in 1994 the
French government passed a law
prohibiting the use of English words
we're good
French equivalents existed on pain of a
hefty fine the British Parliament
threatened retaliate reaction if left to
ball as it was called was not watered
down but the most recent edition of the
Academie Francaise dictionary did admit
about 6,000 new words to the French
language including for the first time a
number of from glare words and
expressions well most of them from the
1950s such as the covergirl the best
seller and the blue jeans most of those
in everyday use from the weekend d'leh
zoom were excluded it's not just the old
english french rivalry Norway and Brazil
have recently adopted similar measures
to keep English out it's a colorful
words that people want to borrow from
English but the language uses a tool for
international documents is a different
matter this is a sample it's an English
that bears only a passing resemblance to
the language you and I speak according
to Article 7 of directive 96 struck 92
struck EC member states must designate a
system operator to be responsible for
operating ensuring the maintenance of an
if necessary
developing the transmission system in a
given area and it's interconnection with
other systems etc mind you there are
places in England where they write like
this we've all been globalized it's very
important and it's very dull it's this
official sort of language that's being
promoted around the world by government
bodies multinational corporations and
the international associations it's
stripped out terms of speech and
colorful idioms deliberately so because
this is language designed to be easily
understood internationally and local
terms could be confusing this sort of
globalization I think could become a
cemetry for English is anyone ever going
to write a poem in this sort of language
or use it when they fall in love or when
they have a real row
or express any of the personal feelings
they have but thankfully as English
spreads around the globe alongside its
official use it has developed rich
vernacular varieties English has been
spoken in Singapore since the early 19th
century but after independence from
Britain in 1958 Singapore went a step
further and English was made the
official language of business and
government besides its ability to unite
an ethnically diverse population of
Chinese Malays and Indians the economic
potential of English was paramount at
school children learn their own first
language but they must all learn English
an elite minority language has become
the property of the whole population but
the day-to-day English that the people
of Singapore actually speak is a far cry
from the official English of the
government wants them to learn it's a
vibrant expressive dialect nicknamed
Singlish full of vocabulary grammar and
inflections borrowed from the
Singaporeans languages regional so all
the know not my liner I know I know this
is it now my zone and this may be the
irony of the global spread of English
the more widely spoken the more it may
fracture into local dialects which
become increasingly mutually
unintelligible
people will make English their own and
in doing so will make it something else
there's a certain before to Latin which
broke into French Italian Spanish
Portuguese in Romania but English has
always embraced variety in change and it
still does and in the final part of our
final program I'd be looking at how
English is behaving now in this country
in this series have looked at how
English began as an obscure tribal
dialect 1,500 years ago and became a
language for the world spoken more
widely and with more variety than any
other language in history for this the
final part of the final program I want
to go down these islands to take
soundings of the state of English in its
homeland today
when English came here in the fifth
century it began to push the Celtic
languages to the fringes to the margins
to Wales of course to Cornwall and here
to the Outer Hebrides and in all those
places it's hung on I'm on Ness at the
northern tip of the Outer Hebrides and
the language around here spoken by
almost everyone is Scots Gaelic it's one
of UNESCO s endangered languages but so
far it's hung on almost miraculously but
now after 1,500 years it's facing its
biggest battle ever against the still
relentless advance of English did you
have English and Gaelic when you went to
school in Bathurst I'm a staff member
but I don't think I had a one word of
English
this traditional Hobart en villages
abandoned 30 years ago a local
population in our bilingual but these
adults grew up speaking only Gallic and
had to learn English at school I think
we could they could catch and I would
think and part of the alphabet but it
wasn't a totally strange language to me
as I remember well we have a seat yeah I
think I was totally bilingual by the
time I left secondary school my
grandfather's generation would speak
English in a way different from what we
would we were very conscious that they
were a literal translation that they
were as we would put it at that time
that they were less advanced there's
still some of that today and in the time
that it's after being here I was after
talking to somebody or after being
somewhere but unless the yourself or
myself
did you stuff your snap yes when do
people with me say it's yourself yes
although youngsters nowadays they've got
whatever transfers across from the media
but if you're talking about something
like pop music or something in the media
that you've seen you're not going to
talk about it in Gaelic when it's been
in English that you've actually seen it
but division forwards and garlic which
describe situations so much better
for example key analyst is whom well
it's more than homesickness
but you see Skype homesickness but it
takes in sort of nostalgia and a lot of
feeling more more so than homesickness
and the same applies to old man we would
use the word bother the old Bo doctor in
the road until the old bottle next door
I would speak Alec to my grandmother and
my mother but to my friends I speak
English galaxies to have an image
problem amongst the young people I mean
we used to speak garlic all the time we
were in primary school but if you have
one person who comes into your classes
speaks English everybody has to change
order that person's isolated so ever
since then I mean we've been speaking
English to everybody was just so used to
it no to have it the English spoken here
still has a tang of the Gallic but his
age is getting duller it's sounding more
and more gradually like the language of
the mainland but how stable is that
English continues to demel a way up here
and if even louis weakens can glasgow be
far behind
Glasgow has some of the most distinctive
voices in Britain companies like a call
centres here because they think that the
softer version of the glass region
accent is one of the most trustworthy
and friendly in the country I'll send an
email to Azure and request but at its
broadest glass region dialect is
farthest away from standard English it
can be virtually incomprehensible to
outside many Daleks have eroded to the
extent that they're just accents but
other dialects have retained their
distinctive nature glass region is a
dialect which is made up of a rain
actually two different forms of English
Scottish English which was taken over in
the 18th century which is essentially
standard English spoken with a Scottish
accent and then Scots which has its own
distinctive historical development for
example Old English air is head
infantile English that has been retained
but in Scotland is II so it's he'd
glasgow university sends researchers
into the streets to monitor changes in
speech right so one at a time this
gentleman says on that card
this house this this
with Old English who is still in Scots
today so they say moose what about the
accent does that also change over time
we have for example further now in
cockney it's very normal safe I think
but up here it isn't however it is now
thank thank
but inevitably there has been
speculation that it's the media that
it's watching soaps it's watching TV I'm
particularly southern English forms of
TV that are causing these changes but
there's a problem here there's no real
research to actually establish this
empirically have you any examples of
very recent new Glaswegian words the one
that we've been quite excited about is
nip it's a verb and an example of nip
would be I nicked her I saw her nipping
him can you think of any words that you
know what it means it seems to mean
something like kiss or smell probably
get off with there's a lot of talk about
this particular time the last 25 the
last 50 years being the period when
region like sense retreated and began to
die what happens do we have for that
here an accent is actually a combination
of features and so you can change
certain features in the same way in
Glasgow and in Redding but because the
original combination of features that
you started off with and Redding in
Glasgow were different although you have
the same changes for some of the
features the rest the features are quite
different so the resulting mix will
remain distinctive so my feeling from
looking at glass region at the moment is
that actually glass region will retain
its distinctiveness
as we look back at the adventure of
English we've steamed through centuries
and so we've been able to see sweeping
changes in the vocabulary and the way it
was used but many changes in language
have happened over a long period and in
small steps word by word and sound by
sound so when we look at the way
language is changing now all round us
it's not so easy to see the bigger
picture or where the changes are leading
which currents are influences will mark
out the future one of the greatest
causes of change in English has been
extinct and with other cultures and
other tongues these encounters are still
happening today my next stop is Bradford
to see this in action Bradford has one
of the largest concentration of South
Asian populations in Britain they're
about 1.7 million who have come to this
country from South Asia from India
Pakistan Bangladesh making it the
biggest ethnic minority many of those
who came in the first instance didn't
speak English but as their children were
born here and went through the British
school system they did speak English
they do speak English at school at least
here they speak Yorkshire English
welcome to the tale of a delicious
adventure in a wonderful land Kate but
that the name will tell much either way
she barely comes into the story but if
wishes were fishes I'd bet with all
throw them back the first language of
these children's parents and
grandparents is usually who do open job
and that's often the language of the
children speak at home and these
languages are greatly complicated and
enriched the Yorkshire English they
speak at school and on the streets I
speak half English and half Punjabi when
I'm talking to my mates if I if I know I
can't said this word in English I will
say in my home language means I swear
like I swear I won't do that again
I found with my white friends and you
know like accidentally I would say it
cussed me I really did this and they say
what is cussed me and then I'll say it
means I swear I swear you know I'm being
honest when they use the word curse
middle elven is quite funny the way they
say no
may not happen you know they'll use the
language as well very differently as
well for something but they don't know
they say the same thing the only well
Punjabi would be use when we text in his
odd the rest is all short English that
you probably use when you're on the
internet sending a message English is
borrowing adopting changing altering
words all the time as we've seen
throughout these programs it's a massive
job keeping track of them being as it
were the keeper of words if anyone body
deserves to be called the keeper of the
English language
it's the Oxford English Dictionary and
that's my next stop we've been
travelling down the country from the
Hebrides south just taking soundings has
taught the languages like these days and
I wondered how these figured in the in
your dictionary from the Japanese
there's Buddha an old man yeah and I
believe that would actually still is in
it is it is in the Oxford English
Dictionary sense of an old intensive and
it's like earlier sense I'm a suspect
our spectral prisons in Glasgow there's
the word nip being used to get off with
it's not in the dictionary yet in that
last sense no we haven't got enough
evidence for it we're looking for fairly
fairly extensive evidence from from
Glasgow or elsewhere in Bradford where
the Punjab Ian would do influence the
several words casmi meaning I swear
there's war how is it going anchovies
Underpants shudders is in the OED are
already possibly from it from a Hindi
word that's but she that's one of these
wizards achieved some sort of currency
through the media through television and
the other words that you mentioned you
know they're not in the dictionary yet
again this is a borderline area the
interface between cultures it's always
an interesting area for linguistic
description and will tend to wait
several years before a word to find some
sort of
more established place in the language
before we put it into the dictionary the
operation going behind us here is a sort
of scientific investigation of the
language evidence starts coming into our
car files and my computer files which
we're monitoring and we can see that it
it's maybe significant because so much
of language is just some sparks that
disappear let's talk about slang about
bling bling bling bling
meaning the ostentatious jewelry or as
an adjective relating to that
ostentatious wealth for that sort of
thing it crops up five or six years ago
but but this stayed around so it's on
the way into the dictionaries not there
yet but it's on the way and it's been
being reviewed by our revised advisors
over at the moment what about the
relation between English English an
American English and now other languages
the whole concept of different varieties
of English is obviously more important
now than it was or more recognized now
than it was twenty or thirty years ago
so whereas at the time you might have
thought of British English and American
English as being the main features on
the linguistic landscape people talk
about the different Englishes as I sort
of know you can count these days so you
can have a plural English's with
American English Australian English
Singapore English Indian English etc etc
and they've all got their own
characteristics
so they independent in many ways but
they also feed into a general sort of
internet English information what's the
size of the dictionary at the moment
about seven hundred and fifty thousand
words this is covering English from the
anglo-saxon period up to the present day
yes Valley tough require so taking was
in do you ever dispense it was you ever
let words drop kick them out them we
have a very simple rule for leaving for
picking with an addition as we don't
once the words in in the full oxford
english dictionary it stays there
because it's part of the history of the
English language so once it's in it's
there
well you got any favorite ones you want
us to take the adventure of English
began 15 centuries ago when invading
Germanic tribes brought their dialects
here from mainland Europe English
survived against the odds facing near
extinction from other invaders and other
languages before becoming our national
tongue over the last five centuries as
we've seen settlement and subjugation
industry and imperialism armies and art
have combined to make it a language not
for this country alone but for the world
but the adventure has already gone even
further a quarter of a century ago NASA
launched its two Voyager probes into
deep space at the end of 2003 they're
heading out of our solar system in the
hope of contact with unknown forms of
life each probe carries a gold-plated
recorded disk designed to last 4,000
million years in space and on each disk
there are brief greetings in 55 of the
planet's languages the only long message
recorded by the then secretary of the
United Nations Kurt Waldheim is in
English I send greetings on behalf of
the people of our planet we step out of
our solar system into the universe
seeking only peace and friendship to
teach if we are called upon
English is on its way to the stars but
the story of English has also been one
of constant changes in the language it's
never stood still as we've seen so if a
thousand years or more in the future
people meet life from other planets who
have learned their 20th century English
from Voyager it'll sound a strange and
archaic to English speakers here in the
future as the earliest anglo-saxon does
to us today what we got a dinner NER of
the one field cooling a throng of Hunan
who the Alpha Lingus Ellen from adore in
the beginning was the word and the Word
was with God and the Word was God and
the Word was made flesh and dwelt among
us
you