this is the south bank in London
two thousand years ago if you had heard
a human voice around here the language
would have been incomprehensible a
thousand years ago the English language
had established its first base camp
today English circles the globe it
inhabits the air we breathe
what started as a guttural tribal
dialect seemingly isolated in a small
island is now the language of well over
a thousand million people around the
world
you
the story of the English language is an
extraordinary one it has the
characteristics of a bold and successful
adventure tenacity luck near extinction
on more than one occasion
dazzling flexibility and an
extraordinary power to absorb and it's
still going on
new dialects new English's are evolving
all the time all over the world
successive invasions introduced then
threatened to destroy our language our
first program tells that story
for 300 years English was forced
underground our second program tells how
it survived and how it fought back
our third program will tell how the
English language took on the power
blocks of church and state
1/4 how it became the language of
Shakespeare in later programs were going
to leave these shores as English did to
tell the story of how in America the
language of one great Empire became that
of another we'll go to the Caribbean
where a variety of new part English
dialects took root India where English
became a commanding unifying language in
a country of a thousand tons and
Australia where a confident new English
was invented by a people many of whom
had been expelled from their mother
country
we'll travel through time to to explore
how English in the 21st century has
become the International language of
business the language in which the
world's citizens communicate
over the last 15 hundred years these
small islands have achieved much that is
remarkable but in my view England's
greatest success story of all is the
English language these programs are
about the words we think in talking
right in singing the words that describe
the life we live this is where we can
begin just after dawn in a foreign
country on a flat shore by the North Sea
in what we now call the Netherlands
this is Friesland and it's in this part
of the world that we can still hear the
modern language that we believe sounds
closest to what the ancestor of English
sounded like fifteen hundred years ago
and this is the mouth of heaven to show
her mouth have a thoughtful an
orthodontic frost-free idiot of some
yoga doc that for all on the groom in
Friesland many people start their day
listening to the weather forecast from
popular weatherman Pete policeman and
among the easy Eliza
Vera dial some of his words might sound
familiar like three and four frost and
freeze and template tuition when the
beta tray of the fuel grab the enforced
at sea on that free is a mist and blue
fearless the chorus of mist and Dunmore
and I might think what's in it blow in
the loft the reason we can recognize
these words is that modern Frisian and
modern English can both be traced back
to the same family the Germanic family
of languages and some words have stayed
more or less the same down the centuries
butter bread cheese meal sleep boat snow
sea storm
the West Germanic tribes who invented
these words were a warlike adventurous
people they'd been on the move through
Europe for the best part of a thousand
years and now had settlements in what we
would call the lowlands of northern
Europe Holland Germany and Denmark but
there were still greedy for land ready
to move on this is the island of
terschelling the English coast is about
250 miles to the southwest behind me it
was from these islands and the low-lying
frisian mainland that in the 5th century
a Germanic tribe part of the family that
also contained Jutes Angles and Saxons
made sail to look for a better life and
they took their language our language
with them
whose mid-flow debar on Fran Radha Hayek
Stefan naka snella Cassini arc snood
ever windin who thought with this early
oder lund gas öktem water bill reckon
our soirees wind for draft the Germanic
tribes weren't the first to invade our
shores more than 500 years before the
Romans had also come by sea to impose
their will now their empire had crumbled
and they'd abandoned these islands
leaving the native tribes the Britons or
Celts to their fate this is Pevensey
castle an ancient Roman fort that used
to stand on the very shoreline of the
south coast the chronicle of the period
reported in the year 491 Germanic
invaders laid siege and slaughtered the
Celts had taken refuge here not one of
them was left alive other kelsa did
survive the invasion a million or more
of them in England but there were a
broken people the clue to their fate
lies in the word the Germanic tribe used
to describe them it was Willis a name
that lives on in our modern languages
Welsh 1,500 years ago
it meant both foreigner and slave the
Celts became servants and followers
second-class citizens the only way up
was to become part of the invaders
tribes to adopt their culture and their
language the Celts in their language
were pushed to the margins
only a handful of words from the Celtic
languages survived into modern English
in the North where I come from we have
crag meaning Rock Combe meaning deep
valley and dialect words like brat and
brach for badger
there are traces in place-names the tour
intro Penner spelled as top and how a
neighboring village to my own that comes
from the Celtic folk peak the car of
Carlisle means a fortified place in the
south they left us the names of Tamils
and Aven Dover and London but these were
fragments the language that prevailed
was that of the victors by the end of
the sixth century these Germanic tribes
occupied half of mainland Britain they
had divided into a number of kingdoms
Kent Sussex Essex and Wessex denoting
the settlements of southern eastern and
western Saxon tribes east anglia named
after the angles who gave England its
name Mercer in the Midlands Northumbria
in the north throughout these areas many
modern place names come from that
settlement or use the words they brought
we live with them we live in them every
day
the Inge in modern place-names means the
people of
torn as in Whitley where I come from
means enclosure or village Han means
farm which might surprise one or two
Tottenham supporters
the Germanic tribes now settled around
the country all spoke their own dialects
from among them when you merge one
language anglo-saxon or Old English and
we all speak it every day fire strike is
none of them can really finish Armstrong
even so hard
I just need some youth from their
teammates really examine a language you
use today and you'll still find hundreds
of words from a language over fifteen
hundred years old
keywords ready from the names we give
family members to numbers think will win
- once there I'll drink to that
I live in a West Ham sort of area and I
love got lower stem friends but for this
game we'll be enemies for the home games
I would go with the guys we meet up in
the top Birds web site or with my
daughter to other games and she's five
at the moment loves it loves singing the
songs nice ones anyway I was coming with
my son so we're just going to get
something to eat first going to the
ground
saving the atmosphere much to go there
has been a few high scoring games over
the years then the highest B of a beat
than the sixth one repeat today one guy
miss most of those words were from Old
English nouns like youth son daughter
field friend home and ground
prepositions like in and on into by and
from and and the are from Old English
all the numbers and verbs like drink
come and go sing like and love but would
these words have sounded different all
those years ago in a slightly quieter
pub I asked language expert quesillo
they sound a little different I mean the
old English the Sun is soo new that's
not so very different game is Garmin
ground is groomed and and I noticed that
Steve says his his daughter loves
singing songs she said that an old
English it would be his doctor lover the
sanga's singing and you can see that
that sounds pretty much like modern
English so in fact you can have a good
conversation in Old English oh yes you
can indeed I mean each each word I'm
saying now is from Old English over any
estimate how many words there
swirling around compared with how many
words we have now we think it was in the
region of 25,000 words I've compared up
with an average destiny which maybe
contains only like hundred thousand
words it sounds pretty small but if you
think about the fact that an average ly
educated person will probably have about
10,000 words and an active recovery
there are plenty of words to go round
English took its first steps away from
its tribal roots with the revival of
Christianity new Michelin hariom he
often reaches we art met Oda's mikta and
his mood gathon we let us praise the
king of heavens when He willed the power
of the creator and his conception the
work of the glorious father who created
every wonder the eternal Lord he often
told flew harlech she tended
in 597 the monk and Pryor Augustine led
a mission from Rome to Kent around the
same time Irish monks of the Celtic
Church were establishing a presence in
the north within a century Christians
built churches and monasteries
this isn't Paul's injera parts of which
date from the 7th century faith and
stone weren't the only things the
Christian missionaries brought to the
country they brought the international
language of the Christian religion Latin
Latin terms became part of the English
word horde Altera became altar a
possible us became apostle mass monk and
verse and many others all come from the
Latin this would become a pattern of
English the layering of words taken from
different source languages and from
Latin to the English took their script
the Angles Saxons frisians and Jutes who
had become the English hadn't brought
script as we know it with them but runes
the runic alphabet was made up of
symbols formed mainly of straight lines
so the letters could be carved into
stone or wood those were their media
rather than parchment or paper though
this is a short poem most examples of
runic writing that survived suggest
runes were mainly used for short
practical messages or graffiti the Latin
alphabet was different with its curves
and bows it allowed words to be easily
written using pen and ink on two pages
of parchment or vellum which gathered
together into a book could be widely
circulated
Christianity brought the book to these
shores verbum the word soon a native
culture of scholarship began to flower a
culture based on Latin and in writing
the Magnificent Lindisfarne Gospels were
created in the 8th century on the island
of Lindisfarne just off the northeast
coast a few miles south at the monastery
of st. Paul's in djaro the great English
monk and scholar bead born and educated
in Northumbria began writing the first
ever history of the english-speaking
people he wrote of course in Latin the
language of scholarship the prevailing
language among the people was still old
English but Latin this powerful medium
was now amongst them now old English was
written down using the Latin alphabet
while retaining some of the old runes as
letters from the 7th century we find
English itself written on parchment in a
language and a script which was just
about recognized as our own
father who serve larf in here flu see
gajala guard Norma Dean - cometh richer
Dean see Willow Dean's Watson he orphne
and in ortho Clough Mussina of village
sellers today and forgive us shoulder
ozra swami forgive on Shuga Museum and
inlaid with whiting Old English still a
march on other languages spoken in
Europe at the time prayers were recorded
and books of the Bible translated the
laws of the land were written down and
the language soon became capable of
recording and expressing an increasingly
wide and subtle range of human
experience and in the right hands Old
English was now powerful and supple
enough to take you to imaginary worlds
fire the blood be poetry what we got a
dinner in Yarra the woman field cooling
a throne loon on so the spear days and
days gone by the Kings will rule them at
courage and greatness we have heard of
those princes heroic campaigns
no one knows who composed the epic
Beowulf sometime between the mid 7th and
end of the 10th century it's the first
great poem in the English language the
beginning of a glorious tradition which
will lead to Chaucer Shakespeare and
Beyond the poem celebrates the glory
days of the Germanic tribes epitomize in
the heroic warrior who gives the poem
its name the power of the language can
be heard in this passage which
introduces bales archenemy the monster
Grendel with a calm of Mordor under miss
Lee odham Grendel dongha quarters in off
the moors down through the mist bands
God cursed Grendel came greedily looking
montes amongst kafir one of the bane of
the race of men's roam fourths hunting
for a prey in the high
corner to record our ring spurned and
joyless he journeyed on ahead and
arrived at the ball on brand the bee
Allah who dig the Higa bargain was in
his rage boiled over he ripped open the
mouth of the building maddening for
blood he grabbed and mauled a man on his
bench bit into his bone wrappings bolted
on his blood and gorged on him in loss
leaving the body
utterly lifeless eaten up hand and foot
what does that tell us about English at
that time Seamus what sort of language
was it when you came to do you think
this is a fully developed poetic
language it's certainly fully developed
poetic language it's it's furrier is
capable of great elaboration but what
struck me generally about Old English
from the moment I read the bits of the
anglo-saxon Chronicle right through to
Beowulf is it's terrific for telling
what happened it's a wonderful sense of
the indicative Moodle through it it's
terrific for action terrific for
description
there's a wonderful forthright capacity
to make up extra language in anglo-saxon
the words are very clear and direct bone
and house for example bone house there
you have the house for the body a word
for the body beautiful words for
instruments the harp is called glial BAM
the Glee beam the happy the happy wood
or else the joy would in some cumin wudu
swords or shield the shield is the war
board weak board that is a specific
poetic energy that's in the language the
the ability to make compounds which is
still in German I guess that gives us a
great beauty high excessive is the
vocabulary I think there 40,000 words
recorded in in Beowulf but a lot of the
words repeat themselves in probably this
is in poetry more than in the prose if
we heard an anglo-saxon speaker speaking
under his roof to his companion
we'd probably hear very a quicker a
different less elaborate language from
Beowulf would you say was it is very
clearly written to be read aloud it's
certainly written to be read aloud the
question that that agitates some
scholars as whether it was written you
know but I think the general consensus
now is that by the time you get to bail
of you have a writer dealing with a
traditional oral language what we
Gardiner NER dawam
failed Kooning of from noon on
who'sa are filling us Ellen from a dog
certainly you open the book what way
gardenia and year document asks to be
uttered and there are many speeches in
it and it comes off the tongue with with
terrific directness
Latin and Greek had created great bodies
of literature in the classical past in
East Arabic and Chinese were being used
in the eighth and ninth centuries
languages of poetry but at that time no
other language in the Christian world
could match the achievement of the bear
Wolford and his anonymous contemporaries
Old English was flourishing the
adventure was underway but while the
seeds of English had come from these
frisian shores in the fifth century so
now in the late eighth century a
potential destroyer was repairing his
battle fleet 500 miles or so to the
north
in the late 8th century the latin-based
culture of scholarship which had grown
up in places like Lindisfarne and which
had also been the cradle of old english
faced extinction from across the sea
these ruins are of the medieval
monastery that stood on the island of
Lindisfarne it was the Vikings who
sacked and burnt a religious center that
stood here before to these pagan pirates
rampaging out of their longships in 793
this great center of Christian piety and
scholarship a pivotal place in the
survival of the word and the Gospels was
no more than an undefended treasure
house the jewels that grace the books of
the church became baubles around a
vikings neck
today the Vikings may seem romantic
re-enacting their rituals a good day out
over 12 centuries ago their arrival was
not so cheerful to many it seemed to
signal the end for civilization
a year after raising Lindisfarne the
Vikings returned and sacked Jarrow the
abbey where beed had been the greatest
scholar in one of the finest libraries
and Christendom this stronghold of the
Latin word where English was also being
written down uniquely among European
dialects was burned to the ground it's
books with it
it was the start of 70 years of attack
during which the Vikings savaged this
eastern half of the country few stories
survived of exactly where and when they
attacked perhaps chillingly because few
were left to tell the tale
but first the Raiders went home with
their plunder then they decided to take
the land itself in 865 the Vikings
landed a great army south of here in
East Anglia
within five years the Viking invaders
who are now called Danes controlled the
north and east of the country of the old
anglo-saxon kingdoms only Wessex still
held out Old Norse the language of the
conquerors was spreading throughout the
land Old English potentially faced the
same fate as the Celtic language it had
supplanted virtual oblivion English was
in need of a champion and it found one
King Alfred statue stands here in
Winchester the capital of his ancient
kingdom of Wessex he's the only monarch
in our history to be known as the Great
and he's often been hailed as the savior
of England that may be debatable as the
idea of a single unified England didn't
really exist in Alfred's day what is
certain is that he was a great defender
of the English language
it was the Victorians who dubbed Alfred
the Great he was one of their darlings
an English hero whose exploits were
enthusiastically woven into the fabric
of national myth but he very nearly
didn't make it he come to the throne of
Wessex within a year of the first Danish
attacks in the southeast and at first he
could hardly hold them back in 878 the
Danes were on what appeared to be a
decisive battle at Chippenham in
Wiltshire
alfred with only a few followers went on
the run into the marshes of somerset
moving as a contemporary road under
difficulties through woods and into
inaccessible places legend has Alfred
unrecognised taking shelter in a poor
woman's cottage and being scolded for
burning the wheat and cakes he'd been
set to mind but the reality was less
cozy his situation was desperate and if
Alfred's Kingdom fell the whole country
would be controlled and settled by
conquerors whose language would
inevitably crush English but Alfred
proved to be an enterprising warrior and
strategist running free in the Somerset
Levels he discovered the arts of
irregular warfare and mounted guerrilla
attacks against the occupying forces of
go thrown the Danish invader
but he knew that wasn't going to be
enough for Wessex to be regained the
Danes had to be brought to battle and
defeated the fighting men of Wessex had
been scattered but in the spring of 878
night Alfred sent out a call for the men
of the Shire foods the county armies to
join him around 4000 men mainly from
Wiltshire and Somerset armed only with
battle axes and throwing spears
responded to the call they mustered at
Egberts stone were trackways and
ridgeway's met 48 hours later they
advanced shields drumming against the
danish army of 5000 holding high ground
at athens ooon on the western edge of
soars reply contemporary English
accounts described the battle that
followed as a slaughter and a rout of
the Danes by the West Saxons modern
historians question that but there's no
doubt that Alfred prevailed his crown
and his kingdom were secured and more
importantly for our story so is the
English language
the Dane surrendered the leader was
baptized as a Christian and Alfred's
crucial victory was memorialized here in
Russia in an earlier version of a great
white horse carved into the land deep
saved
alfred left an even more significant
mark on the country
he signed a peace treaty with the danes
which established a border running up
through the country from the thames to
the old Roman road of Watling street the
land to the north and east to be known
as the Danelaw would be under Danish
rule the land to the south and west
would be for the English no one was to
cross the line unless to trade in the
course of time because of Alfred's peace
treaty when Danes in English met they
didn't do so to fight but to do business
even to intermarry communities mixed and
so did the languages in English rather
than being engulfed by the Danes
language began to absorb it I'm in the
market town of Hexham in the northeast
of England maps of the area showed just
how widespread the Danish settlement was
place names ending in by reveal the
Danish name for farm for denotes a
village sweet
a portion of land the births marriages
and deaths pages of the local paper
feature lots of names ending in son that
was a Danish way of making a name by
adding to the name of the father just on
this page I can see Harrison Gibson
Hudson Robson Sanderson Dickenson
Simpson Dickinson again and Watson and
school where I was just across the
country there was a Pattinson a Johnson
a role in some not another Dixon outside
in the street you can see the same thing
on shop signs everywhere
even give the centuries of people moving
around the country names ending in Sun
are still far more common in what were
the Danish territories of the north and
west than they are in the south and east
but all you can hear the echoes of the
Danes Old Norse language in the way
people speak surely Allah and of the the
Sailor man lemme Carolyn it's a little
field on its own really sensors are back
down by the side of it looks down to a
little water in the structure looking a
second down by the you know don't bite
you're not going if you it's like a
little isolation feely Johnny it's only
a couple of acres the whole thing
interests me see if you sheep showed
would love it for debate today there
some Old Norse word stayed in the local
dialect of the north
words like Beck for stream and Garth for
paddock as a boy Rick and I remember
hearing and using dialect words like
Slattery for shower slate for slippery
yet for gait lab Philippe yech for oaken
yam for home as in arzga and young pure
nose heard in Wigton every night of the
week and there are many others but the
influence of Old Norse wasn't just local
or on the country over time hundreds of
Norse words entered the mainstream of
English and we still use them every day
the SK sound is a characteristic of Old
Norse and English borrowed words like
score and sky and skive as well as
perhaps a thousand others including
anger bull freckle knife neck root skull
and window
sometimes we're both Old Norse and Old
English had a word for the same thing
both words lived on in English each
taking on a slightly different meaning
where Old English said craft Old Norse
said skill for an English hide the North
said skin in Oldham she was sick
in Norse you're ill here was another
example of English as extraordinary
ability to absorb to take in words from
other languages adding them to its word
hoard increasing the richness and
flexibility of the vocabulary I think
that the point about my cover is how
much it astonishes by its ordinary
nature words like law egg husband leg
LLL die ugly all these words are from
Old Norse and yet you wouldn't
necessarily think they were foreign at
all most astounding of all I think other
pronouns they their and them those are
also from Old Norse an in terms of
grammar in a way they simplified English
didn't they took it away from its
Germanic roots these probably true to
say that Old Norse affects the English
language more than any other visit
actually leads to a restructuring of the
language Old English form sentences and
not by word order as we do but by
tacking on endings on to the ends of
things like articles and pronouns and
nouns and what happens is through
contact with a pretty similar language a
lot of these inflectional endings start
to lose their distinctive nature and
actually this is a process that we can
see happening fairly early on in the
anglo-saxon period so the language is
prone to do that but contact with north
language just speed eases up gave it a
shove towards modernity can you give us
a very simple example of that yes let's
take a simple sentence like and the King
gave horses to his men that would be
something like in Old English say
chimney gave blank an his guru now in
Old English you didn't tend to have a
preposition like to instead you could
use a special ending which kind of meant
to his men
and that would be um a um ending and you
just tack that onto the end of the noun
for man so you'd have Ghulam
um ending now the plural for the word
for horse you will say gave horses to
his men would be have an N on it so
every blonde can unfortunately towards
the end of the old english period we
start to see that um ending becoming
more and more indistinct and we see
spellings like GU man a n just the same
as blank and a n it's obvious that the
king is more likely to give horses to
his men men men to his horses but you
can see that there's a potential there
for difficulties and so we start to see
and prepositions being used in place of
those endings which has become
indistinct spoken English survived the
Danish invasion but as the ninth century
drew to a close the written culture was
in a ruinous State and King Alfred was
concerned when Alfred looked at the
state of his kingdom he was appalled the
scholars in the monasteries had once
made England the greatest powerhouse of
Christian teaching in Europe but a
hundred and fifty years had passed since
the High days of bead and the scholarly
tradition had declined hastened on its
way by a century of Viking reigns in all
the country Alfred could barely find a
handful of priests who could read and
understand Latin and if they couldn't
understand Latin they couldn't pass on
the teachings of the religious books
that told people how to lead virtuous
lives they couldn't save souls where the
written word had once flourished alfred
now found only chronic spiritual
sickness he looked for a cure one way
was to educate more clergy in latin but
that wasn't enough he hit on a more
radical solution a solution that hinged
not on Latin but on English and he took
English to new heights of achievement
in the preface to his own translation of
Pope Gregory's pastoral care alfred
wrote I remembered how before it was all
ravaged and burned I'd seen how the
churches throughout all England stood
filled with treasures and books and
there was also a multitude of God's
servants who had very little benefit
from those books because they couldn't
understand anything of them since they
were not written in that own language
their own language was of course English
Alfred didn't want to do away with Latin
but he realized that it would be far
easier to teach people to read books
written in the language they spoke the
best scholars could then go on to learn
Latin and join Holy Orders the rest
would still have access to scholarship
and spiritual guidance but it would be
written in English here in his capital
city of Winchester Alfred drew up a plan
it was an extraordinarily imaginative
project to promote literacy and restore
the English language
we should he wrote translate certain
books which are most necessary for all
men to know into the language that we
can all understand and also arrange it
as with God's help we very easily can if
we have peace so that all the youth of
freemen now among the English people
will have the means to be able to devote
themselves to it may be set to study for
as long as they're of no other use until
the time that able to read English
writing well Alfred had five books of
religious instruction philosophy and
history translated from Latin into
English a laborious and costly
undertaking
copies were sent out to the 12 bishops
of his kingdom for their wisdom to be
spread as widely as possible to each
bishop to emphasize the importance and
value of the project
Alfred sent a costly pointer used to
underline the text this is the Alfred
jewel
many historians believe that it formed
the head of one of those pointers
crafted in Crystal and enamel gold it
was discovered in 1693 in Somerset and
is now on show at the Ashmolean Museum
in Oxford it's inscribed Alfred had me
made in English Alfred the Great had
made the English language to jewel in
his crown
here in Winchester Alford had
established what was effectively a
publishing house other projects he
undertook included the commissioning of
the Anglo-Saxon Chronicle detailing
hundreds of years of history.
Alfred died in 899, one of his legacies was an
English language which is more
prestigious and widely read than ever before.
There was nothing to compare with
this range of written vernacular history,
philosophy, poetry, anywhere else in mainland Europe.
English was out on its own.
By the middle of the 11th century
English seemed secure, but now other
invaders were waiting in the wings and
English was about to face its greatest threat ever.
This place, the old Roman forte Pevensey,
was a fateful one for the English language.
It was here among other places
that the Frisians and other Germanic tribes
had made landfall in the 5th century
and introduced their own language.
Now in 1066 another wave of invaders was landing : the Normans.
When in 1066 William, Duke of Normandy, sailed
with his army to claim the English throne,
he was sure he had right on his side.
The English King Edward the Confessor
had spent many years in Normandy
and in that time contemporaryhe sources
say had come to regard William as a brother or even a son.
And he named him as his successor.
Sensing his impending death and fearing rebellion at home,
the childless Edward had dispatched
Harold Godwinson, his wife's brother and his Earl of Essex,
the richest and most powerful of the English Lords,
to Normandy to pledge loyalty to William.
This Harold did, swearing on two caskets of holy relics.
But when Edward did die, Harold,
supported by the English nobility had
himself crowned in Westminster Abbey
on the very day that Edward was laid to rest there.
To the truculent and ruthless William
this was an affront.
Invasion with maximum force (was) the only possible response.
The armies met here near Hastings.
This is the spot where traditionally Harold fell,
fatally pierced through the eye with an arrow.
The site was later named after the engagement,
but it's named not with an English word like "fight"
but with a word from the language of the Norman Victor's, “Battle”.
Harold would be the last English-speaking King of England for three centuries.
On Christmas Day 1066 William was crowned in Westminster Abbey
in a service conducted in English and Latin，
William spoke French throughout.
A new king and a new language were in authority in England.
"enemy" "castle"
"castle" was one of the first French words
to enter the English language.
the Normans built a chain of them to
impose their rule on the country.
This magnificent castle at Rochester was one
of the first to be fortified in stone.
By blood the Normans were from the same
stock as the Norseman who'd invaded in
earlier centuries but they no longer
spoke a Germanic language. Rather would
we call old French which had grown from
Latin roots. Many of the words they spoke
would have been very strange to the
native English but would quickly become
unpleasantly familiar. Arm words "army"
"archer" "soldier" "garrison" and "guard" all
come from the conquering Norman French.
French was the language that spelled out
the architecture of the new social order.
"crown" "throne" and "court", "duke" "baron" and
"nobility" "peasant" "vassal" "servant", the word
"govern" comes from French as do "liberty"
"authority" "obedience" and "traitor".
The Normans took the law into their own
hands: "felony" "arrest" "warrant" "justice"
"judge" and "jury" all come from French and
so do "accuse" "acquit" "sentence" "condemned"
"prison" and "jail". It's been estimated that
in the three centuries after the
conquest about ten thousand French words
colonized the English language.
They didn't all come in immediately but the
conquest opened a conduit of French
vocabulary that remain open on and off
ever since. Today French words are all
around us: "city" "market"
"porter". Here we are, look ??? ???
"salmon" weighs about 14 pound, it is a
fabulous fish. We've got some fabulous
"mackerel", they've come out from Aberdeen,
next door the "oysters" they come from the
Essex coast "sole". "pork" "sausage" "bacon"
"fruit" "oranges" "limon" "grape" "tart"
"biscuit" "sugar" "cream" "fry" "vinegar".
Nearly 500 words dealing with food cooking and
eating alone entered English from French,
just a fraction of the imports which
would enrich the English word hoard in
the centuries after the Norman Conquest.
Within 20 years of taking control of the
country, William sent his officers out to
take stock of his kingdom. The monks of
Peterborough who were still recording
the events of history in English in the
Anglo-Saxon Chronicle noted
disapprovingly: "they're not one piece of
land escaped the survey, not even an ox
or a cow or a pig".
The Doomsday Book, there are in fact two
volumes, show us how complete the Norman
takeover of English land was and how
widespread their influence and their
language. The Norman settlement had
concentrated the wealth of England more
than ever before or since. The native
ruling class from before the conquest
had been slaughtered, banished or
disinherited in favor of William's
followers. Half of the country was in the
hands of just a 190 men,
half of that was helped......  The English
language had been forced underground. It
would take 300 years for it to re-emerge
and when it did, it would have changed
dramatically.