so far in the adventure of English we've
traced the story of the language through
its first thousand years from the 5th
century to its great flowering at the
time of Shakespeare what began as a
minor Germanic dialect had come to these
shores with the Saxons endured invasion
by Vikings and 300 years of suppression
by Norman French during which time
English virtually went underground he
did even topple the Latin as the
language of worship and philosophy and
by the Elizabethan age English
completely dominated this sceptred aisle
but now the English language is about to
leave Britain in the next four programs
will tell the story of the way you
English became Britain's greatest export
some would say gift to the modern world
and how it became a global language
we shall see how English travelled to
India where it encountered scores of
other more ancient languages including
Sanskrit which did much the mother our
own tongue yet even at the end of our
imperial rule in the mid twentieth
century English remains in India as a
major unifying tongue we'll follow it to
the West Indies where new English
dialects have been spawned as rich and
vigorous as the native ones used by
Thomas Hardy and D H Lawrence and to
Australia where once exiled English now
reaches back to influence the use of the
mother country but first to the new
world where 17th century Puritan English
stubbornly beat up opposition from
native tongues and rival European powers
to become the language of what was to
grow into the greatest country on Earth
America
you
this was the Newfoundland to the first
settlers eyes this was a vast and it
seemed empty space and yet is because of
their first determined steps onto this
soil nearly four hundred years ago that
English would one day speak for America
this is Plymouth Rock it's literally the
foundation stone of modern America well
this is the very spot where the Pilgrim
Fathers landed in New England in
November 16 2010 on the Mayflower there
were religious separatists and they were
here to create a new community where
they could worship as they wished they
bound themselves to another the
Mayflower Compact swearing to found a
colony for the glory of God and the
advancement of the Christian faith they
were above all people who lived by the
Word of God in English they came from a
hard-line Puritan religious tradition
which had been persecuted and reviled
they'd been tortured and murdered for
their faith in an english-language Bible
and to them that Bible that language
meant life itself they weren't the first
people on the continent Native Americans
had been here for thirty thousand years
and the woods and the plains rang with
the sounds of hundreds of their
languages when the Pilgrim Fathers
looked around them instead of a New Eden
they saw what they described as a
hideous and desolate wilderness full of
threat and danger and for the season it
was winter and they that know the
winters of that country know them to be
sharp and violent and subject to cruel
and fierce storms dangerous to travel to
known places much more to search an
unknown coast besides what could they
see but a desolate wilderness full of
wild beasts and wild men and what
multitudes there might be of them they
knew not
they were cold hungry and pray to
sickness nearly half of the company of
144 died that first winter it wasn't
going to be easy to turn their oath into
reality and to give English its toehold
on the land the Pilgrim Fathers had one
advantage though they had come here to
stay and they wanted their settlement to
be English New England they were to call
it but true England might have been more
accurate their first move was to build a
settlement recreated here Plymouth
Plantation
they lived in terror of the supposedly
wild men in the wilderness outside but
before they could even do that they were
to owe their survival to one of those
wild men and an extraordinary encounter
with the English language and whilst we
were busy here about we were interrupted
for there presented himself as Savage
which caused an alarm
he very boldly came all alone up to the
houses where we intercepted it not
suffering him to go in as undoubtedly he
would out of his boldness he saluted us
in English and Bay us welcome
so welcome was the first word spoken by
native that the Pilgrim Fathers
understood the man who'd come out of the
wilderness had picked up some words from
the English fishermen who worked the
coast even more extraordinary he was
able to introduce them to this quantum
or Squanto as he became known he is the
most important man in this chapter of
the adventure of English he'd been
kidnapped by English sailors 15 years
before take it to London where he was
trying to be a guide an interpreter and
learn English then he managed to escape
on a return visit to the colonists it
must have seemed like a miracle he was
the most unlikely of all coincidences
that they should have settled near the
tribal home of the man who was almost
certainly the only English speaker for
hundreds of miles around but for the
extraordinary good fortune the whole
history of America might have been very
different for Squanto saved the colony
and who knows gave America the English
language
Squanto taught the settlers how to farm
the unfamiliar land and he got them
through that terrible first New England
winter it's almost certain that without
him sickness and hunger would have wiped
out the settlers against all odds the
English colony had been saved by an
encounter with the English language the
adventurer had planted its roots in
American soil
the settlers had a new country full of
new places and geographical features new
animals and plants they needed words to
describe them and occasionally they
turned to the native languages skunk was
derived from the local language and
squash for the variety of pumpkin grown
here meaning young woman was a
local word as was Papoose a young child
and wigwam was another early borrowing
from the local languages but what's
really remarkable is not that these
words did enter the English vocabulary
but how few of them there were four
centuries English had been borrowing
words in their thousands from Latin
Danish French and every other language
it had come into contact with but here
faced with the richness of an entire
continent the English borrowed words not
in thousands but in handfuls the
writings of the founding fathers here
run to thousands of pages but contain
less than a dozen borrowed Indian words
so why are there so few in a strange new
country the English settlers may have
taken great comfort in making the
objects around them at least sound
familiar look at the names they gave the
local terrain Falmouth Yarmouth
Boston Cambridge Bella Ricki Bedford
Taunton they were trying to recreate the
English shires
in the American wilderness and perhaps
there was desperation here as well as
determination the true language their
own they would survive as they had in
the old country so they put a wall
between themselves and the native world
in the end we must conclude that they
were here to impose their habits and
their language on the land not to be
changed by it
words God's good English words were at
the heart of the lives of the settlers
here improper speech was a crime
blasphemy slander cursing lying perjury
railing revealing scolding swearing
threatening treason and defying
Authority were all offenses the
colonists were trying to control the
language and this set the pattern for
their teaching of English and as New
England grew this was how they did it
with a New England primer
the Bible I see from the very beginning
Americans took immense care over the
correct teaching of English
it was taught well and in a way that was
highly religious and this set the tone
as English spread
it wasn't all going English's way though
other European powers are adjusting for
influence in the new world Delaware
where a Swedish settlement had taken
root was conquered in 1655 by the Dutch
Admiral Peter Stuyvesant and
incorporated into the Dutch New
Netherlands his base New Amsterdam
Washington conquered by the British in
1664 and renamed New York there was
rivalry with the French which turned
into war when it finally ended in 1763
Britain was given sell claim to the east
of the continent and took a grip on the
north in Canada even the Spanish colony
of Florida came under British rule but
perhaps the real edge that gave English
a stronger presence than the other
European languages came not through the
gun but through the plow sure the
Spanish on the whole concentrated on
sending armies and priests to the New
World and taking gold the French were
interested in sending fur trappers and
trading with the natives it was only the
English who continued the spirit of the
Pilgrim Fathers and came to stay
persistence and sheer weight of numbers
eventually ensured that English not
Spanish Dutch or French would be the
language heard from the Atlantic coast
to the Appalachian Mountains
but his English spread it also started
to develop a character return to drift
away from the language spoken in England
there was already the beginnings of the
tomato tomato problem in some cases
meaning shifted English shop had become
an American store lumber meant rubbish
in the old country for Americans lumber
was and still is cut timber and Hall
came to me to transport in a vehicle not
as in England to move by force American
English was also developing its own
sound the first settlers had come from
various parts of England each with its
own regional accent but no single accent
dominated as they talked to each other
the variety very quickly became a blend
to this day there's only a tiny
variation accents across America
compared to Britain and the further west
you go the more true that becomes by the
middle of the 18th century in the
absence of
your pronunciations and dialect words
has been noted approvingly by upper
class British visitors who regarded all
such variations as vulgar in 1764 Lord
Gordon wrote the propriety of language
here surprised me much the English
tongue being spoken by all ranks in a
degree of purity and perfection
surpassing any but the polite part of
London it's a sentiment that would be
repeated again and again that the
Americans didn't just be good English
they spoke it better than the English
themselves it wasn't only where language
was concerned that the colonists began
to stand up to the English tension was
growing between them and the crown in
1775 here on this bridge at Concord in
Massachusetts 75 American volunteers
confronted 700 for his troops one of
them fired Weathers ever since been
called with a touch of hyperbole the
shot heard round the world revolution
had begun a year later 13 colonies
declared their independence and did so
imperfect what we might call classical
English we hold these truths to be
self-evident that all men are created
equal that they are endowed by their
creator with certain unalienable rights
that among these are life liberty
pursuit of happiness John Adams who had
become the second President of the
United States rate of a future in which
all Americans spoke the language equally
well in which eloquence would be the way
to high office and no one will be
excluded because their speech betrayed
inferior origins it was a birth of a
democratic ideal that still part of the
American myth that anyone can become
present everyone would have a
presidential recovery and accent this
was no longer the King's English
but perhaps the people's English and
they wanted to set it in stone this is
another foundation of America not a rock
but a little blue book it was written by
a schoolteacher called Noah Webster
through the last years of the 18th
century in the 19th century it was sold
in countless general stores like this
one stacked among the tins of molasses
and sacks of beans the snake' oils
paraffin lamps and shovels it soon
became known
the American spelling book or the
blue-backed speller it sold at fourteen
cents a copy and in its first hundred
years it sold 60 million copies more
than any other book in American history
with the exception of the Bible this is
one of the most influential books in the
history of English the first word is
academic the first sound is a C perfect
the next part is aa aa d e M then I see
altogether Democratic d e M the hundreds
of words and model sentences in
Webster's book have been repeated by
millions of children on countless
occasions all together very nice and the
practices thought have changed the sound
of the language to this day Americans
tend to pronounce words with a farm or
even emphasis than the English and in
particular than the clipped vowels of
the English aristocracy whose influence
Webster wanted to oppose where the
English say Cemetery the Americans have
cemetery English laboratory American
laboratory but pronunciation wasn't all
that he influenced it was from this book
that American learn how to spell correct
spelling came to be seen as a standard
of education and civilization throughout
America and it still is today and the
spelling bee became part of the life of
every town and village this morning
we're gonna start a spelling lesson with
practice for the spelling bee that we're
going to be doing the first word is
syllable sometimes when you study words
you might break them into a syllable
pattern Webster's book standardized
spelling across America and he also
tried to improve on inconsistent and
illogical Spelling's the next word is
democracy yeah
tem o c ry under Webster's system honor
color and a score of similar words lost
day you double letters were reduced to
single ones like the airline traveler or
the G in Wagga er replaced our e as the
ending of theater or Center defense with
the sea became defense with an S acts
lost its e acts England had made the
language but America had begun to claim
its future by the 1820s East Coast
America was presenting itself
confidently as the guardian of English
meeting up vulgarity and fashion there
is even a cheeky motion proposed in the
House of Representatives to invite the
sons of the English aristocracy to come
to America to learn how to speak
properly Americans felt they kept the
English language pure for 200 years so
pure that they were still using words in
English had dropped words like a
greenhorn burly deft scant talented and
likely Americans still say sick to mean
ill not just nauseous they say for
meaning autumn just as the English did
once and when Americans say I guess
they're using a formal word that would
have been familiar to Chaucer yes and
they denied that they were changing the
language when Webster published his
groundbreaking American Dictionary in
1828 he claimed that is this contained
less than fifty terms that were new to
the country here was America claiming to
preserve English in all its past glories
to have erected a barrier against change
and corruption but they could no more
exclude these natural developments in
the language than the first colonists
could hide behind a stockade from the
world beyond John Adams had predicted
that America would drive the English
language into a great future his vision
was prophetic but the language would be
very different from the measured East
Coast tones that Adamson had known
American English was going west
and going wild
in 1804 the United States purchased what
was then called Louisiana from the
French for three cents an acre and more
than doubled the size of the country
overnight
you
and these lands were nothing less than
the whole american heartland the Great
Plains and prairies drained by the
Mississippi River and it's tributaries
like the Missouri Ohio and Tennessee it
stretched all the way from New Orleans
in the south to the Rocky Mountains and
what is today the Canadian border in the
north
Jefferson the president sent an
expedition of 45 men under the
leadership of captains Meriwether Lewis
and William Clark into the unknown
interior in search of a navigable river
route to the west coast
Lewis and Clark's expedition became one
of the epic journeys in the history of
exploration it started here in st. Louis
on the great junction where the
Mississippi and the Missouri rivers come
together Lewis and Clark were army
trained frontiersman backwoods
specialists and because Jefferson
insisted on daily journals being kept
the expedition was recorded not in a
Puritan language of faith nor in
Webster's urbane prose but in the
practical language of the frontier and
this is crucial because it marks the
beginning not only the opening of the
continent but of the decline of the East
Coast grip on American English we
finished butchering the Buffalo and on
my return to camp I plot within a few
inches of a rattlesnake but fortunately
escaped his bite we also pass another
Creek and a very bad rapid which reached
quite across the river
a female elk and its fawn swum down
through the waves which ran very high
hence the name of Elk Rapids which we
instantly gave this place opposite to
these Rapids there is a high bluff and a
little above on the lar bird a small
cottonwood bottom in which we found
sufficient timber for our farce and
encampment these are words peculiar to
America or in a peculiarly American use
in England the creek is a tidal Inlet in
America it's broadened its meaning to
cover all manner of streams adjectives
turning to nouns rapid into Rapids and
Bluff was coined here to describe flat
cliffs rattlesnake was another of those
descriptive combinations of English
words as was Cottonwood and elk is one
of the words imported from England and
applied to a different beast buffalo
though had been in English word for over
two centuries imported from a Portuguese
book about China Lewis and Clark's
journals include not Webster's 50 words
peculiar to America but over 2,000 of
them most are names of objects a great
catalog of flora and fauna and man-made
items that were new to English eyes
words like hickory hominy maize moccasin
moose opossum pecan persimmon toboggan I
derived from native languages as well as
more obscure words like Kinnikinnick and
me
chef Lisa smoking Hemi can a preserved
mixture of meat fat and berries and
Tamarack a kind of lunch
others are English Carnage's with
descriptive properties of their own the
whippoorwill a bird named by the sound
of its call or the Mockingbird a name
inspired by its habit of imitating other
bird songs and there are hundreds of
names made by combining existing English
words from black bear bluegrass
bottomland backtrack box older brown
thrush Buckeye bullfrog bald eagle and
Blue Jay to sapsucker Snowberry snow
whistling Swan Timberland tumble-bug
turkey Buzzard and Yellow Jacket but
this was just the beginning
in the wake of Lewis and Clark the Great
Rivers became America's super highways
once this key side in st. Louis the
Gateway to the West
hustled with scores of paddle steamers
taking new settlers to the new lands
this was the hub of the frontier in the
1830s and 40s the very word immigrant is
an American invention vast migrations of
people had never been a huge factor in
the old world but it was the defining
experience of the new one and new
settlers brought new linguistic energies
the Pilgrim Fathers had come primarily
from the south and east of England but
two centuries on Americans were as
likely to come from Scotland escaping
the aftermath of the Highland Clearances
or from Ulster often driven out by
famine high rents religious intolerance
or simply looking for the chance to make
a new and better life as many as half
the population of Ulster crossed the
Atlantic and many kept moving west they
became a major part of the rich mix of
people who were creating a new American
country and a new American voice
Scots and Irish brought new words and
expressions to America
the Scottish verbs Scoon meaning to skim
over water took to the sea as a new type
of ship the schooners the Irish donated
to add cabin to name the typical
frontier dwelling they also brought dead
as in dead straight and the similar use
of plumb and right came to America
through use by both Scots and Irish as
did the habit of sticking an a on the
front of verbs like a going the old
French process too is apparent
everywhere along the Mississippi it's
there in the place names from New
Orleans Baton Rouge and Lafayette in the
south descent Louie cage or ado and
Belleville further north and towns
ending in the French suffix viel but
everywhere Edwardsville Greenville
Jacksonville Clarksville the French gave
us the name of one of the great Western
institutions the hotel America took who
were the French had given to a grand
private house for a municipal building
and turned it into the name of a new
invention a palace for all the people
far grander in ambition and the Inns and
taverns had offered rest to travelers in
England and their clients were
businessmen in 18th century England
merchants had been described as
businessmen but now the word took on its
modern American meaning the mover and
shaker in the worlds of finance and
expansion and opportunity
the country was on the move and on the
make the river teem with poor migrants
rednecks have got their name from away
their necks were burnt by the Sun as
they bent to work in the fields because
they couldn't afford the steamboat fur
they traveled on rafts which they
steered with us called rifts so they
were known as the riffraff on board
boats like this one richer travelers
were in turn regarded as highfalutin
because of the high fluted smokestacks
that carried soot and cinders well away
from those passengers and also perhaps
because of this to five hats those dudes
war baby strode the Texas Nick the
biggest on the boat woman this is
five-card stud gambling was a favorite
activity among the riverboat passengers
passed the buck and the buck stops here
both come from such card games the buck
was a buck horn handled knife passed
round to show who was Delia and they're
just the start of the phrases that
American gamblers gave to the language
in the middle of the 19th century
assuming you happen esha deol became
part of phrases like square deal new
deer a fair deal raw deal dealer will
take three big deal no big deal and
raise it great I'll raise your bid you
bet put up or shut up and I'll call your
bluff
we're all first heard around the card
table I'll call you you have an ace up
your sleeve so you up the ante someone
throws in his hand but you keep a poker
face now the chips are down but the
cards are stacked against you someone
plays a wild card and scoops the jackpot
think
Cheers
gambling and drinking spread across the
West no surprise there this was a very
different frontier from the original one
at Plymouth and nothing added more slang
words and phrases to the language than
alcohol barroom and saloon both entered
the language soon followed by bartender
and set him up measures like a snifter a
and a finger all came from the
bars of America and bootlegging comes
from the practice of hiding a flat
bottle of whiskey in the leg of a boot
to be sold illegally to the natives and
there were literally hundreds of terms
for drunk even before the Revolution
Benjamin Franklin listed two hundred and
twenty nine of them minted in America
including he's casting up his accounts
his head is full of bees he sees the
Bears his cherry Mary his one bull
cropped he's halfway to Concord he's ate
a toad and a half a breakfast
he's grow table his globular he's loose
in the hills he's intoxicated his juicy
he Clips the King's English he sees two
moons his nip top circle his oil
he's like a rat in trouble his double
tongue he's trammeled he's got the
Indian vapors he's out of the way he's
very weary teetotal was another word
that came into the language from the
Irish settlers along with speakeasy
shillelagh and smithereens yes indeedy
and no siree and later of course came on
the wagon westward expansion had long
been the cause of land disputes between
the settlers and the natives
and once they left the Great Rivers for
the wagon routes like the Oregon and the
Santa Fe trails
contact and often friction between
migrants and Indians increased many of
the Indian words that had already come
into English reflected this antagonism
sculpt a good old English noun had
become a far more threatening verb as
early as 1693 tomahawk was another early
addition to the language so were warpath
wool war dance and long knives an Indian
word for white man and firewater the
term they gave to alcohol
phrases like no-can-do or long time no
see are literal translations from Indian
languages the word grave to describe
Indian warriors were certainly inherited
from the French and buk slang for a
dollar derives from buckskin the
standard unit of trade between Europeans
and Indians conflict with the natives
was just one of the hazards faced by the
people who went west every one of them
had an epic journey to tell of the
hardships imposed by distance and the
weather everyone had carved a new life
out of a landscape made on a scale
unknown in Europe they chose new
American heroes for themselves through
whose stories they could distill their
own experiences and they chose them and
told tales about them on a grand scale
the most famous of all straddled the gap
between fact and fiction Davy Crockett
he was as we know from the song born in
a mountain top in Tennessee he was the
son of a veteran of the revolution he
became a congressman famous for his
plane speaking and he died defending the
Alamo in Texas in 1836 he was as
American as they came and he became a
legend the king of the wild frontier the
hero of a series of paper-bound books
telling exaggerated stories about him
this fictionalized Crockett was the
first great exponent of a style of
speech as big as the country called tall
talk when he opened his mouth he made
the first shank
these is time to come upon us like a
whirlwind on earth patient they are come
like a cat amount at full jumps we are
called upon to show our grid like a
follow line again a pine log exterminate
mollify and calumny ate the pole pierced
the heart of the enemy cram is pesky
carcass full of thunder in lining like a
stuffed savage and turtle him off with
our red-hot poker and while the Stars
Uncle Sam the stripes of this country
way problem footing in the breeze war
where where is the Craven low-lived
chicken bread po top and red mounted
wrist leaded mother son are you you will
not raise the beacon light of triumph
now the Citadel the aggressor and
squeeze ahead to Liberty and Gloria
confidence bread ornate baroque words
shebang shindig and slumgullion calf lop
Caban and got thump an American need not
simply leave hurriedly he could obscure
qu8
or skedaddle he didn't just use
something up he exploited it the
language was hunky-dory rambunctious
splendiferous its figure whose in speech
and that habit of coming up with vivid
verbal images has left us with many that
figure in everyday talk it's not my
funeral if you fly off the handle
because you have a chip on your shoulder
an axe to grind I might sit on the fence
and dodges issue
I won't fizzle out I will crack up no
two ways about it I'll knuckle down and
make the fur fly
I'll go the whole hog and knock the
spots out of you and you'll be a goner
you'll kick the bucket so face the music
you're barking up the wrong tree
you won't get the drop on me I'm in
cahoots with some people with the
know-how keep a stiff upper lip and have
the horse sense to pull up stakes okay
within two generations of the opening of
Louisiana the American language had been
reborn no legislator sitting in a
library in all of the eastern states
could have hoped to arrest its exuberant
progress it's a fact that the biggest
author of the language is unknown this
was the Democratic language that Adams
had foreseen but democracy meant that
everyone threw in their two cents worth
and the old conservative values were
trampled in the movement West
I never quicker than when gold was
discovered in them thar hills
Gold Fever brought tens of thousands of
people from the eastern states and now
let us home were loaded with new words
prospector was one they wrote about how
they staked their claim about how they
hope that gold dust would pan out of the
water that they were sipping while they
would strike it lucky or strike it rich
and brews a bonanza which came from the
Spanish word for fair weather and for
the first time a surefire investment
became known colloquially as a gold mine
and the gold rush gave us two words that
became far more famous in the 20th
century when a certain levi-strauss
started to make hard wearing clothes for
miners use the cloth called jean
Faustian originally made in Genoa Levi's
and jeans have been as American as Stars
and Stripes ever since the arrival of
the railroad was what really opened up
the country and it created the industry
that gave the West its most
characteristic vocabulary it was a
certain Joseph McCoy who had the idea of
driving cattle often hundreds of miles
to railheads
so they could be exported to the markets
back east previously they'd only been
butchered for local use overnight
McCoy became immensely rich so rich the
story goes that other envious souls used
to try to pass themselves off as the man
who had such a simple but brilliant idea
and so he developed the habit of
introducing himself to strangers as the
real McCoy he gave the world a
catchphrase and he also gave it the
cowboy
English had known the word cowboy since
the 18th century but now it took on a
new currency in a new meaning
McCoy's brainwave turned the cattle
industry into a license to print money
and the cowboy into a national icon
Cowboys had been working near the
Mexican border for years picking up
Spanish words which now drove north with
ranch comes from the Spanish as does
Corral where horses or cattle were
penned Mustang Bronco and the more
humble burro
the chaps sombrero and Pancho they might
were the cinch that secured the saddle
valerian and the lassoo they used to
rope cattle the Sierras measures and
canyons they rode across the cries of
vamoose and pronto the Stampede that
they feared and the rodeo where they
drove the cattle together all came from
Spanish the language of the West has
become the standard idea of what
American English is like completely
overtaking the proper speech of the East
and the man who is virtually
single-handedly responsible for this was
one of the greatest showman and boosters
of them all
he was William F Cody Buffalo Bill and
he chose to be buried here on the hill
was above Denver where the Rockies rise
steeply out of the Great Plains
he turned the frontier experience into
an epic entertainment Buffalo Bill's
Wild West extravaganza featured live elk
and Buffalo real Indians attacking a
stagecoach
sharp shooting displays musical cowboys
in spotless outfits that have never seen
a cattle drive and the reenactment of
Custer's last stand at Little Bighorn
in which Buffalo Bill himself arrived on
the scene just too late to save the day
it was nonsense and it was a smash
across America and Europe for 30 years
long after Indian resistance had ended
and the last buffalo herd had been
massacred
he created a vote for the language of
the worst and began a line of Western
myth that kept that language alive
through countless books and films and
the dreams of luxury and optimism became
an enduring fantasy of a Western
Eldorado and Eden somewhere over the
rainbow or at least the next county line
it's all there in a little song about
the hobos another good frontier word who
rode the railways west in search of
their own American dream
in the big rock candy mountains you
never change your socks and the little
stream the mouthal how much we cling
down the rocks the brakeman have to tip
their hats and the railroad bulls are
blind there's a lake of stew and a
whiskey too you can paddle over on him
in a big canoe in the big rock candy
mountains but there was another group of
Americans who'd never been invited to
show that dream the black slave
population of the south and they spoke
about their experiences in a very
different language I'll see you all is
coming fall in the big rock candy
mountain
this is Sullivan's Island a little patch
of land in Charleston Harbor off the
coast of South Carolina it was the first
taste of America for hundreds of
thousands of immigrants in the 18th and
19th centuries but the immigrants who
came through here hadn't chosen the
American dream of a better life they had
been sold into slavery Sullivan's Island
was a holding pen for imported slaves
between half and two-thirds of them
entered America here before being sold
on mainly to work on the cotton
plantations
there's no Statue of Liberty here just
this plaque erected in 1999 to
commemorate their arrival they came here
from the countries of West Africa and
from plantations in the Caribbean slaves
who spoke different languages were put
together on the same sea voyage here to
stop them plotting together to seize
control of the ship
so one ship and on shore there was a
great fable of languages
the slaves had to find a tongue in which
to talk to one another and to their
masters it was English but English very
heavily influenced by African ways of
talking then y'all get home and put it
put aboard and get your stuff in the
sack and that they know the man the
knock on the door yeah yeah say you
wouldn't spell all these pieces are ya
let's come up the pizza yeah you take
the girl and you're fakin or anything
you have a spot of tea the language
these people are talking is Gullah which
is survived as a distinct variety of
English here around the South Carolina
islands so fella come yeah and walk up
on the bank if they were you doing up on
that Bank there either don't you know
that was taught by many people to be the
closest we can get to the kind of
language that would have been spoken by
the slaves in the 18th and early 19th
centuries and that this is the origin of
modern afro-american vernacular did
y'all get off about 50 feet off and
y'all look over there yeah
and he gone his buddy he looked good boy
done thank God he's down hard hey help
help
don't die rustling yeah we put
together varying African words along
with Elizabethan English and came out
with something that sound like a dish
yeah well neither yet agree to talk like
this so sometimes people think maybe
it's English then they go but not quite
there were Evo's Mandinka smile Incas
Yorubas Gulas kid see a freak Mende that
were all kidnapped captured and then
isolated together on these islands
during enslavement once the slaves
reached the plantations they lived in
cabins like these beside the main house
here are many words that came into
Gullah from African languages have found
their way into standard English words
such as banana which comes from a Wolof
language spoken in Senegal and voodoo
traceable to an African word spinach in
the language spoken by the Yoruba people
other African words regimented standard
English include the animals zebra
gorilla and chimpanzee the musical terms
Samba Mambo banjo and Pongo and the food
and plant names goober me peanut yam and
gumbo meaning okra African compound
words were translated giving English
terms like bad Mouse and nitty gritty
originated as a term for the grit that
accumulated in the bilges of slave ships
as well as McAlary Gullah employ some
grammatical features that differ from
standard English if someone say hundred
wine for do that I'd be done to him
oh yeah so they ask you are you going to
do it I already did it and I did it a
long time ago
essentially is what you're saying I had
done to him I done don't do this you see
so you hear somebody say I done don't do
that that mean they did it and they did
a long time ago and why are you asking
me or getting basically so it's a lot
more going into it so if someone says
100 want over the hunter done yet they
say you're going over there I had done
Yeti that but it don't do that too but I
didn't grind it but they ain't been did
it why don't I ever did it well either
did they want to imitate it you see so
it's like well you were going over there
yeah I already went there but when I
went you weren't there but I was there
but you're right I wasn't there when you
were there phrases like these have a
rich and economical expressiveness in
other ways Gullah and other black
English's have stripped down their
grammar they drop verbs like is use
don't wear Stalin English says doesn't
and omit the apostrophe and s that
standard English uses as a sign of
ownership this kind of simplification is
common when languages meet and emerges
of new hybrid it's exactly what happened
when saxs and day
dealt with each other in England in the
9th century and changing this grammar
forever but in this case the changes
were mistakenly taken by many white
observers as evidence that black
speakers just hadn't got the
intelligence to speak the language
properly but they were simply trying and
failing to copy white speech in fact
they were adding to the language now
listen yeah you know some people say a
dear friend of him but they're always
your friend like that boy Robert that
boy no hand nothing to him you yell I
said that cutter was slow motion and
that bird rabbit just a Snickers in
water beat I captain black speakers had
their own tradition of performances that
showed just how flexible and Express if
their language was they told stories and
they're still told today now hope at all
I tell you burn rubber hand tick off it
look at his split a severe Robert is a
direct descendant of animal tricksters
who teach in African folklore a view to
tell the truth but cutter he's a yes of
ma'am I say you're lighting your
lighting in your tool in you in or tool
in your new way but folktales weren't
the only thing that fueled dreams of
freedom with English the slaves had
learned Christianity white society
thought it would teach obedience the
Bible became is central to the lives of
the slaves as it had been to the first
settlers in New England but the message
they found in it wasn't a Beatles it was
liberty once again the Bible in English
became the book of freedom yeah Jesus
called me a Jesus call
oh
I better get ready Jesus be coming back
by the first decade of the nineteenth
century the American states in the north
and abolish slavery when the blacks of
the South sang steal away or one more
river to cross or bound for Canaan land
they were introducing new words and
sounds into the language and they're
also singing not just about the next
world but about this one about the hope
of escaping to the north and to freedom
the chains of slavery were rusting and
on the 12th of April 1861 in the early
hours of the morning shots were fired at
Fort Sumter in Charleston Harbor just
behind me this was the start of the
American Civil War which the north of
course was to win four years later
Confederate forces abandoned Schultz the
Union army marched in unopposed they
freed the slaves promised in the
language of their spirituals had come
good for the black people jostle
the American Civil War gave us the
phrase hold the fort and the first
people to hear anything on the grapevine
were in the southern states where army
telegraph lines strong in the trees
became so knotted that they were said to
look like Greg Fox you got the Lord's
forgiveness there was plenty of
resistance to the new order the Ku Klux
Klan who apparently derived their name
from the Greek word coup class meaning
circle were formed in the aftermath of
the war they gave English the word
bulldozer originally a bulldoze meaning
a dose large enough for a bull it was a
dose of whipping and it was administered
to black people often fatally words like
bulldozers are a savage reminder that
the end of the war didn't bring the end
of segregation and Prejudice in theory
blacks in their language were now free
to mix with whites but in practice it
was only the 20th century that the
mixing of the cabarets really began that
just like in the plantation houses white
speakers started to ape black speech and
cool was born and that's a story for
later program
even after the Civil War very few white
people treated black language with any
interest or respect Warren who did was a
man who'd grown up on the Mississippi
and was fascinated by all of its talk
black and white luckily for us he was a
genius when he made writing his
profession he chose as his pen name a
call that he'd heard the river Bergman
used to sound a depth of two thousands
Mark Twain and the river runs through
Twain's greatest book The Adventures of
Huckleberry Finn
it's set in the years before the Civil
War and to the story of a young boy who
escapes what he disdainfully calls the
civilizing influence of his Aunt Sally
Huck takes to the river on a raft in the
company of an escaped slave called Jim
in his introduction Twain told his
readers that he'd taken great pains to
capture the different dialects of the
river a southerner talks music he once
wrote and when he'd Huck Finn described
life on the river he found its melody
it's lovely to live on a raft
we had the sky up there all speckled
with stars and we used to lay on our
backs and look up at them and discuss
about whether they was made or only just
happened Jim allowed that they was made
but I allowed that to happen I judge it
would have took too long to make so many
Jim said the moon could have laid him
well that looked kind of reasonable so I
didn't say nothing against it because I
seen a frog lay most as many we used to
watch the stars that failed to see him
streak down Jim allowed that got spoiled
and was Hove out of a nest this is a new
voice in the American record that of the
common man under frontier English has
come a long way from the sober and
sacred language that the Puritans at
first brought to New England it has
changed its sound and it has changed its
character words were no longer solely
vehicles for God's truth there are also
words are defended the East Coast wasn't
yet ready to relinquish its
self-appointed role as guardian of the
language like here at Concord the cradle
of the revolution the civilized and
Salas who sat on the library committee
banned Huckle Griffin for its vernacular
language it was they said couch
rough ignorant dialect and that there
was a systematic use of bad grammar and
an employment of in elegant expressions
but though the library committee might
call Twain's language vulgar it couldn't
ban the vigor of English that had grown
up away from the East Coast American
English Huck's closing words defied
their attempts to control it there ain't
nothing more to write about and I am
rotten glad of it because if I'd have
known what a trouble it was to make a
book I wouldn't have tackled it and
ain't a-going to know more but I reckon
I got a lot out for the territory ahead
of the rest because Aunt Sally she's
gonna adopt me and sivilize me and I
can't stand it I've been there before
and the vigor continued to increase in
the late 19th century new waves of
immigrants flooded into America Germans
Italians Greeks Russians Jews for all
across Europe they came to a land that
promised to give a new home to the tired
poor huddled masses longing to breathe
free to become American was their dream
and for most all of them that meant that
they wanted their children to speak the
language of the new country they would
power the adventure of English into the
20th century
you