in the last program we looked at the way
in which English had begun to oust
French is the language of law and
government and how there was a new
confidence in English literature but
during the 14th and 15th centuries there
began a movement to return English to
each central place in society this fight
was often a violent one it was as much a
political story as a linguistic one and
it starts right at the top for late
medieval Britain was above all a
religious society the Catholic Church
controlled and pervaded all aspects of
life and it was in the church that this
struggle for access and power would be
fought English set out to become the
language of God
you
in the beginning was the word and the
Word was with God and the Word was God
God created the heavens and the earth
now that was formless and empty God said
let there be light and there was light
through him all things were made without
him nothing was made that has been made
in him was life and that life was the
light of men
number 12 in your handbook and then
stand up ready to really sing possibly
in the beginning was the word but not if
you lived in 14th century England and
couldn't speak a Latin power in words
lay in the Bible there was no Bible in
English in formal terms God spoke to the
people in Latin six centuries ago the
Bible stories were commonly enjoyed but
not the Bible itself to the vast
majority it was a closed book before Zia
and easier private but a prince with
Alton pair should descend tune in a
Lardon to mock man keen clearly to lates
them that alone and in bedlam heavy
shall that Psalm barn before these are
the Mystery Plays first performed in New
York around thirteen seventy six and
still being performed today they tell
the Christian story from the mystery of
God's creation to the birth death and
resurrection of Christ they are
religious plays but they're not the
Scriptures there are sort of biblical
surf opera at the same kind of removed
from an original source as a nativity
plays are today if you wanted to hear
the real thing you'd have to go in there
in the Minster and hear it in Latin I'd
hear you'll get the strip cartoon
version in English only one plane chair
is now performed in the original
language the language of the town of
Chaucer it made us some maravillosa man
if fully you'll be hit but it should
mean that what not yay for all you can
gap and Gong he can sing it as well as
day and on a say it shall soon be pro
bird are we pass if you a will help held
on for the seat was
da Sattler TTA in order this year it's
the Shepherd's play the story of the
three shepherds seeing the angelic host
coming and preparing for the newly born
Jesus money known Li but there's a I
shall see it has so crooked in me rose
flatly lippies an angel' rocked who's
hidden is new above in bedlam should be
born a boom then spark or prophecy true
and bard as mating there this long
that was the language of the streets
immediate and direct but in God's has
Latin ruled
anybody who has brought up in the ways
of the Church of England as iowa's would
find a medieval church service
linguistically a strange and remote
affair when you went to church there and
everybody had to was compulsory there
was no familiar English hymnal hymns
ation and modern or even the Book of
Common Prayer everything was in Latin
and at best you'd only have understood
the odd word of it only the clergy were
allowed to read the Word of God and they
did even that silently a bell was wrong
to let the congregation know when the
priests had reached the important bits
for the authority of the Catholic Church
it was vital that a priest and a
language stood between a believer and
the Bible but all that was about to
change dramatically in the 14th century
those the beginnings of a counter
movement that was going to turn
english-speaking world on its axis it
would eventually tear the church in two
it would mark the end of the Middle Ages
and would cost many many lives it was
the battle for the language of the Bible
the English some of them wanted access
to the kingdom of heaven in the language
of the streets they wanted a Bible had
belonged to them and they were prepared
to fight for it
it was the boldest way for English to
become the language of real power the
prime mover was John Wickliffe who at
the age of seventeen was admitted here
to Merton College Oxford
you
Wickliffe was a charismatic scholar
fluent in Latin and therefore familiar
with the Bible he was a major
philosopher and theologian who believed
passionately that his knowledge should
be shared by everyone and he was
fiercely opposed to the power and wealth
of the church when men speak of the
church she said they usually mean
priests monks cannons and Friars but it
should not be so whether a hundred
Pope's he wrote and all the Friars
turned to Cardinals their opinions in
matters of faith should not be accepted
except insofar as they're founded on the
scripture itself the church in Wickliffe
style was often lazy and corrupt Bible
reading even among the clergy were
surprisingly rare or often they didn't
have the Latin
when the Bishop of Gloucester surveyed
311 deacons arch deacons and priests of
the diocese he discovered that a hundred
and sixty eight were unable to repeat
the Ten Commandments 31 didn't know
where those commandments came from and
forty couldn't repeat the Lord's Prayer
Wickliffe railed at the corruption and
complacency of the church his overriding
thought was summed up in his passionate
belief in the right of every man whether
cleric or layman to examine the Bible
for himself this meant a full English
Bible but it wasn't an easy task
it was unauthorized by the church and so
potentially heretical even seditious it
had to be done in secrecy for its aim
was to overthrow the powerful with words
we know that by the beginning of 1380
Wickliffe had organized the translation
from the latin of the first english
bible
the work took place here in Oxford
probably with a number of translators
and it wasn't only the mammoth task of
translation that faced them their Bible
had to be disseminated to
once a translation was done new Bible
was reproduced hundreds were copied in
script area production lines turning out
handwritten copies
170 of these Bibles survived a huge
number for a 600 year old manuscript
which tells us there must have been
armies of people secretly transcribing
it hopping it and passing it all and
here it is the first English Bible verb
or easily copied out in perfect script
look at it the first thing that strikes
me is how like the Lindisfarne Gospels
it is the tradition went on of this book
you can fairly say it literally changed
the world and later for the sake of this
book hundreds will be martyred dying the
most horrible deaths but this was the
most radical cause of its day one some
sort worth dying for God's word in
English here it is in modern speech the
beginning God made of note heaven and
earth pursue the earth was idle and void
and darkness were on the face of depth
and the Spirit of God was born on the
waters and God said light be made and
light was made and God saw the light
that it was good and he departed the
light fro darkness and he kept the light
day and the darkness night
and the Eventide and Moreau tide was
made one day there was a problem with
with cliffs Bible he wasn't an easy
translation many familiar phrases do
have their origin here worries me an eye
for an eye and words such as barbarian
birthday Cala P child bearing
crowed communication crime dishonor Envy
frying-pan godly graven humanity injury
Jubilee lecture madness menstruate
middleman mountainous novelty oppressor
Philistine pollute puberty ramparts ISM
unfaithful visitor and zeal you
read them first in whip glyphs Bible
from the 13/8 days onwards but on the
whole Wickliffe and his team was so in
awe of the sacred nature of the Latin
scriptures that they did a translation
word-for-word even keeping the Latin
word order so it contains phrases like
Lord go from me for I am a man sinner
and I forsooth and the LORD thy God
strong jealous these were people still
nervous with their own language and
shows that it could carry the weight of
God's Word one result was that there are
over a thousand Latin words that turn up
for the first time in English whose use
in English is first recorded in
Wickliffe translation quite ordinary
ones like Emperor Justice profession
city cradle suddenly angel multitude and
glory a good word for this Bible this
was still a difficult language to wit
cliffs contemporaries but at least it
wasn't Latin
by the standards of the day it was the
bestseller the church condemned him for
it maintaining that he'd made the
scriptures more open to the readings of
lay men and women thus the jewel of the
clerics is turned to the sport of the
laity and the pearl of the gospel is
scattered abroad and trodden under foot
by swine
Wickliffe had begun to organize and
train what amounted to a new religious
order 'but inherent preachers whom he
dispatched around england
the purpose was to spread the word
literally in English it was like a
guerrilla campaign they were determined
to win the battle for God in the
highways byways taverns inns and village
greens they preached against Church
corruption and proclaimed Wickliffe
anti-clerical ideas they read from his
English Bible and then became known the
Lollards
the name might be derived from “lollaerd”
meaning weeds or from "lollen" to whisper
murmur or hum. They were a secret but
influential movement and hated by the
catholic establishment they went
straight to the source of God's teaching
and cut out the priests. Blessed be poor
men in spirit for the kingdom of heaven
is theirs blessed be mild men for they
shall wield the earth blessed be they
that mourn for they shall be comforted
this should be their that hunger and
thirst write wise for they shall be
fulfilled
blessed be merciful men for they shall
get mercy unless it be they that be of
clean heart for they shall see God
blessed be they that suffer persecution
for rightfulness for the kingdom of
heaven is theirs, so shine your light
before men that they see your good works
and glorify your father that is in
heaven
the church wasn't gonna stand for this
it cutted it's very authority on this
spot black friars in London on May the
17th 1382
a special Synod made up of eight bishops
various masters of theology doctors of
cannon and civil law and forty-five
friars met to examine wit cliffs works
it was a show trial. The conclusion was
preordained and two days into their
meeting they drafted a statement
condemning with cliffs pronouncements as
outright heresies. The Synod also
condemned Wycliffe’ associates (??). It
ordered the arrest and prosecution of
itinerant preachers throughout the land.
Eventually it secured a parliamentary
ban on all english-language Bibles on
the 30th of May that year the Synod
instructed every diocese to publish the
verdict Wickliffe became ill the stress
defeated him and he was paralyzed by a
stroke
two years later he died
Wickliffe death didn't signal the end of
the movement but afterwards lollards
were at constant risk of their lives
they met in hidden places especially in
Hereford and Monmouthshire they managed
to elude the agents of the church and
keep their faith alive one contemporary
chronicler said that every second man he
met was a Lala and they went all over
England luring great Nobles and lords to
their fold it's most unlikely that there
were that numerous but nevertheless this
was a national political movement and
its cause was the English language in
some of say some went soft was the song
he shocked me English food as he sheep
when but in a Meijer morning on Malvern
no illness me befell a fairly of fiery
this is the West Midlands dialect of
William Langland's Piers Plowman
it's a religious poem the most popular
poem and it's day. It's the first time we
know of but the English language was
used to express a personal Christian
spiritual vision and his evidence of a
native tradition that's a real and
growing alternative for the established
religious culture. Came to Langland in
the series of dreams
the first here on the Malvern hills  it's
written in a literate verse. Itself a
form which harks back to the old english
of Beowulf and it's an allegory of the
Christian life and of the contemporary
corruption of the Christian Church and
as he be honed into the east and a hey
to the sauna he saw a tool on a tuft
trail hairy market a date dollar bin
Eartha a dong Geun there in with the up
ditch and Derrick dreadful of sister a
fail felled full of Falk fondly there
between working and wandering as the
world asketh some puttin him to the
pluie play them for Selden in setting
and in sewing swung can fall harder he
found their Ferris all the for orders
preaching the peddler for profit of
heroin burrs glossing the Gospel as hem
goodly cthe for the parish priest and
the pardon are parted the silver that
the poor peddler of the parish should
have Eve that here new war
English here is being used to form
Magister literal language but one which
is an alternative to the received
authority passed down either through
French or Latin
this is plain speaking a plain folk it
seems to say this is real experience
this is the language of an individual
relationship with God.
It prefigures books like pilgrims
progress and Paradise Lost. It would be
stir the Pilgrim Fathers and in good
time become the Protestant language of
the English Reformation. But meanwhile
the church was not satisfied with with
Wycliffe's death it continued to burn Bibles
it burned people and in ordered Wycliffe
to be posthumously burned in 1414 the
most imposing council ever called by the
Catholic Church condemned Wickliffe as a
heretic and in the spring of 1428
ordered his bones to be exhumed and
removed from consecrated ground when the
primate of England looking on wit cliffs
remains were disinterred and burned by a
little bridge that spanned the river
Swift a tributary of the haver
his ashes were scattered into the stream
so officially the Bible remained in
Latin but there was a lollard prophecy of
the time which ran: The Avon to the Severn
runs, The Severn to the sea. And  the waters be.
Wycliffe’s dust shall spread abroad
Wide as
the waters be. The prophecy was right
English would eventually have its Bible
but the church would not give way before
the new force of English until the state
had buckled first the battle for an
English Bible was a battle literally of
the soul of England but before it could
be won the heart and mind of the country
had to be persuaded to and that process
began here in 1417 in France with Henry
the fifth
right trusty and well-beloved brother
right worshipful fathers in God and
trusty and well-beloved for as much as
we know well your desire were to hear
joyful tidings of our good speed we
signify unto you that of our labor has
sent good conclusion in the early 15th
century Henry was campaigning around
northern France winning French territory
and famous battles especially dodging
kur it seems a small thing but it was of
quite extraordinary significance that
after his victory henry v broke with 350
years of royal tradition and wrote his
dispatches home in english this was an
astute move English Kings had begun to
speak English unto his father Henry the
fourth but all court documents had
hitherto been written in French as they
had been since the Norman Conquest
Henry's English letters are deliberate
pieces of propaganda to be spread
throughout the land here's his letter
announcing peace upon Monday the 20th
day of May we arrived in this town tois
and the Accord of the peace perpetual
was here sworn by the Duke of Burgundy
and semblable by us in our own name
the letters forthwith sealed under the
Great Seal copies of which we send to be
proclaimed in our city of London and
through all our realm that our people
may have knowledge thereof for their
consolation signed Henry by the grace of
God King of England
Henri's motives may have been the
exploitation of anti-french fervor but
once he returned from the campaigns he
continued to write in English and in
doing so he made the first major step
towards the creation of an official
standardized English that everybody
could read. The houses of parliament
where I am now are also called the
Palace of Westminster that's a reminder
that on this site the kings of England
wanted their principal London residence
this Hall is all that survived the Great
Fire and somewhere around here when the
king was in residence would have been
the first circle of his government this
is called the signet office it wrote
personal letters on behalf of the
monarch which carried the Royal Seal and
in ways familiar to us today once Henry
decreed that the signet office should
use English it was inevitable that the
rest of the country would come to do the
same
the problem was which English across the
country people still spoke a mass of
different dialects and would have had
trouble understanding one another for
instance the word "stian" or "stane" in the
north was stone in the south the "ing"
participle as in "running" was said as "and"
in the north and "ende" in the East Midlands
and "inde" in the West Midlands so running
could also be said as "runninde" "runnand"
and "runnende". But that was nothing
compared to the variety of spellings in
use because England had traditionally
used French or Latin as its written
languages had never been any need to
agree on a common linguistic standard or
even how to spell particular words but
now there was take the word Church for
instance one of the most common and
important in a language in the north of
England it was commonly called a cook
while the South used Church however Kirk
could be spelt KYR k KY r ke ke IR ke ke
e RK k IRC and ke r ke Church was
variously CH u r CH e CH ER c AG t h ir
CH e CH ER c h CH y RC
h CH p RG e g hy r CH e and SC hy r CH e
fortunately from the languages point of
view there was a big engine of state
that could deal with this unruly tongue
it was the chance really reduced the
Chancery the civil service of the day
because it was crucial that a document
produced in London could be read in
Carlisle we needed a common written
language this is the public records
office were the official documents of
the 15th century are kept
as Chancery began to use the English
language it had to make hundreds of
decisions about which form of a word on
which spelling to adopt we don't know
how these choices were made but we do
know that they stuck thousands of
documents were painstakingly written out
and sent all over the country many had
legal status so they had to be exact and
consistent. And under the influence of
Chancery the language starts to look
more modern and more even words like any
but many not such ought and even I
previously I Chi CH he had also been
allowed find their modern forms at
Chancery lond
becomes land and church Kirk and all the
others become Church during the decade
1469 to 1479
alone for instance the modern word
shell starts as Excel then shall and
finally settles into its modern form
shall the word arrived becomes right
half and doth become has and does by
fifteen hundred under the influence of
Chancery the language is becoming
recognizable to us
anything else in common with yours
King internet imagine e^x some edge of I
and s anyway no why is there a reason
why it will end in different ending it's
just the English language it's a very
good answer okay but just because
everyone began to spell the same way it
didn't mean the language became any more
logical look at this why English is so
hard
we'll begin with the box and the plural
is boxes but the plural of ox is oxen
not boxes so one file is goose butter
called geese you may find a lone mouse
or a whole load of mice but the plural
of houses houses not pice if the plural
of man is always and why shouldn't the
plural of pan be cold pen and it goes on
and it goes on and it goes on what's the
poet trying to tell us the English is
confusing hands of you agree with Allah
okay hands down
ask any foreigner in fact ask any pupil
about mastering English spelling and
it's in consistence isn't they'll say
what have we done to deserve this
a lot of it is just to do the mother or
nature of English and a lot of it is to
do with accidents of usage from
centuries ago but some of it was
deliberate hands up if you think that
English is so hard to learn around the
time English was being standardized by
Chancery that was much debate about the
best way to spell things broadly there
were reformers who wanted to spell words
according to the way they were
pronounced and traditionalists who
wanted to spell them in one of the ways
that always be okay the traditionalists
one confusing because silent is fine
they couldn't help tampering though and
a desire to make the route of the
language more evident words that had
ended English from French for instance
were given a Latin look the letter B was
inserted into debt and doubt the letter
C
individuals words that were thought to
be of Greek origin sometimes had their
spelling adjusted so that throne and
theatre acquired their age rhyme on the
other hand was given an age just because
rhythm had one even though it's
etymologically absurd on a similar
principle and L was inserted in court
because it becomes silent but it was
still present ensured and would the same
with h words like "whole" were and
"whelk". unlike anybody who tries to
rationalize English they really messed
it up you feel confused if you just like
me
okay let's carry on it's not going to
look at the second first okay
the cow is a plural maybe mouse or kind,
but the plural above is there's not fine
as I see off first and you show me your
feet
okay right you can all stand there I've
got the point
let's go as if to prove the folly of
trying to bring reason into the language
the English promptly decided to
pronounce everything differently anyway
around this time and nobody really knows
why a sea change took place in the way
English sounds this is called the great
vowel shift and in happen comparatively
quickly we think a generation or two
before it English was pronounced in a
way that sounds foreign to us now "might"
used to sound rather like today's meet
which in turn was said something like
MIT so the sentence I might go and buy
some meat once sounded like I'm eat go
and buy some meat that was the great
vowel shift it made 15th century English
recognizable in the modern era but it
didn't change the spelling what really
gives all languages their uniformity is
of course writing and what gives writing
is huge modern power is the invention
and spread of printing printing was
invented in Gutenberg Germany around
1435 it's often regarded as the most
seismic technological change Western
culture has gone through printing marks
the beginning of the Information Age
it's extraordinary looking at this
simple piece of technology to think of
what a revolution had brought about this
isn't 15th century but it worked in
exactly the same way and because this
device made it easy to manufacture books
in large numbers it became very hard
indeed to control the spread of ideas
and print favored the language of the
people
English was pressed into service and
although Latin was still the language of
religion and scholarship when Caxton
introduced printing to england he got
straight on with making books in english
Chaucer's Canterbury Tales and Mallory's
tales of King Arthur ways bestsellers
but English was still a fluid and
regionally difficult monster and Caxton
worried about how to achieve a common
standard that will be understood and
read by all certainly it is hard to
place everyman because of diversity and
sean's of language for in these days
every man will utter his comunicación in
such terms that few man shall understand
today but in my judgment the common
terms that be daily used been lighter to
be understand than the older and on
siient English Caxton tells us that he
is translating Virgil from a French
version but he doesn't know which
English word to use for eggs he tells a
story of some merchants from
Northumberland who are away from home
and visit the house in Kent to buy food
one asks the woman for egg is she tells
him she doesn't speak French another ask
for the same thing with a different
plural errand which means eggs in the
dialect of Kent and he gets them so
which word should Caxton choose for his
translation he settles for egg is
and so now do we so it's printers as
much as teachers and writers who decide
on a lot of words and their Spelling's
and although it was writers like Chaucer
and Wickliffe would establish the
dominant dialect it was Caxton's
publications that consolidated the
game's gains which would eventually be
made permanent by the English Bible
which in Tudor times thanks to printing
reached everyone who could read the
scene was set for the creation of
probably the most influential book
that's ever been in the history of
language English or any other
early in the reign of Henry of the
eighth the new king was still promising
the Pope to burn any untrue translations
he meant Wycliffe's Bible relentlessly
circulating in hand-copied editions and
he set his Lord Chancellor Cardinal
Wolsey to hunt down and burn all
heretical books on the 12th of May 1521
a huge bonfire of confiscated heretical
works is made outside the original sand
Paul's Cathedral it was said that the
flames burned for two days that same
year a young man who was Oxford educated
and an ordained priest became tutor to a
large household in little Sodbury
Gloucestershire where he started to
preach in the common place called st.
Austin's Greene in front of the church
his name was William Tyndale and his
Bible was to bring about a radical
change within the English language and
in English society he's had more
influence on the way we speak that
anyone except Shakespeare and he had to
leave the country to do it
Tyndale was in the mold of Wickliffe 100
years on to a cleric who challenged him
II answered her many years I will cause
a boy that drive the plow to know more
of the scriptures than thou dost you may
say he finished with this business
he believed passionately in an English
fun
in 1524 age 29 Tyndall left England
never to return he settled in Cologne
and began the work of translating the
New Testament into English not from
Latin but from the original Hebrew and
Greek by 1526 6,000 copies had been
printed abroad and were about to be
smuggled into England Henry aids and
Cardinal Wolsey who spies had alerted
them were terrified of this perceived
threat and the whole country was put on
alert naval ships patrolled the coastal
waters boats were stopped and searched
and a great many of the Bibles were
intercepted for the state this was a
serious struggle Latin was the language
not only of God but the state's
authority arrested on it too the enemy
had to be beaten off an enemy that would
eventually give the English language so
magnificently to the English people
but first tens and then hundreds of
these Bibles began to get through the
Bishop of London tried a love attack he
sought to buy the entire print run
through an intermediary oh he will burn
them Tyndale the submersed have said
when he heard this well I am the gladder
but I shall get the money of him for
these books and the whole world for cry
out upon the burning of God's Word and
that's what happened the bishop bought
and burnt his books and Tyndall used the
money to prepare and print a better
version at Church expense and this is
what the conflict was about a Bible for
the people in their spoken language
blessed are the poor in spirit for
theirs is the kingdom of heaven blessed
be they that mourn for they shall be
comforted blessed are the meek for they
shall inherit the earth
blessed are they which hunger and thirst
for righteousness for they shall be
filled
blessed are the merciful for they shall
obtain mercy blessed are the pure in
heart for they shall see God
blessed are the peacemakers for they
shall be called the children of God
blessed are they which suffer
persecution for righteousness sake for
theirs is the kingdom of heaven ye are
the salt of the earth it's hard it's
impossible to overpraise the quality of
Tyndall's writing its rhythmical beauty
its simplicity of phrase has penetrated
deep into the bedrock of english as we
still know today Tyndall's work form 85%
of the later King James Bible the one we
all know and we all use his phrase is
still scapegoat
let there be light the powers that be my
brother's keeper filthy lucre fight the
good fight sick unto death flowing with
milk and honey the apple of my eye a man
after my own heart the Spirit is willing
but the flesh is weak sign of the times
ye of little faith eat drink and be
merry brokenhearted clear-eyed and
hundreds and hundreds more words like
beautiful fishermen landlady seashore
stumbling book taskmaster two-edged
Viper zealous and even Jehovah and
Passover come to us from Tyndale by this
stage in the adventure of English we're
coming across words that carry our ideas
and emotions and feelings even today
words that not only tell us about the
external world we live in but about the
inner nature of our condition then God
said let there be light
and God saw the light and that it was
good and he divided the light from the
darkness and called the light day and
the darkness night and so of the evening
and morning was made the first day
before long there were thousands of
copies of Tyndall's Bible in England in
his happy phrase the noise of the new
Bible echoed throughout the country
produced in a small pocket-sized
addition that was easily concealed it
passed through the cities and
universities into the hands of even the
humblest men and women the authorities
especially Thomas More still railed
against him for putting the fire of
Scripture into the language of our
bodies but the damage was done the
English had their English Bible legal or
not
the hunt for $10 continued viable in
1535 to hide assassins and trapped him
in Andhra and smuggled him out of the
city to Vil vodka cell where he was
imprisoned in his last letter Tyndall
asked that he might have a warmer cap
for I suffer greatly from the cold a
warmer coat also for what I have is very
thin a piece of cloth with which to
patch my leggings and I asked to be
allowed to have a lamp in the evening
for it is wearisome to sit alone in the
dark but most of all I beg and beseech
your clemency that the commissary will
kindly permit me to have my Hebrew Bible
grammar and dictionary a time I continue
with my work.
And continued his work he did phrases
like a prophet has no honor in his own
country a stranger in a strange land a
law unto themselves we live and move and
have our being and let my people go all
come from Tyndall's pen. In August 1536
Tindall was found guilty of heresy by a
court in the Netherlands and on October
the 6th he was strangled then burned at
the stake his last words were Lord
opened the king of England's eyes in
fact events had already opened the Kings
eyes Henry the Eighth had tried to
divorce Catherine of Aragon and that had
brought him into confrontation with the
Pope now he too was opposed to papal
supremacy Henry's mood had changed and
scripture was suddenly more important in
church authority
Thomas Moore had been executed for
refusing to see things the Kings way and
his new advisors Thomas Cromwell and
Thomas Cranmer keen to keep their heads
moved on ecclesiastical reform
and that reform came with the split from
Rome and the English Reformation now
England needed the scriptures to be
available in its own tongue English was
to become at last the language of power
Henry's change of mind came too late to
save Tyndall even supposing he gave his
fate any thought at all but by the time
of Tyndall's martyrdom Henry had already
authorized this Coverdale Bible which
was translated from the German and was
the first legal Bible in England that
was in 1535 in 1537 Matthew's Bible and
amalgam of covered airs and Kindles was
allowed to be printed in England in 1539
we have the great Bible designs to be
the official version for newly
Protestant England and to be placed in
every parish church in the land after
centuries of suppression three Bibles
are approved and published inside six
years and he goes on the Geneva Bible
the bishops Bible the Rheims Bible the
English language has suddenly flowered
it's already returned to the palaces of
Port and state like this one Lambeth
Palace in London it's again become the
language of a vivid and vigorous
national literature and now with the
split from Rome its Concord the last and
highest Bastion the church it was the
spirit of Protestantism that the Bible
be available to everyone in 1530 thomas
moore had ranted about the shame of it
being read by Plowboys
but the great Bible of 1540 came with a
preface by more successive farmer which
commended it to all
here may men wing young old learn and
unlearn at rich or priests lame and
Lords ladies officers tenants and mean
men virgins wives widows lawyers
merchants artifices husbands and all
manner of persons of what a state or
conditions however they be learn all
things what they ought to believe what
they ought to do as well as concerning
Almighty God as themselves all others
and so we've come full circle where the
medieval Catholic Church kept the Bible
from the people Henry's new church set
out to get the Bible to as many people
as possible it's had an extraordinary
influence on the spread of our language
by the end of the sixteenth century
there were so many competing versions
that King James the first ordered a
standardized version which we now know
as a King James Bible of 1611 the
writers drew on all the previous
versions but mostly on Tyndall's
interestingly they made no attempt to
update the language that was now 80
years old so even though by 1611 English
had undergone further revolution the
King James translators would still use
room sometimes for you as in ye cannot
serve God and Mammon even though nobody
said ye in common speech anymore
they use thou for you gut forgot spake
for spoke and so on
in other words the King James Version
was deliberately archaic even then and
that's part of its extraordinary power
it was designed to feel as if it had the
authority and resonance of speech from
the past it was meant to sound ancient
antique like the very words of God
and above all the men who made this
version listened to their final drafts
being read aloud over and over again and
altered them accordingly
so that they had the right rhythm and
balance
this makes the authorized English Bible
par excellence a preachers Bible it was
written to be spoken to be heard to be
understood it was written to spread the
word English at last had got on its side
the language was authorized by the
Almighty Himself in the beginning was
the word and the Word was with God and
the Word was God
the same was in the beginning with God
all things were made by him and without
him was not anything made that was made
in him was life and the life was the
light of men and the light shine earth
in darkness and the darkness
comprehended it not and the Word was
made flesh and dwelt among us
you